<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>Background to PMTCT
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>
			HIV and AIDS have caused untold harm and human suffering globally. Over 90% of
			<lb/>
			people infected with this deadly virus live in sub-Saharan Africa including Malawi. In
			<lb/>
			Malawi, the prevalence of HIV among the child bearing age group <ref type="biblio">(15 -49</ref>) is
			estimated
			<lb/>
			to be at 14% and close to a million people have already died of AIDS related conditions
			<lb/>
			<ref type="biblio">(MDHS, 2004</ref>). Women and children are more affected than the rest of the general
			<lb/>
			population. HIV infection in children below 15 years is largely due to mother to child
			<lb/>
			transmission (MTCT). Worldwide, over 2 million children have got infected through
			<lb/>
			MTCT <ref type="biblio">(UNAIDS, 2008)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The high prevalence of HIV among the women is contributed by multiple factors. The
			<lb/>
			factors that are responsible for the proliferation of HIV and AIDS in these women include
			<lb/>
			tradition, gender inequalities, biological make up, inadequate coverage of health care in
			<lb/>
			some areas, distance, failure of women to negotiate on matters regarding sex and poverty
			<lb/>
			among others. It is estimated that 18% of the pregnant women in Malawi are infected
			<lb/>
			with HIV and this prevalence is relatively high in urban areas as it ranges from 19 -30%
			<lb/>
			<ref type="biblio">(MDHS, 2004)</ref>. As a result of this, mother to child transmission of HIV becomes an
			area
			<lb/>
			of concern and calls for the prevention of mother to child transmission of HIV (PMTCT).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>PMTCT was first introduced in 2001 into the ANC as an international initiative and then
			<lb/>
			was adopted by different countries in Africa <ref type="biblio">(WHO, 2006; Druce and Nolan, 2007)</ref>.
			The
			<lb/>
			primary aim of the PMTCT programme as put in the guidelines was to decrease the
			<lb/>
			number of HIV infected babies born to HIV positive mothers. Primary prevention of HIV
			<lb/>
			infection particularly among women of childbearing age has always been the backbone of
			<lb/>
			the programme. It is believed that without intervention, up to 50% of babies born from
			<lb/>
			HIV positive women get infected through labour, delivery and breast feeding. A number
			<lb/>
			of interventions have been aimed at limiting the risk of newborn infections during
			<lb/>
			delivery, such as caesarian section as the mode of delivery and administering
			<lb/>
			antiretroviral (ARV) drugs prepartum and peripartum and providing alternatives to
			<lb/>
			breastfeeding. However, all these approaches are not always possible in developing
			<lb/>
			countries and the relative importance of ARV drugs, in particular nevirapine (NVP), has
			<lb/>
			been investigated <ref type="biblio">(Sullivan, 2003; Volmink et al., 2007)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>HIV testing starting with &apos;opt-in&apos; strategy was introduced in PMTCT programmes in
			<lb/>
			2001 following international initiatives, with efforts to reduce MTCT. Opt-in strategy is
			<lb/>
			an approach whereby all clients are encouraged to undergo voluntary counseling and
			<lb/>
			testing (VCT) at their own will (<ref type="biblio">Perez et al., 2006</ref>). Later, opt-out strategy was
			adopted
			<lb/>
			by many countries in sub-Saharan Africa <ref type="biblio">(CDC, 2004</ref>). The aim was to enable all
			<lb/>
			pregnant women to be screened for HIV infection. Screening should occur after a woman
			<lb/>
			is notified that HIV screening is recommended for all pregnant women and that she will
			<lb/>
			receive an HIV test as part of the routine panel of prenatal tests unless she declines (opt-<lb/>out
			screening) (<ref type="biblio">Bajunirwe and Muzoora, 2005)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>PMTCT programmes adopted different policies to ensure successful intervention of the
			<lb/>
			programmes. In 2002, the MTCT-plus Initiative was established which aimed to move
			<lb/>
			beyond interventions to prevent infant HIV infection. It does this by supporting the
			<lb/>
			provision of specialized care to HIV-infected women, their partners and their children
			<lb/>
			who are identified in MTCT programmes <ref type="biblio">(WHO, 2003; Iliff et al, 2005</ref>).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Much attention has been given to the ARV prophylaxis in developing countries.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Commonly a single dose of nevirapine 200 mg administered to a woman at the onset of
			<lb/>
			labour and a similar drug but in syrup form given to the child within 72 hours after
			<lb/>
			delivery reduces infection by 38 -50% <ref type="biblio">(Scarlatti, 2004</ref>). The single use of
			nevirapine as
			<lb/>
			prophylaxis in PMTCT has been recommended by the World Health Organization
			<lb/>
			(WHO) and widely adopted by many poor resource countries particularly those in sub-<lb/>Saharan Africa. The
			common availability of nevirapine and its simplicity in
			<lb/>
			administration including the fact that it is cheap with fewer side effects make it
			<lb/>
			acceptable, accessible and affordable in poor resource settings. However, the single use
			<lb/>
			of nevirapine as prophylaxis in PMTCT programmes has been associated with the
			<lb/>
			development of resistance at some stages in the lives of women who eventually receive
			<lb/>
			antiretroviral treatment <ref type="biblio">(Lallemant et al., 2004</ref>). It is for this reason that
			combined
			<lb/>
			regimen has been adopted although at the time of conducting the study; nevirapine only
			<lb/>
			was being used in PMTCT.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>PMTCT at Malamulo
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Malamulo PMTCT programme was started in July 2004 as part of a national initiative to
			<lb/>
			protect more HIV positive pregnant women from transmitting HIV to their babies. With a
			<lb/>
			catchment population of 70,000, it was observed that more pregnant women who came to
			<lb/>
			Malamulo hospital for the antenatal care tested HIV positive and this was the same at
			<lb/>
			national level. As a Christian Health Association of Malawi (CHAM) unit, Malamulo
			<lb/>
			hospital is supported by Malawi Government&apos;s Ministry of Health though CHAM like
			<lb/>
			any other faith based health facility in Malawi. Malamulo hospital is owned by the
			<lb/>
			Seventh Day Adventist Church.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>
			Both curative and preventive services are offered by this hospital and the integrated
			<lb/>
			approach is used to run the preventive services. The services include; voluntary
			<lb/>
			counseling and testing (VCT) and synonymously called HIV testing and counseling
			<lb/>
			(HTC), management of sexually transmitted infections (STIs), home based care (HBC),
			<lb/>
			youth friendly health services (YFHS), family planning (FP), prevention of mother to
			<lb/>
			child transmission (PMTCT) of HIV, provision of ARVs, nutrition, static and outreach
			<lb/>
			mother and child health (MCH) services. Over the study period, the project was largely
			<lb/>
			funded by USAID through local and international NGOs called Umoyo Network and
			<lb/>
			later Private Agencies Collaborating Together (PACT Malawi) respectively among other
			<lb/>
			donors.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>At that time Malamulo hospital HIV testing services adopted an opt-in approach whereby
			<lb/>
			women accessed HIV testing after receiving information if they wished to do so. The
			<lb/>
			HIV testing was done at one central point and this was in the out-patient department
			<lb/>
			(OPD). Therefore, women in the antenatal care were routinely referred to OPD for HIV
			<lb/>
			testing after accessing all the necessary antenatal care. However, it was observed that not
			<lb/>
			all antenatal women accessed HIV testing in the OPD regardless of being referred to the
			<lb/>
			services and many were lost in the process. It was due to this that HIV testing was
			<lb/>
			integrated in the antenatal care as a local initiative so as to capture more women in March
			<lb/>
			2005.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In January 2006, opt-out (routine) HIV testing was started and by this approach, more
			<lb/>
			antenatal women accessed HIV testing in the same way they accessed other routine
			<lb/>
			antenatal investigations and consequently joined PMTCT programme. Unfortunately,
			<lb/>
			maternal services at that time were payable, so much as more antenatal women accessed
			<lb/>
			HIV testing and joined PMTCT programme, quite a small proportion of them completed
			<lb/>
			full antenatal care and delivered in the hospital.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In October 2006 free maternal care was introduced at Malamulo also as a national
			<lb/>
			initiative to capture and help more marginalized women access maternal care and
			<lb/>
			consequently reduce preventable maternal and infant mortality.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>It is only Malamulo hospital that offers comprehensive PMTCT package in the catchment
			<lb/>
			area. All antenatal women who test HIV positive are routinely registered into the PMTCT
			<lb/>
			programme. These HIV positive women are then subjected to the prescribed PMTCT
			<lb/>
			package and this comprises of the following; provision of antiretroviral prophylaxis
			<lb/>
			(nevirapine) with advice to be taken at the onset of labour and the child to get the same
			<lb/>
			drug in syrup form within 72 hours after delivery, to access hospital delivery and to
			<lb/>
			exclusively breast feed the child for six months. The consequences of home delivery as
			<lb/>
			well as hospital delivery in relation to PMTCT programme are explained to these women
			<lb/>
			to understand why it is important for them to make informed choices. If eligible the
			<lb/>
			woman is provided with long term antiretroviral treatment. There is also provision of
			<lb/>
			supplementary feeds to the women and their infants when necessary, provision of
			<lb/>
			cotrimoxazole to the infants as prophylaxis.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Further, these women are encouraged to come with their husbands so that they can access
			<lb/>
			HIV testing as couples. After delivery, women and their infants are followed up to 18
			<lb/>
			months when babies&apos; HIV status is determined. HIV negative babies at 18 months are
			<lb/>
			discharged from PMTCT programme and the HIV positive ones are then subjected to
			<lb/>
			comprehensive care and investigations such as CD4 counts, hemoglobin, and continuous
			<lb/>
			provision of cotrimoxazole as prophylaxis for chest infections and depending on the
			<lb/>
			levels of CD4 counts, these infants are put on long term general antiretroviral treatment.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Why operational research?
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The overall aim of the study was to study the demand and adherence to key components
			<lb/>
			of the PMTCT programme.
			<lb/>
			A good number of researches continue to be done in various fields but much of their
			<lb/>
			applicability remains questionable and if anything they end up in book shelves and an
			<lb/>
			award of academic credentials thereof. This study took a different direction all together in
			<lb/>
			that not only did it suffice the requirements but also paved a way to improve the reality
			<lb/>
			on the ground. It is as a result of this that positive consequences of service delivery
			<lb/>
			regarding its acceptability, accessibility as well as affordability by the marginalized rural
			<lb/>
			communities have been explored.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>The conducted research in a nutshell
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>This study employed a mixture of both quantitative and qualitative approaches. Data
			<lb/>
			sources included antenatal care (ANC), PMTCT and delivery registers, structured
			<lb/>
			questionnaires, in-depth interviews with HIV positive women in the programme and
			<lb/>
			focus group discussions with community members, health care workers and traditional
			<lb/>
			birth attendants.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Three interventions were introduced in the antenatal care (ANC) at the hospital at
			<lb/>
			different times. These were HIV testing integrated in the ANC clinic in March 2005, opt-<lb/>out testing in
			January 2006 and free maternal services in October 2006. A steady increase
			<lb/>
			of the service uptake as interventions were being introduced was observed over time.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>HIV testing was generally accepted by the community and women within the
			<lb/>
			programme. However positive HIV tests among pregnant women were also experienced
			<lb/>
			to cause conflicts and fear within the family. Although hospital deliveries were
			<lb/>
			recognized to be safe and clean, home deliveries were common. Lack of transport, spouse
			<lb/>
			support and negative attitudes among staff were some of the underlying factors
			<ref type="biblio">(Kasenga,
				<lb/>
				2009)
			</ref>
			.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Research triggered actions
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>As a result of this study, the following consequences were arrived at; Ever since PMTCT
			<lb/>
			programme got started at Malamulo hospital, very few marginalized women actually
			<lb/>
			accessed hospital delivery services despite attending ANC due to financial constraints.
			<lb/>
			Coincidentally, with long standing lobbying with Malawi Government through its
			<lb/>
			Ministry of Health and district health office (DHO), free maternal care was introduced in
			<lb/>
			October 2006. Good proportions of women in general as well as those in the PMTCT
			<lb/>
			programme now do access maternity care. This has also beefed up the uptake of HIV
			<lb/>
			testing, antiretroviral prophylaxis for the HIV positive women and their infants as well as
			<lb/>
			access to general long-term antiretroviral treatment. This has created an opportunity to
			<lb/>
			scale up the programme and improve the quality of care given as has been commented by
			<lb/>
			other authors <ref type="biblio">(Pai and Klein 2009)</ref>. It is clear that apart from financial constraint as a
			<lb/>
			barrier, there are also other challenges that prevent women from accessing the services at
			<lb/>
			the hospital.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Negative attitude of health workers was observed as one of the barriers that prevent
			<lb/>
			women from accessing maternity care. Pregnant women in delivery suits would like to be
			<lb/>
			treated as human beings with respect and dignity, an observation which was echoed as
			<lb/>
			missing among some of the midwives at the health facility&apos;s labour ward. The same
			<lb/>
			women preferred home delivery with the assistance of traditional birth attendants to
			<lb/>
			hospital delivery due to the warm reception the traditional birth attendants accord them.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Previous successful home delivery experiences, provision of warm bath, porridge, respect
			<lb/>
			and dignity to the women before and after delivery were said to be some of the
			<lb/>
			motivating factors for the women to continue having home deliveries. After debriefing
			<lb/>
			the study findings to the management, strategies were developed to improve on this. All
			<lb/>
			the health workers were involved and issues such as increased workload, less experience
			<lb/>
			in labour ward and tradition among other factors, were named as contributing factors to
			<lb/>
			negative attitude of health care staff. In response to this the management came up with
			<lb/>
			the following strategies:
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<list>
			<item> Suggestion box was put in maternity ward for the women and interested parties
				<lb/>
				to put in their aspirations. These suggestion boxes are reviewed monthly to
				<lb/>
				respond to the issues as they arise.
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item> Monthly and yearly ward performance competitions began so that the best ward
				<lb/>
				receives an award as a token of appreciation. There is a committee which has
				<lb/>
				been set up to handle this activity.
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item> Best health worker of the year for each department and should receive awards.
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item> General staff meetings organised by the management through the human
				<lb/>
				resources&apos; office to handle personnel issues including staff attitude to patients in
				<lb/>
				general. In such meetings people expressed their opinions and what ought to be
				<lb/>
				done to improve the situation. Also staffing issues in such meetings were being
				<lb/>
				tackled as health workers expressed concern that they were understaffed.
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item> The matron&apos;s office took an active role in seeing to it that nurses and midwives
				<lb/>
				performed their duties in accordance with their profession and routine meetings
				<lb/>
				were held relating to this.
				<lb/>
			</item>
		</list>
		
		<p>Minimal male involvement in reproductive health care was as well long observed right at
			<lb/>
			the inception of the programme. This observation was contrary to the fact that men in this
			<lb/>
			study decided for their wives where to access maternal care. It is important to note that
			<lb/>
			traditional tendencies in the study area are enshrined in paternalistic approaches, as such
			<lb/>
			whatever men decide is firmly held by the general communities particularly women.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>From the time immemorial until the turn of the century, it has been very uncommon to
			<lb/>
			see men participating actively in the reproductive health services or rather mother and
			<lb/>
			child health (MCH) services in general. This has for a long time disadvantaged not only
			<lb/>
			women and the children but also men themselves resulting into poor understanding and
			<lb/>
			acceptability of different health issues and family break ups particularly when health
			<lb/>
			matters in question require both couples to take actions.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<list>
			<item>Based on the study findings, the hospital management through community medicine
				<lb/>
				department developed the following strategies to positively address this challenge;
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item> Women in the ANC to be encouraged to come with their spouses to PMTCT and
				<lb/>
				ANC services in general and to participate in what is called &apos;couple
				<lb/>
				counselling&apos;before and after undergoing HIV testing.
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item> Men to be encouraged to come with under five children to the health facility for
				<lb/>
				screening, immunisation, growth monitoring just as women routinely do.
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item> If a man comes alone to the health facility with a sick child or joins his wife to
				<lb/>
				access ANC he ought not to be in the queues.
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item> Males may be encouraged to accompany their wives to the labour ward to see and
				<lb/>
				support their wives as they undergo delivery experiences. This is optional as this
				<lb/>
				issue is culturally sensitive and few men wish to participate in this way.
				<lb/>
			</item>
		</list>
		
		<p>To enforce this, routine meetings with men and women, village headmen and faith based
			<lb/>
			leaders continue to be conducted in the communities. In addition, the district health office
			<lb/>
			(DHO), various non governmental organisations and funding agencies including USAID
			<lb/>
			through Private Agencies Collaborating Together (PACT Malawi) which funded the
			<lb/>
			activities in the study area supported the male involvement initiative. However, it is
			<lb/>
			encouraging to note that currently, over 10% of women who come to the health facility
			<lb/>
			are now being accompanied by their husbands, a move which was not there before.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The provision of antiretroviral prophylaxis (nevirapine) which was given to the women in
			<lb/>
			the PMTCT programme at 32 weeks and above is now given at the first contact with the
			<lb/>
			woman during the antenatal care. This is because, it was observed that when nevirapine
			<lb/>
			was being given in late pregnancy, there were lots of missing opportunities as some
			<lb/>
			women could deliver at home or on the way to the hospital before accessing the
			<lb/>
			antiretroviral prophylaxis. This as well resulted into babies not accessing nevirapine as
			<lb/>
			per PMTCT programme protocol. Therefore, early administration of antiretroviral
			<lb/>
			prophylaxis to women in the PMTCT programme, has improved the accessibility of the
			<lb/>
			services.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The study further explored the opportunities of maximising the various resources at
			<lb/>
			different levels namely; health workers at facility, health surveillance assistants (HSAs)
			<lb/>
			from the district health office who work both at the health facility as well as at the
			<lb/>
			community levels. In addition opinion leaders such as village headmen, faith based
			<lb/>
			leaders and community volunteers at community levels were some of the resources that
			<lb/>
			were utilized and provided a way of possible decentralisation of the services so as to
			<lb/>
			widely reach a good proportion of the population within the studied facility&apos;s catchment
			<lb/>
			area.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The involvement of TBAs in maternity care has always been a contentious issue although
			<lb/>
			their home delivery services can not be completely ruled out. There are trained TBAs in
			<lb/>
			the area who conduct normal deliveries with minimal or no complications but there has as
			<lb/>
			well been a thin line between those who can afford to refer some of the cases they can not
			<lb/>
			manage and those who can not. It has also been not clear to establish number of women
			<lb/>
			who deliver at the home of trained and untrained TBAs as some of the TBAs do conduct
			<lb/>
			their services in secrecy. Although the Malawi Government recognises their participation
			<lb/>
			in maternal health but it is clear that their services can be potentially harmful to some of
			<lb/>
			the women particularly those at risk. It is as a result of this that officially home delivery
			<lb/>
			with the assistance of the TBAs is being discouraged and this calls for all women to
			<lb/>
			access maternal care at the health facility.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Conclusions and recommendations
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Based on the study findings, the following were concluded and recommended; increased
			<lb/>
			accessibility and utilisation of maternity care can as well potentially increase the
			<lb/>
			coverage of PMTCT services. Free maternity care removes partly the economic
			<lb/>
			constraints that prevent marginalised women from accessing the services. Similarly, the
			<lb/>
			integration of services into ANC increased the women&apos;s uptake of HIV testing and
			<lb/>
			hospital delivery influenced women&apos;s adherence to antiretroviral prophylaxis (NVP).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Both women as well as the community in general supported institutional delivery.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Further, by encouraging hospital delivery and male involvement, more PMTCT women
			<lb/>
			are likely to adhere to the PMTCT programme and consequently reduce MTCT of HIV.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Further studies on the quality of care offered in the presence of increased service uptake,
			<lb/>
			estimation of true programme coverage and effectiveness are required. Policy makers as
			<lb/>
			well as potential donors need to come up with interventions that have positive effects for
			<lb/>
			the disadvantaged communities. Operational research provides an opportunity for health
			<lb/>
			care institutions to optimise the local implementation of programmes like PMTCT. The
			<lb/>
			provision of such research skills should be encouraged by MOHP and donor
			<lb/>
			organisations. Service providers at facility and community levels, policy makers at all
			<lb/>
			levels, all stakeholders and the communities should see themselves as partners in
			<lb/>
			development and should work together to reduce preventable maternal and infant
			<lb/>
			mortality including MTCT of HIV.
		</p>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
