<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>The second decade
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The challenges in global health have always been complex and multifaceted. They will be
			<lb/>
			even more so in the next ten years. Disease patterns will continue to evolve, new and re-<lb/>emerging
			diseases will combine with shifting demographics and changing lifestyles to
			<lb/>
			raise substantial questions about how to protect and promote people&apos;s health and how to
			<lb/>
			care for them when they are sick. In this changing environment INDEPTH will need to
			<lb/>
			make strategic choices around four issues:
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<list>
			<item>1. Identifying and moving forward priority research areas
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				2. Building research capacities
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				3. Developing and implementing research standards
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				4. Translating research results into action
				<lb/>
			</item>
		</list>
		
		<head>1. Identifying and moving forward priority research areas
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>INDEPTH&apos;s longitudinal health and demographic surveillance, in some sites dating back
			<lb/>
			several decades, is unique in public health. In considering its options for the next ten
			<lb/>
			years, INDEPTH should strive to exploit the full range of research possibilities provided
			<lb/>
			by this ongoing, comprehensive compilation of data. A structure for classifying research
			<lb/>
			priorities is provided by the World Health Organization (WHO) research priorities
			<lb/>
			framework, which identifies five types of research that are pertinent to any given health
			<lb/>
			need (<ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The five research axes describe a continuous cycle, comprising:
			<lb/>
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				i. Measuring the dimensions and nature of health problems
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item>
				<lb/>
				ii. Understanding the causes of problems; the determinants of health and ill-<lb/>health
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item>
				<lb/>
				iii. Developing solutions to address the problems
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item>
				<lb/>
				iv. Translating the actions and delivering solutions
				<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item>
				<lb/>
				v. Evaluating the effectiveness of the solutions.
				<lb/>
			</item>
		</list>
		
		<p>Using this framework, we can identify a number of priority research areas to which
			<lb/>
			HDSS sites are uniquely placed to contribute.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Measuring the dimensions and nature of health problems: − One of the most
			<lb/>
			significant gaps in public health information is the limited availability and poor quality of
			<lb/>
			data on mortality patterns, trends and causes. Without such data, continuously, over time,
			<lb/>
			for all population groups, there can be no evidence-based public health decision-making.
			<lb/>
			The uniqueness of the HDSS sites is that they are able to generate such data in settings
			<lb/>
			with no other comparable source of information on births, deaths and causes of death.
			<lb/>
			INDEPTH should deepen and extend its collaboration with WHO, Health Metrics
			<lb/>
			Network and other agencies in the Monitoring Vital Events Initiative. The skills and
			<lb/>
			capacities in vital statistics monitoring accumulated in the HDSS sites can serve as the
			<lb/>
			nucleus of country-wide capacities for better vital statistics. While most HDSS sites are
			<lb/>
			currently located in rural areas, migration patterns and increasing urbanisation call for
			<lb/>
			increased demographic surveillance in urban slums in order to better understand the
			<lb/>
			health challenges facing the more than 50% of the world&apos;s population now urbanized.
			<lb/>
			At the same time, HDSS at the district level is needed to enable decentralization to be
			<lb/>
			underpinned by clear evidence on district level needs and the impact of interventions.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Understanding the causes of problems; the determinants of health and ill-health: −
			<lb/>
			Understanding the etiology and determinants of ill-health requires long-term longitudinal
			<lb/>
			cohort studies that can elucidate multifactorial underlying determinants such as socio-<lb/>economic status,
			environmental, biological, and behavioural risk factors. The inclusion of
			<lb/>
			clinical measures and bio-markers in HDSS will greater enhance our understanding of
			<lb/>
			disease patterns and causation. More studies are needed on the determinants of inequities
			<lb/>
			in health and how to overcome them.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Developing solutions to address the problems: − The HDSS sites are well placed when it
			<lb/>
			comes to testing innovative solutions to existing and emerging health challenges, offering
			<lb/>
			possibilities for scientific evaluation of the effectiveness of new products, interventions,
			<lb/>
			or packages of interventions such as Integrated Management of Adult Illnesses (IMAI).
			<lb/>
			They also permit the evaluation of health systems such as the impact of incentives for
			<lb/>
			health workers in terms of health worker recruitment and retention.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Translating the actions and delivering solutions: − Perhaps the most important
			<lb/>
			contribution that the HDSS sites can make is in the area of the implementation of
			<lb/>
			interventions in &quot;real&quot; settings where contextual factors have a strong influence on
			<lb/>
			results, moving from demonstrations of efficacy to evidence of effectiveness. Examples
			<lb/>
			of the kinds of research questions that could be answered in INDEPTH settings include:
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<list>
			<item> Assessing the interface between global health initiatives and the strengthening of
				<lb/>
				health systems -are there synergies to be found?
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				 Defining the delivery requirements for chronic diseases -can HIV services be used as
				<lb/>
				an entry point for chronic disease prevention and treatment?
				<lb/>
			</item>
		</list>
		
		<p>Evaluating the effectiveness of the solutions: − A particularly important opportunity
			<lb/>
			provided by the HDSS sites is in the area of the evaluation of interventions and programmes,
			<lb/>
			especially in relation to scaling up, health system performance and system-wide interventions.
			<lb/>
			INDEPTH could tap into the substantial resources available from global health funds, the Global
			<lb/>
			Fund to fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria (GFATM) and the Global Alliance for
			<lb/>
			Vaccines and Immunisation (GAVI), by developing monitoring and evaluation proposals
			<lb/>
			as part of national proposals to these global funds. INDEPTH could also &quot;retail&quot; solid
			<lb/>
			baselines as a basis for assessing and attributing changes from interventions; currently
			<lb/>
			baselines are largely absent in most evaluation efforts.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Health system strengthening: − Cutting across each of these research streams, is the
			<lb/>
			issue of how to strengthen health systems in order to enable the successful scaling up of
			<lb/>
			interventions. There is mounting evidence that health systems that can deliver services
			<lb/>
			equitably and efficiently are critical to the achievement of national and global health
			<lb/>
			goals, both in terms of communicable diseases and maternal and perinatal health, but
			<lb/>
			also, critically, for the prevention and management of chronic and non communicable
			<lb/>
			diseases. Global health initiatives now incorporate attention to health systems
			<lb/>
			strengthening into the support provided to countries. However, there is an urgent need for
			<lb/>
			research on all aspects of health system performance, from understanding the dimensions
			<lb/>
			and nature of health system constraints, to developing innovative strategies for
			<lb/>
			strengthening health systems, translating these into action on the ground and evaluating
			<lb/>
			to assure continuous improvement, enhanced efficiency and effectiveness. The HDSS
			<lb/>
			sites should engage in research on improving performance across each of the health
			<lb/>
			system building blocks -service delivery, health workforce, health information systems,
			<lb/>
			medical products, vaccines and technologies, financing and governance (<ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref>).
			The
			<lb/>
			availability of solid data on health status generated through the HDSS surveillance will
			<lb/>
			permit an evaluation of health system performance in terms of improved health
			<lb/>
			outcomes, enhanced responsiveness, improved efficiency and social and financial risk
			<lb/>
			protection.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>2. Building research capacities
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The INDEPTH Network and the HDSS sites have an unrivalled reputation in terms of
			<lb/>
			building capacities for research in developing countries. As its embarks on its second
			<lb/>
			decade, there is much that INDEPH can do to build upon and further strengthen its
			<lb/>
			achievements in this area:
			<lb/>
			Building capacities among individual researchers: − INDEPTH should establish more
			<lb/>
			formal links for &quot;researcher&quot; training and faculty appointments with schools of public
			<lb/>
			health around the world. It should also consider setting up an &quot;INDEPTH Fellows&quot;<lb/>
			programme, tapping into resources from donor institutions that actively support capacity-<lb/>building such
			as Fogarty, the Swedish International Development Cooperation Agency
			<lb/>
			(Sida), the Rockefeller Foundation, and the International Development Research Centre
			<lb/>
			(IDRC). Such capacity-building should address the range of skills relevant to research,
			<lb/>
			not only with regard to study design, data collection and statistical analysis but also in the
			<lb/>
			management, archiving and curation of the large and complex data sets amassed by the
			<lb/>
			HDSS sites.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		<p>
			Extending the network: − There are a number of opportunities for INDEPTH to reach
			<lb/>
			out beyond its traditional links to the research community in developing countries. For
			<lb/>
			example, INDEPTH should link to the fast growing &quot;observatories&quot; movement to which
			<lb/>
			it can bring scientific and statistical rigour and insight. The Network should also look into
			<lb/>
			establishing explicit linkages with longitudinal surveillance sites in Organisation for
			<lb/>
			Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD) countries, such as Framingham. Such
			<lb/>
			collaboration would be particularly beneficial as the HDSS sites focus more on tracking
			<lb/>
			the epidemiological transition and the growing prevalence of non-communicable diseases
			<lb/>
			in developing countries. In addition, INDEPTH should seize the opportunity to position
			<lb/>
			itself as a key partner in the emerging global collaboration on health metrics and
			<lb/>
			evaluation. The HDSS sites generate data on vital events which, although not
			<lb/>
			representative of the population as a whole, can provide important information on levels
			<lb/>
			of mortality by age and sex. Moreover, the HDSS sites are helping to build the skills for
			<lb/>
			demographic surveillance required for sustainable civil registration.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>3. Developing and implementing research standards
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>INDEPTH continues to be instrumental in developing and applying high standards in the
			<lb/>
			conduct of research across its sites. There is scope for further standard-setting innovative
			<lb/>
			work in methods and measurement strategies, for example:
			<lb/>
		</p>
		<list>
			<item>
				 Development and testing of small area sampling and survey tools, for example for
				<lb/>
				use at neighbourhood and sub-district levels, in order to generate population data
				<lb/>
				on coverage and health status that district level managers need;
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				 Development of real-time, multi-site, evaluation methods;
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				 Building &quot;interoperability&quot; between population-based HDSS surveillance records
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				and individual electronic medical records.
				<lb/>
			</item>
		</list>
		
		<p>INDEPTH should also continue to contribute to setting and implementing standards of
			<lb/>
			research conduct, such as the ethics of data management, protecting privacy and
			<lb/>
			confidentiality while promoting public access to data. INDEPTH sites have to grapple
			<lb/>
			with incentive structures in epidemiological research that put private and institutional
			<lb/>
			interests at odds with the public good. They have to deal with chronic under-investment
			<lb/>
			in data management and analysis skills and need to push for more realistic &quot;overheads&quot;<lb/>
			from donors to support real costs of research infrastructure.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>4. Translating research results into action
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Translating the results of research into action at scale is critically dependent on effective
			<lb/>
			communication with those in a position to bring about change, namely policy makers and
			<lb/>
			all those with power of resource allocation, many of whom are not located within the
			<lb/>
			health sector. At the beginning of this paper we argued that INDEPTH needs to do more
			<lb/>
			to document and publicize its achievements over the first decade. As it embarks on its
			<lb/>
			second decade, increased and targeted advocacy and communication must become a core
			<lb/>
			part of INDEPTH&apos;s work. INDEPTH needs to develop and nurture relationships not only
			<lb/>
			with the research and public health communities but also with politicians, policy-makers,
			<lb/>
			practitioners and the general public. Sharing of research findings should be a core
			<lb/>
			component in every site and advocacy and communications skills should be considered
			<lb/>
			alongside statistical and epidemiological skills as central to INDEPTH&apos;s mission.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>One way of encouraging increased access to the products of HDSS research would be by
			<lb/>
			establishing an INDEPTH Virtual Library with on-line access to publications, papers, and
			<lb/>
			data sets. But it is important to ensure that the results of research are appropriately
			<lb/>
			packaged and transmitted to different audiences who will be key to INDEPTH&apos;s ongoing
			<lb/>
			success and, indeed, survival. Even when data have been gathered and summarised to
			<lb/>
			high standards, further analysis-of what is both reported and missing-is usually needed
			<lb/>
			before the information can be disseminated and communicated to non-technical
			<lb/>
			audiences and used as the basis for policymaking. Information can be conveyed directly
			<lb/>
			to policymakers or indirectly through secondary audiences, such as academics,
			<lb/>
			researchers, health professionals, parliamentarians, the media or advocacy groups, who
			<lb/>
			are in a position to affect policymakers. INDEPTH should use an array of communication
			<lb/>
			channels including seminars, peer-reviewed journals, special events, national and
			<lb/>
			international meetings, and policy briefs. Links to open access journals such as Global
			<lb/>
			Health Action should be vigorously pursued.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Legends to Figures
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<figure>Fig 1: WHO research priorities framework
			<lb/>
			Fig 2: Health system building blocks
		</figure>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
