<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>Introduction
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The under-reporting of maternal deaths is common in both developing and developed
			<lb/>
			countries. Even in countries where all or most deaths are medically certified, institutional
			<lb/>
			maternal mortality can still be grossly underestimated. Hospital studies have shown that
			<lb/>
			routine methods of identifying maternal deaths under-estimate the number by one-half to
			<lb/>
			two-thirds <ref type="biblio">[1-4]</ref>, with the main problem being the misclassification of indirect
			maternal
			<lb/>
			deaths as non-maternal.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Accurate estimates are important for several reasons: it is necessary to define the scale of the
			<lb/>
			problem of maternal mortality so that adequate resources can be allocated to address it;
			<lb/>
			complete reporting allows all maternal deaths to be audited, so facilitating relevant changes in
			<lb/>
			policy and practice; and in the context of evaluation it is essential that any changes
			<lb/>
			attributable to an intervention can be quantified precisely.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The Initiative for Maternal Mortality Programme Assessment (Immpact) project is an
			<lb/>
			international research initiative to strengthen the evidence base on cost-effective and
			<lb/>
			sustainable safe motherhood interventions (http://www.immpact-international.org/). As part
			<lb/>
			of this project, enhanced methods and tools have been developed to measure processes of
			<lb/>
			care as well as health outcomes, including maternal mortality. The objectives of the sub-<lb/>component of
			Immpact reported here was to document the completeness of reporting of
			<lb/>
			institutional maternal deaths in two districts of Indonesia and to assess the usefulness of a
			<lb/>
			new approach developed by Immpact, called as RAPID (Rapid Ascertainment Process of
			<lb/>
			Institutional Deaths) in identifying missing deaths.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>RAPID is a method designed to identify unreported maternal deaths within health facilities,
			<lb/>
			and to highlight areas for improvement in routine institutional death reporting. RAPID
			<lb/>
			involves reviewing all the health facility records relating to deaths among women of
			<lb/>
			reproductive age and subsequently identifying pregnancy-related deaths. This process differs
			<lb/>
			from the method routinely used in health facilities to identify pregnancy related deaths
			<lb/>
			because the deaths of all women of reproductive age are examined, so the search is not
			<lb/>
			limited to obstetric wards, but includes all wards in the hospital where women may be
			<lb/>
			patients. This minimizes the possibility of missing pregnancy-related deaths that occur
			<lb/>
			outside the obstetric area. RAPID also differs from previous research methods that have
			<lb/>
			examined under-reporting by taking information from registers to identify pregnancy-related
			<lb/>
			deaths, and only investigating the case notes for deaths that cannot be classified using readily
			<lb/>
			available routine sources.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>We also looked at whether it was possible to improve the reporting using existing sources of
			<lb/>
			data, and if so where such an improvement should be targeted.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Methods
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<figure>The data collection was conducted during April-May 2005 in the district hospitals of
			<lb/>
			Pandeglang and Serang, in Banten Province, Indonesia. The hospital records of all women
			<lb/>
			who had died aged 15-49 years during 2003 and 2004 were checked for evidence of their
			<lb/>
			pregnancy-related status. Information was extracted from registers and case notes onto pre-<lb/>tested
			forms. Before the study commenced ethical approval was obtained from Ethics
			<lb/>
			Committee of the University of Indonesia. Each institution also gave written consent before
			<lb/>
			data collection began.
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<p>The definition used to classify deaths as maternal was that the death occurred while a woman
			<lb/>
			was pregnant or within 42 days following the end of pregnancy, irrespective of the duration
			<lb/>
			and site of the pregnancy, from any cause related to or aggravated by the pregnancy or its
			<lb/>
			management but not from accidental or incidental causes <ref type="biblio">[5]</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Register review
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Each team, consisting of one medical doctor and a research assistant, identified all the
			<lb/>
			possible register sources of information on deaths to 15-49 year old women at each of the
			<lb/>
			participating hospitals. There were a total of 12 wards in the two district hospitals where
			<lb/>
			women may have died, and in each ward there were various sources of information about the
			<lb/>
			cases (e.g. ward registers, nurses&apos; daily reports, and death registers). These sources were
			<lb/>
			listed and then searched for deaths, until all deaths among 15-49 year old women were
			<lb/>
			recorded with details of the diagnosis and cause of death. Deaths could be recorded in more
			<lb/>
			than one register, so it was essential that the information obtained was cross-checked between
			<lb/>
			the different registers. Using the information from the registers as many deaths as possible
			<lb/>
			were classified as likely &apos;maternal&apos; or &apos;non-maternal.&apos; All the deaths that could not be
			<lb/>
			classified as either maternal or non-maternal progressed to the next stage of investigation:
			<lb/>
			case note review.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Case note review
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Case notes were sought for all the women whose pregnancy-related status at time of death
			<lb/>
			remained unclear following register review. Information on diagnosis, cause of death,
			<lb/>
			treatments, procedures, obstetric history and demographics were extracted with the intention
			<lb/>
			of re-classifying these as maternal or non-maternal deaths. The purpose of this extraction was
			<lb/>
			not to review clinical management or procedures, but simply to gauge the likelihood that a
			<lb/>
			woman was pregnant or recently pregnant when she died. Based on the information extracted
			<lb/>
			from the case notes above, data collectors classified the pregnancy-related status of each
			<lb/>
			woman.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Comparison with other data sources:
			<lb/>
			Hospitals&apos; routine data sources for maternal death
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The total numbers of maternal deaths reported by the hospitals for the two years period were
			<lb/>
			collected from the district health offices (DHOs). Informal discussions with both hospital
			<lb/>
			staff and district health office staff were also conducted to obtain a description of the routine
			<lb/>
			reporting practices from the hospitals to the district health offices.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Results
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The register review identified 666 adult female deaths of which 135 were initially classified
			<lb/>
			as maternal deaths <ref type="figure">(Figure 1)</ref>. A further 20 maternal deaths were identified
			following case
			<lb/>
			note review, giving a total of 155 maternal deaths identified in the two district hospitals using
			<lb/>
			RAPID. Classification for the non-maternal deaths from the register reviews was mostly
			<lb/>
			based on the cases diagnosis, such as &apos;severe head injury caused by car accident&apos; and &apos;burns.&apos;<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Of the 453 cases that remained unclassified after register review, 191 (42.2%) had missing
			<lb/>
			case notes and could therefore not be subject to further examination. Of the 262 case notes
			<lb/>
			that were examined the vast majority, 241 (92%) could not be classified into maternal or non-<lb/>maternal
			following the review due to incomplete information.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure>
			(Figure 1)
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		
		<p>When attempts were made to collect routine figures for maternal deaths it was found that
			<lb/>
			hospitals were not in fact routinely reporting deaths to the district health offices. In practice,
			<lb/>
			the Maternal Child Health unit staff of the district health offices irregularly collected
			<lb/>
			information on maternal deaths directly from the obstetric areas and intensive care unit
			<lb/>
			(ICU); this was not a routine process, occurring once every 1-3 months. From the district
			<lb/>
			health offices annual record, there were total of 67 maternal deaths reported by the two
			<lb/>
			hospitals&apos; routine statistics. This number is less than a half of the number identified by
			<lb/>
			RAPID. The routine reports only include deaths from the obstetric wards, delivery room and
			<lb/>
			ICU. In this study, 86% of the maternal deaths were found in these three clinical areas, with
			<lb/>
			the majority (67.1%) either in the delivery rooms or the obstetric wards <ref type="table">(Table 1)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure type="table">
			(Table 1)
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<p>
			<ref type="table">Table 2</ref> shows how direct and indirect obstetric causes of death are distributed
			between the
			<lb/>
			clinical areas. Nearly all of the deaths identified from the obstetric wards and ICU were due
			<lb/>
			to direct obstetric causes, while in contrast most of the deaths found on other wards were due
			<lb/>
			to indirect causes (73%).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure type="table">
			(Table 2)
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<head>Discussion
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Despite our limited ability to compare the RAPID results with the hospitals&apos; routine data
			<lb/>
			fairly, (due to incomplete reports from the hospitals), it is reasonable to say that the hospitals&apos;<lb/>
			routine reports missed considerable numbers of maternal death cases. Furthermore it is likely
			<lb/>
			that the true number of maternal deaths was even higher than the number found in this study.
			<lb/>
			We consider it likely that our method missed additional maternal deaths due to the lack of
			<lb/>
			completeness in recorded information: missing registers, missing case notes or inadequate
			<lb/>
			notes written by health providers. Most diagnoses could be coded, but some could not, since
			<lb/>
			the health care providers only noted symptoms or conditions. Usually there was inadequate
			<lb/>
			information regarding pregnancy-related status for the cases outside the obstetric wards.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The under-reporting of maternal deaths in the current study was partly due to inadequacies in
			<lb/>
			the coverage of the routine reporting system, which only collected maternal deaths from the
			<lb/>
			delivery room, the obstetric and ICU wards. Approximately 14% of the cases missed from the
			<lb/>
			routine report were identified on non-obstetric wards, and these were mostly indirect
			<lb/>
			maternal deaths, although additional direct deaths were also found. There appeared to be poor
			<lb/>
			understanding among hospital staff that indirect obstetric deaths should be regarded as
			<lb/>
			maternal deaths, and it seems that the possibility of finding maternal deaths on other wards
			<lb/>
			was not considered by the hospital authorities. However failure to collect data from non-<lb/>obstetric
			wards was not the main reason for under-reporting: even on the obstetric and ICU
			<lb/>
			wards, the number of cases identified by RAPID, was twice as high as the number in the
			<lb/>
			routine hospital report.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Our findings are similar to those of other studies, both in developing and developed countries.
			<lb/>
			A study in Tanzania <ref type="biblio">[6]</ref> assessing the completeness of various information sources
			and the
			<lb/>
			related estimates of maternal mortality found that official statistics only reported two out of
			<lb/>
			22 maternal deaths occurring in one facility. Another study conducted in France in 1991
			<ref type="biblio">[2]
				<lb/>
			</ref>
			found that nearly half of the maternal deaths had not been reported as such on the death
			<lb/>
			certificate, and even those that had, may not have been subsequently registered correctly; as a
			<lb/>
			result, maternal deaths were underestimated by nearly 50%. Another study conducted in
			<lb/>
			Surinam <ref type="biblio">[7]</ref> used a reproductive age mortality survey (RAMOS) in 5 hospitals to
			identify 85
			<lb/>
			cases of maternal death. This was 1.3 times higher than the officially reported 65 cases of
			<lb/>
			maternal deaths.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The inadequate reporting of indirect obstetric deaths is also in concordance with other work.
			<lb/>
			A study in Taiwan <ref type="biblio">[8]</ref> found that factors contributing to the under-reporting and
			<lb/>
			misclassification of maternal mortality included: care sought for non-obstetric reasons, death
			<lb/>
			from non-obstetric causes; care received in private health facilities, and death occurring at
			<lb/>
			home with certification by a non-obstetrician-gynecologist. A World Health Organization
			<lb/>
			(WHO) report <ref type="biblio">[9]</ref> shows that out of 66 countries reporting vital registration
			figures for causes
			<lb/>
			of maternal death over the period 1992-1993, over half (33 countries) reported no indirect
			<lb/>
			deaths at all. Yet the 1997-1999 Confidential Enquiry in the United Kingdom found that
			<lb/>
			indirect deaths now account for more maternal deaths than deaths due to direct causes <ref type="biblio">
				[10]</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>One of the limitations of the study was that the register review process could not be
			<lb/>
			implemented as simply as had been anticipated. The RAPID retrospective process revealed
			<lb/>
			that there was no standard format for the registers in each ward, which meant that the type of
			<lb/>
			information available varied between registers and the RAPID forms had to be revised. The
			<lb/>
			most important consequence of this was that cases could exist in single or multiple registers,
			<lb/>
			so there was a need to cross-check cases between registers. The identification of duplicate
			<lb/>
			cases between registers had not been adequately considered by the method, as hospital
			<lb/>
			identifiers alone proved insufficient (these were often missing). This meant a great deal of
			<lb/>
			extra work was involved in going back to registers and case notes to check that extractions
			<lb/>
			had not been duplicated. The absence of case note numbers in some registers also meant that
			<lb/>
			cases only recorded in such a register could not be followed up.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The majority of the maternal deaths identified in this study were found at the register review
			<lb/>
			stage; future similar studies in this context could consider removing the case note review
			<lb/>
			element from the method. This would significantly reduce the resources needed to implement
			<lb/>
			the review.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Conclusions and Recommendations
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The RAPID method found 155 maternal death cases in the two hospitals for the period of
			<lb/>
			2003-2004. This is more than twice the number of maternal deaths reported routinely by the
			<lb/>
			hospitals. It is likely that the real number of maternal deaths is even higher, as some registers
			<lb/>
			and case notes were missing; and because even where they were available, the information
			<lb/>
			needed to identify a death as pregnancy-related is not always recorded.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>RAPID highlights possible misunderstandings in what should be regarded as a maternal
			<lb/>
			death, and in particular the inclusion of deaths from indirect (non-obstetric) causes. In other
			<lb/>
			contexts RAPID has focused on all pregnancy-related deaths <ref type="biblio">[11]</ref>, and this may be
			preferable,
			<lb/>
			considering the difficulty in determining whether particular causes of death are exacerbated
			<lb/>
			by pregnancy <ref type="biblio">[12-13]</ref>. However, identifying pregnancy-related deaths means that
			there is
			<lb/>
			greater emphasis attached to the information obtained from case notes, which is a limitation
			<lb/>
			given the incompleteness of data on pregnancy status obtained from this source.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>We recommend that DHO and hospital staffs are formally orientated to the definition of
			<lb/>
			maternal death, and that non-obstetric wards are included in the collection of data for routine
			<lb/>
			reports on maternal mortality. The RAPID process is a practical method that can alert
			<lb/>
			hospitals to the magnitude of under-reporting maternal deaths. It also draws attention to
			<lb/>
			shortcomings in the quality and storage of case notes, and provides evidence to initiate
			<lb/>
			improvements in all these areas. We suggest that regular implementation of RAPID, or its
			<lb/>
			integration into the routine hospital information system, could help to monitor improvement
			<lb/>
			in reporting, and call on hospitals to improve the quality and storage of registers and case
			<lb/>
			notes to facilitate this process.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure type="table">Table 1. Numbers of maternal deaths by clinical area
			<lb/>
			Wards
			<lb/>
			Number of
			<lb/>
			cases
			<lb/>
			%
			<lb/>
			Delivery room
			<lb/>
			61
			<lb/>
			39.4
			<lb/>
			Obstetric wards
			<lb/>
			43
			<lb/>
			27.7
			<lb/>
			ICU/ICCU
			<lb/>
			29
			<lb/>
			18.7
			<lb/>
			Emergency Room
			<lb/>
			9
			<lb/>
			5.8
			<lb/>
			Internal medicine wards
			<lb/>
			8
			<lb/>
			5.2
			<lb/>
			General
			<lb/>
			4
			<lb/>
			2.6
			<lb/>
			Surgery wards
			<lb/>
			1
			<lb/>
			0.6
			<lb/>
			Total
			<lb/>
			155
			<lb/>
			100
			<lb/>
			Table
		</figure>
		
		<figure type="table">2. Numbers of maternal deaths by direct/indirect cause and by clinical area
			<lb/>
			Direct Maternal Indirect Maternal Inconclusive
			<lb/>
			Total
			<lb/>
			Wards
			<lb/>
			N (%)
			<lb/>
			N (%)
			<lb/>
			N (%)
			<lb/>
			N (%)
			<lb/>
			Obstetric
			<lb/>
			100 (96.2)
			<lb/>
			4 (3.8%)
			<lb/>
			0 (0)
			<lb/>
			104 (67.1)
			<lb/>
			ICU
			<lb/>
			25 (86.2)
			<lb/>
			3 (10.3)
			<lb/>
			1 (3.4)
			<lb/>
			29 (18.7)
			<lb/>
			Other
			<lb/>
			3 (13.6)
			<lb/>
			16 (72.7)
			<lb/>
			3 (13.6)
			<lb/>
			22 (14.2)
			<lb/>
			Total
			<lb/>
			128 (82.6)
			<lb/>
			23 (14.8)
			<lb/>
			4 (2.6)
			<lb/>
			155
		</figure>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
