<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			There is increasing concern and research around the health issues of ageing, not least
			<lb/>
			because of the increasing proportion of older people in many populations <ref type="biblio">[1]</ref>.
			<lb/>
			However, whilst it is widely recognised that more developed countries are
			<lb/>
			encountering an increasing &quot;burden&quot; of elderly people, a more global perspective is
			<lb/>
			often lacking <ref type="biblio">[2]</ref>. This partially reflects gaps in the global data, which mean that
			the
			<lb/>
			details of ageing in many contexts are poorly documented, as highlighted by HelpAge
			<lb/>
			International <ref type="biblio">[3]</ref>. Many other concerns about ageing relate to possible future gaps
			in
			<lb/>
			pension provision as a result of demographic changes <ref type="biblio">[4]</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		<p>
			The numbers behind the global situation, though, clearly show that issues of ageing
			<lb/>
			are by no means restricted to more affluent settings <ref type="biblio">[5]</ref>. Using the UN population
			<lb/>
			estimates <ref type="biblio">[6]</ref>, characteristics of the global population in 2010 by level of
			development
			<lb/>
			are illustrated in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>. The world&apos;s over-60 population is 0.8 billion,
			11% of the
			<lb/>
			total. Whilst the overall shape of this population pyramid is perhaps unsurprising,
			<lb/>
			there are several points to note. It is only among the over-85 age group that the elderly
			<lb/>
			of the more developed countries out-number those of the less-and least-developed
			<lb/>
			countries. The over-80s account for 14% of the over-60s.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		<p>
			Interesting as this contemporary situation may be, it also has to be recognised that it is
			<lb/>
			far from static. <ref type="figure">Figure 2</ref> shows the UN&apos;s projected developments in the world&apos;s
			<lb/>
			population by 2050. By this time, it will be only in the over-95 age group where there
			<lb/>
			will be a majority from more developed nations. The world&apos;s over-60 population will
			<lb/>
			be 1.4 billion, almost 18% of the total. The over-80s globally will account for 20% of
			<lb/>
			the over-60s. Thus it becomes clear that, in the global context, the proportion of
			<lb/>
			elderly people who live in more developed countries will decline sharply. The
			<lb/>
			difference in the shape of the 2050 pyramid compared with 2010 basically reflects the
			<lb/>
			upward shift of an increasingly large proportion of the population over time, with
			<lb/>
			some of the biggest changes seen in the less-and least-developed countries.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The role of the elderly within any population depends on many interlinked factors,
			<lb/>
			including social determinants, financial concerns, familial structures, and cultural
			<lb/>
			norms, all of which impact on the health and well-being of older people. Favourable
			<lb/>
			trends hence lead to longer survival, hopefully associated with continuing good
			<lb/>
			quality of life. The concept of &quot;successful ageing&quot; <ref type="biblio">[7]</ref> thus attempts to
			create a more
			<lb/>
			constructive paradigm around growing older, as opposed to problematising the ageing
			<lb/>
			process.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>What are the health problems globally that mitigate against successful ageing? Much
			<lb/>
			emphasis is rightly given to increasingly high rates of non-communicable diseases as
			<lb/>
			causes of mortality among the elderly <ref type="biblio">[8]</ref>, and it is inevitable as life expectancy
			<lb/>
			increases that the incidence and prevalence of those diseases which predominantly
			<lb/>
			affect the elderly will also increase. But at the same time, the elderly retain their
			<lb/>
			vulnerability to infections, particularly in environments where widespread epidemics
			<lb/>
			may occur. Emmelin et al.&apos;s detailed account of the impact of abnormal weather
			<lb/>
			patterns on a rural Ethiopian population <ref type="biblio">[9]</ref>, leading to food shortages and major
			<lb/>
			mortality peaks relating to malaria and diarrhoeal diseases, clearly demonstrates that
			<lb/>
			the elderly may be just as vulnerable as the youngest in such epidemics (<ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref>).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>It is also very important to avoid the fallacy of assuming that relatively low life
			<lb/>
			expectancy at birth reflects low survival among the elderly. To take two fairly
			<lb/>
			extreme examples, Ethiopia and Sweden, UN estimates of life expectancy at birth for
			<lb/>
			the period 2000-2005 were 50.7 years and 80.1 years respectively <ref type="biblio">[10]</ref>.
			Nevertheless,
			<lb/>
			survival curves from the age of 60 from Swedish national statistics <ref type="biblio">[11]</ref> and the
			<lb/>
			Butajira Rural Health Programme in Ethiopia<ref type="biblio">[12]</ref>
			<ref type="figure">(Figure 4)</ref> show that
			survival
			<lb/>
			differences among the elderly in these two very diverse settings are not so great.
			<lb/>
			However, what <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref> does not show is that in Sweden 93% of babies born can
			<lb/>
			expect to reach their 60 th birthday, while the corresponding figure in Butajira is just
			<lb/>
			52%. Thus the current levels and projected increases in the numbers of elderly people
			<lb/>
			in less-and least-developed countries are related more critically to the number of
			<lb/>
			people entering old age, rather than the survival experience of elders. Hence, at least
			<lb/>
			from a survival perspective in the global context, &quot;successful ageing&quot; might more
			<lb/>
			accurately be described as &quot;successfully joining the elderly&quot;.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In terms of research agendas on ageing, there are also significant global disparities.
			<lb/>
			Apart from the relative lack of research on ageing in poorer settings, some research
			<lb/>
			hypotheses and methods are mainly focussed on more developed settings. Current
			<lb/>
			advances and discoveries around genetic and other biomarkers associated with the
			<lb/>
			ageing process are such examples <ref type="biblio">[13,14]</ref>. There is a clear need for technology and
			<lb/>
			capacity transfer to enable some of these more complex research methods to be
			<lb/>
			applied more widely on a global basis, both for the sake of research equity and
			<lb/>
			broader-based understanding.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In summary, the key points of relevance for setting a more global agenda for ageing
			<lb/>
			are:
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<list>
			<item> The number of elders in the world is steadily increasing, with the majority of
				<lb/>
				the increases being in less-and least-developed countries
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				 The elderly in poorer settings are doubly vulnerable, being exposed both to
				<lb/>
				diseases of ageing and infectious epidemics
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				 In less-and least-developing countries, the proportion of people becoming
				<lb/>
				elders is a major determinant of population change
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				 Technology transfer is needed to facilitate a more global approach to high-<lb/>technology ageing
				research
				<lb/>
			</item>
		</list>
		
		<p>Global Health Action would welcome research papers on ageing which reflect these
			<lb/>
			global perspectives.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure>Figure 1:</figure>
		
		<p>The age-sex structure of the world&apos;s population in 2010, by level of
			<lb/>
			development. (data source: UN Population Division <ref type="biblio">[6]</ref>)
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<formula>-350
			<lb/>
			0
			<lb/>
			350
			<lb/>
		</formula>
		
		<p>population (millions)
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure>Figure 2:</figure>
		
		<p>The age-sex structure of the world&apos;s population in 2050, by level of
			<lb/>
			development. (data source: UN Population Division <ref type="biblio">[6]</ref>)
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<formula>-350
			<lb/>
			0
			<lb/>
			350
			<lb/>
		</formula>
		
		<p>population (millions)
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure>Figure 3:</figure>
		
		<p>The impact of infectious epidemics on all-cause community-based
			<lb/>
			mortality rates in Butajira, Ethiopia, by age-group. (data source: Emmelin et al. <ref type="biblio">[9]</ref>)
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure>
			0
			<lb/>
			20
			<lb/>
			40
			<lb/>
			60
			<lb/>
			80
			<lb/>
			100
			<lb/>
			120
			<lb/>
			140
			<lb/>
			160
			<lb/>
			1997
			<lb/>
			1998
			<lb/>
			1999
			<lb/>
			2000
			<lb/>
			2001
			<lb/>
			mortality per 1,000 person-years
			<lb/>
			under 5 yrs
			<lb/>
			5 -49 yrs
			<lb/>
			50+ yrs
			<lb/>
			malaria-related
			<lb/>
			epidemic
			<lb/>
			diarrhoea-related
			<lb/>
			epidemic
			<lb/>
			Figure 4
		</figure>
		
		<figure>: Survival after the age of 60 years in Ethiopia and Sweden (data sources:
				<lb/>
				Fantahun <ref type="biblio">[12]</ref> and Statistics Sweden <ref type="biblio">[11]</ref>)
			<lb/>
			0
			<lb/>
			0.2
			<lb/>
			0.4
			<lb/>
			0.6
			<lb/>
			0.8
			<lb/>
			1
			<lb/>
			60
			<lb/>
			70
			<lb/>
			80
			<lb/>
			90
			<lb/>
			age (years)
			<lb/>
			survival from 60 years
			<lb/>
			Ethiopia
			<lb/>
			Sweden
		</figure>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
