<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			Having participated in the formal process of his PhD defence, it was a real pleasure to
			<lb/>
			read the paper by Ed Fottrell discussing challenges, limitations, possibilities, and research
			<lb/>
			areas related to mortality data in developing countries <ref type="biblio">(1)</ref>. In a few pages he has managed
			<lb/>
			to highlight the most important aspects around that topic. A quotation from J.W. Lee,
			<lb/>
			former Director General of the World Health Organisation, &quot;To make people count, we first
			<lb/>
			need to be able to count people&quot; is filled with life here. Fottrell lucidly constructs a bridge
			<lb/>
			from describing the data we want to describing the data we have, and it is most interesting
			<lb/>
			to read about ongoing research activities leading towards making the best use of the data
			<lb/>
			at hand, with their undoubted limitations, to get information, for example on cause-of-death
			<lb/>
			distributions, to a precision and certainty which allow them to be the basis for public health
			<lb/>
			action. His paper, as well his recent PhD thesis <ref type="biblio">(2)</ref>, shows nicely that being a good
			<lb/>
			statistician who understands sampling surveys and theory of measurement error analysis
			<lb/>
			is necessary but not sufficient in order to make significant contributions to improving
			<lb/>
			mortality surveillance in resource-poor countries. Personal experience in developing
			<lb/>
			countries, the ability to see what can be done and what cannot be done, and to simplify
			<lb/>
			things as much as necessary, but not too much, are just as important.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>For public health purposes information on mortality is necessary. But what degree of
			<lb/>
			precision is needed? What is &quot;sufficiently accurate&quot;? How can it be concluded that quality
			<lb/>
			is &quot;sufficient&quot;? Fottrell&apos;s supervisor wrote in another recent publication: &quot;Realistically,
			there
			<lb/>
			will not be universal vital registration and individually based cause-of-death data on a
			<lb/>
			worldwide basis anytime soon, no matter how useful such information might be in public
			<lb/>
			health terms. Therefore a mixed-methods approach will continue to be used, combining
			<lb/>
			data sources that are most appropriate to their particular settings, and meeting needs at
			<lb/>
			different levels.&quot; <ref type="biblio">(3)</ref>. The approaches that have been developed and used in
			the past to
			<lb/>
			obtain the previously mentioned parameters require: (i) refinement -meaning that existing
			<lb/>
			methods may not be fully satisfactory and need updating; and (ii) evaluation -the
			<lb/>
			performance of existing methods must be investigated. Another important point, also
			<lb/>
			mentioned in the paper, lies in the fact that insufficient use has been made of the huge
			<lb/>
			amount of data that has been collected. There are many reasons for this. First, in order to
			<lb/>
			analyse health and demographic surveillance system (HDSS) data effectively, efficient
			<lb/>
			working groups must exist, consisting of biostatisticians, database managers and
			<lb/>
			computer scientists, and epidemiologists -the first, to decide on statistical methods and
			<lb/>
			correctly apply them; the second, to efficiently and accurately organise the databases, and
			<lb/>
			the third, to identify questions of interest and to interpret the findings.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In that respect, I may add some personal experiences with data from one particular HDSS,
			<lb/>
			in Nouna, Burkina Faso. This HDSS has existed since 1992 and fully-functioned since
			<lb/>
			1993, and it has grown from covering a population of about 30,000 individuals to a current
			<lb/>
			population under surveillance of about 70,000. More villages have been included, and
			<lb/>
			methods for collecting and organising the data have become more sophisticated over the
			<lb/>
			years. How was that done, who was financially involved and have the data been used
			<lb/>
			appropriately? Regarding the latter, Fottrell comments &quot;That the value of data lies in their
			<lb/>
			use, not in their collection, does not always seem to be appreciated by surveillance
			<lb/>
			systems&quot;. However, I think it is not so much a lack of appreciation, but more of a lack of
			<lb/>
			availability of trained personnel. There is also a direct correlation with lack of funding, as
			<lb/>
			noted below, but in the case of the Nouna DSS it proved difficult to attract good local
			<lb/>
			statisticians to a working place in the periphery of the country when they could get better
			<lb/>
			paid jobs in the capital city. So in our case the funding of a large collaborative research
			<lb/>
			programme by the German Research Foundation since 1999 has allowed us to be more
			<lb/>
			active in collaboratively analysing HDSS data collected over the years, and a number of
			<lb/>
			scientific publications have emerged, as summarized in a monograph <ref type="biblio">(4)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Financing mechanisms for HDSSs is an important point that was not covered in Fottrell&apos;s
			<lb/>
			paper. In the case of the Nouna HDSS, financing has always been a critical issue, as
			<lb/>
			described by Diesfeld <ref type="biblio">(5)</ref>. Data quality and financial support are highly correlated, as can
			<lb/>
			be seen in the data of the Nouna HDSS during the 1990s, when percentages of missing
			<lb/>
			values increased at times when sufficient financial support was lacking. The situation
			<lb/>
			improved after the research grant from the German Research Foundation in 1999
			<lb/>
			facilitated better surveillance procedures. Thus the Nouna HDSS, and most others, are
			<lb/>
			constantly working to find sustainable means of guaranteeing uninterrupted, high-quality
			<lb/>
			surveillance of their respective populations, and the INDEPTH network has contributed
			<lb/>
			greatly to achieving high quality standards in the sites linked to the network. Funding
			<lb/>
			agencies are increasingly acknowledging this fact, but still it is an on-going challenge to
			<lb/>
			get long-term funding for the basic maintenance of the surveillance process.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In the early days of most HDSS sites, overall mortality was the main outcome of interest,
			<lb/>
			and only over time has more effort been put into assessing causes of death. The first
			<lb/>
			INDEPTH monograph reported total mortality, mortality by age and life expectancy only.
			<lb/>
			Verbal autopsy has developed in the meantime and became the method of choice for
			<lb/>
			cause-of-death statistics in developing countries. Limitations of the verbal autopsy method
			<lb/>
			are obvious, although refinement of the method over the years has led to increases in
			<lb/>
			sensitivity and specificity. Further developments, for example using the InterVA method,
			<lb/>
			have yielded further improvements <ref type="biblio">(6-8)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The recent advances in cause of death statistics, however, appear to have been focussed
			<lb/>
			more towards communicable diseases. Given recent projections on cause of death
			<lb/>
			distributions in Africa, deaths due to non-communicable diseases will become more
			<lb/>
			frequent, and verbal autopsy based methods may have serious limitations here. More
			<lb/>
			research is needed here -a frequently used but still correct phrase. The author of the
			<lb/>
			paper to which this Commentary pertains, and his collaborators, certainly have sufficient
			<lb/>
			fields for future investigations.
		</p>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
