<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>
			How relevant is our work?
			<lb/>
		</head>
		<p>A lot of semantic nuances hide ideological differences in every-day discussions
			<lb/>
			between public health professionals. If we are to fulfil our potential role as
			<lb/>
			change agents as we try to solve the problem of preventable ill-health, we will
			<lb/>
			need to pool together our (assumed) genuine and honest predisposition to action
			<lb/>
			in public health --no matter whether we are ethically or politically motivated. Such
			<lb/>
			a pooling together has to begin by launching a process of critical analysis of our
			<lb/>
			respective professional motivations and goals (including their frequently
			<lb/>
			overlooked contradictions). This very process should, hopefully, show to what
			<lb/>
			extent our actions in public health can be made to converge to achieve a real,
			<lb/>
			final impact in ameliorating preventable ill-health anywhere, in a reasonable time
			<lb/>
			horizon. Basically, public health professionals should be searching for a new
			<lb/>
			shared ethos --a professional, and at the same time, political ethos.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Of course, there are those who argue: &quot;Why don&apos;t we just forget about the
			<lb/>
			conservative public health professionals in our guild and focus our efforts more
			<lb/>
			on helping to change poor people directly (the slum dwellers, the poor peasants,
			<lb/>
			the unemployed) since they will ultimately be the ones called upon to bring about
			<lb/>
			lasting social changes anyway?&quot; The answer to this question can be ambivalent
			<lb/>
			since neither of both activities are exclusive: it is mostly a question of what
			<lb/>
			percentage of effort to devote to each of them.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In the long run, there will have to be moral changes on the part of those of us
			<lb/>
			who enjoy the luxuries of affluence. The question is, will these lead to ideological
			<lb/>
			changes in some? <ref type="biblio">(2)</ref> We have already passed the era when we asked public
			<lb/>
			health to become more applied and involved in participatory research; now,
			<lb/>
			already since Alma Ata in 1978 <ref type="biblio">(2a)</ref>, we are asking its practitioners to become
			<lb/>
			more socially conscious and more committed as real change-agents, leaving
			<lb/>
			behind a lot of epidemiological preciosity. Depoliticized public health is not a
			<lb/>
			discipline in the real service of man (Franz Fannon). There is indeed a heavy
			<lb/>
			burden put on the shoulders of health care practitioners if they are to &apos;fit into
			<lb/>
			Fannon&apos;s shoes&apos; and implement social policies and/or fight to change them as
			<lb/>
			they try to comprehensively care for their patients. <ref type="biblio">(2b)</ref> We cannot assume that
			<lb/>
			all providers have the exposure or expertise to use a more political language and
			<lb/>
			approach in their practice. So, key is to ask how providers will get this political
			<lb/>
			education to move to a new consciousness regarding social issues as the
			<lb/>
			underlying determinants of health. A good part of it is covered elsewhere <ref type="biblio">(2c)</ref>
			<lb/>
			and some of it covered further along this debate piece.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Political naivete?
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Many among us still think that politics is not a &apos;virtuous&apos; activity. That is probably
			<lb/>
			why they embark in (only) quixotic actions against the injustices of the prevalent
			<lb/>
			social system --which they also, more often than not, condemn--without realizing
			<lb/>
			that, in the end, they are being instrumental to its maintenance. They assume
			<lb/>
			decision-makers in the administration are rational and righteous and will bend in
			<lb/>
			front of hard scientific and/or epidemiological evidence or will react to outrageous
			<lb/>
			injustice. The more liberal among us, on the other hand, pay lip-service to
			<lb/>
			needed changes, even applauding interventions by the more radical among us;
			<lb/>
			but they lack, perhaps as much as the mainly moralists, the political education
			<lb/>
			about what is really needed to overcome preventable ill-health in our consumer
			<lb/>
			societies. The fight against preventable ill-health and malnutrition is eminently a
			<lb/>
			political and not a technical struggle. Technology is hardly the adequate point of
			<lb/>
			departure to achieve the deep structural changes needed to drastically reduce
			<lb/>
			preventable ill-health and deaths even to the timid levels called-for by the MDGs.
			<lb/>
			<ref type="biblio">(2d)</ref> the right political approach is the better point of departure. Health
			<lb/>
			professionals are rarely trained in the social sciences and, therefore, use social
			<lb/>
			theory implicitly rather than explicitly. <ref type="biblio">(3)</ref> This is where the challenge lies in
			<lb/>
			searching for the missing ideological link. 1
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Social consciousness
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Does all this mean that the more radical public health professionals or
			<lb/>
			researchers have a higher level of social consciousness than their non-radical
			<lb/>
			peers? What is clear is that once a certain level of political consciousness is
			<lb/>
			attained (is there a threshold?...) a more bottom-centered action-oriented attitude
			<lb/>
			usually follows. 2 At that point, there is a convergence of ideology and action
			<lb/>
			which makes the difference between taking an observer&apos;s as opposed to a
			<lb/>
			protagonist&apos;s role. Knowing about injustices does not move us. Becoming
			<lb/>
			conscious about them generates a creative anger that calls for involvement in
			<lb/>
			corrective actions. The latter can only happen within the framework of an
			<lb/>
			ideology consciously acquired.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The political forces behind timid sectoral health reforms are to be fought with
			<lb/>
			political actions, not with morals, or with yet more technological fixes. This does
			<lb/>
			not mean that strong ethical principles cannot be used as a political weapon in
			<lb/>
			our work in global health, but this usually fails if not placed in a structural political
			<lb/>
			context: without trying to caricaturize things, &quot;putting the other cheek&quot; is not
			<lb/>
			enough… It is because of an ideological and political lack of clarity that many a
			<lb/>
			public health professional who has occasionally jumped into the political arena in
			<lb/>
			the North or in the South has so often failed. Health care providers do have
			<lb/>
			values --let us be clear--but I am afraid the same are heavily influenced by the
			<lb/>
			reductionistic biomedical model of health we are indoctrinated into from day one.
			<lb/>
			I contend that the latter prevents practitioners from adopting a more socially
			<lb/>
			conscious approach in their practice; it also centers their accountability first and
			<lb/>
			foremost on their technical medical and public health performance with their
			<lb/>
			social accountability falling through the cracks.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Are we afraid of speaking-up in political terms?
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Many health professionals feel that their positions in academe, government or
			<lb/>
			international or private organizations may be jeopardized if they &apos;come out of the
			<lb/>
			closet&apos; with more radical positions. I acknowledge repressive situations in some,
			<lb/>
			but not all, counties; but even under more liberal circumstances, these
			<lb/>
			professionals too often take a survivor&apos;s attitude. The result of such a position is
			<lb/>
			yet more palliative interventions that do not do much to eradicate preventable ill-<lb/>health and
			preventable malnutrition. But there are certain actions that can be
			<lb/>
			implemented in any system that will have a lasting effect in addressing
			<lb/>
			preventable ill-health and malnutrition. We seldom see agencies or concerned
			<lb/>
			public health professionals primarily pushing those actions, because they are
			<lb/>
			mostly non-health, at least at the outset. <ref type="biblio">(2c)</ref> If we could at least begin giving
			<lb/>
			priority to some of these interventions, i.e., employment generation and income
			<lb/>
			redistribution measures, we would be contributing more to solving the health
			<lb/>
			problems of the deprived sectors of the population than by implementing pointed
			<lb/>
			public health interventions only.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Health professionals have to stop thinking that they cannot contribute much to
			<lb/>
			the selection and implementation of non-health interventions, because the latter
			<lb/>
			are outside their immediate field of expertise.
		</p>
		
		<note type="other">These professionals are champions
			<lb/>
			in denouncing transgressions to the principles of the biological and medical
			<lb/>
			sciences, but they are not half as active, and much less effective, in denouncing
			<lb/>
		</note>
		
		<p>transgressions to principles of the social sciences.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Lastly here, I do recognize there is varying political awareness of public health
			<lb/>
			professionals working on global health in different countries; a few of them have
			<lb/>
			successfully engaged in political processes and have played/are playing a
			<lb/>
			valuable public health leadership and political advocacy role. But they are a
			<lb/>
			distinct minority: does the exception confirm the rule…?
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Health problems in poor countries
			<lb/>
			So, what are internationally funded health programs in poor countries really
			<lb/>
			contributing to? How much responsibility are health professionals working in
			<lb/>
			those projects taking for their failure or their success? Who do they see really
			<lb/>
			benefiting from these programs? How do they see these programs&apos; impact in the
			<lb/>
			long run? A good number of these programs only scratch the surface of the local
			<lb/>
			problems and, therefore, contribute to the status-quo in these countries. 3 Every
			<lb/>
			donor brings its own ideas of the &apos;best&apos; health development strategy and its
			<lb/>
			programs will reflect that ideology (yes!, ideology). The influx of foreign experts
			<lb/>
			tends to mystify the planning process and to reinforce people&apos;s feelings of
			<lb/>
			inadequacy about their own capabilities. (4) (4a, 4b)
			<lb/>
			Professionals working in these projects should take part of the blame for failures.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>They should fight for changes in direction if programs are not bringing about the
			<lb/>
			anticipated and expected results. Here, a new role for them becomes more
			<lb/>
			evident: the public health professional as a denouncer of non-realistic goals or
			<lb/>
			processes of achieving them --this, especially because there are still some
			<lb/>
			interventions that will just partly contribute to decreasing preventable ill-health in
			<lb/>
			a given population even within the constraints of the unfair prevailing system. It is
			<lb/>
			true that these colleagues, in most cases, did not participate in the program&apos;s
			<lb/>
			design, but it should never be too late to change directions. Therefore, for these
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>3
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>We must be aware, though, that most poor countries&apos; governments would not accept foreign aid
			<lb/>
			programs at all if otherwise...
			<lb/>
			workers everything said about speaking up in political terms is doubly important,
			<lb/>
			be they ethically or politically motivated.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Some possible new directions
			<lb/>
			Yes, but what can I do?
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>For those accustomed to solving problems and putting them aside, grasping a
			<lb/>
			problem as intractable as the worldwide high prevalence of preventable ill-health
			<lb/>
			and malnutrition guarantees frustration. The flaw in our thinking is that the
			<lb/>
			solution to the preventable ill-health problem is not in nature, but in ourselves --in
			<lb/>
			our approach to the fundamental social relationships among people. (5)
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Preventable ill-health should not be combated because this brings mankind
			<lb/>
			utility, but because it is morally necessary (Emmanuel Kant). What we need to
			<lb/>
			fight for is equity not utility.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>It seems that our uncompromising devotion to science is not enough, we need to
			<lb/>
			use science to follow our con-science. We need to think about ourselves as
			<lb/>
			political human beings working as technicians in health remembering that global
			<lb/>
			change does not begin at the global level, but starts with individuals. (6) Many
			<lb/>
			health professionals have initially been motivated to simply transfer knowledge to
			<lb/>
			the people; the need is now to start focusing more on the social determinants of
			<lb/>
			the problems of mass poverty and preventable ill-health. (7) (2c) They need to
			<lb/>
			act as humanists before acting as health professionals. An important requirement
			<lb/>
			for this is to seek knowledge about the real world and not only about the world
			<lb/>
			we would like to see. (8) One cannot build on wishful thinking. It is precisely a
			<lb/>
			misunderstanding of reality [or a partial, (biomedical?) understanding] that often
			<lb/>
			reinforces the apolitical (or politically ambivalent) position of some health
			<lb/>
			professionals. 4 The social reality is not like a laboratory; many variables in it are
			<lb/>
			unknown and unforeseen and when we look at them it is often in the wrong way,
			<lb/>
			searching for the statistical &apos;whats&apos; instead of analysing the human &apos;whys&apos;.
		</p>
		
		<figure>(9)
			<lb/>
			Health a vehicle?
			<lb/>
			4
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<p>Or, some of them may not really want to understand; they have, all too often and for all the
			<lb/>
			wrong reasons, already made up their minds about one reality.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Public health seems to be as good (or bad) an entry point as any other
			<ref type="biblio">(nutrition,
				<lb/>
				employment, education, energy, natural resources, the environment, etc
			</ref>
			) to get
			<lb/>
			involved in questions of equity and the human right to health in our societies. (9a,
			<lb/>
			9b) Since the hurdles in the road to equity and the right to health are structural in
			<lb/>
			nature, criticizing them from any angle, initially, should lead us invariably to the
			<lb/>
			core of the underlying social structural problems. (2c, 9c, 9d) Health can lead to
			<lb/>
			global considerations only if not made a &apos;single-issue&apos; goal. Advocates of a more
			<lb/>
			limited approach to health often look at constraints from a quite narrow
			<lb/>
			perspective --a fact that seldom leads to more equity. There are too many
			<lb/>
			substitutes for in-depth political action in &apos;single-issue-politics&apos; that lead nowhere.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The worst is that many people do not see this difference and a lot of political
			<lb/>
			motivation and sometimes talent in scientists, health professionals or lay people
			<lb/>
			is lost, because of an apolitical approach to global issues. Single-issue politics
			<lb/>
			approaches suffer from a lack of global vision of society and, in particular, a lack
			<lb/>
			of will to make systemic historical changes. (10) 5
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>What is needed is more time specifically dedicated to work directly with poor
			<lb/>
			communities so they themselves can tackle the social and political causes of
			<lb/>
			their poverty, ill-health and malnutrition. This calls for public health professionals
			<lb/>
			to go, as much as possible, back to field work and out of their offices or
			<lb/>
			laboratories. Only out there, can the strengths needed for a change in direction
			<lb/>
			and perspective be found. Knowledge and scientific power created in institutions
			<lb/>
			away from the people are returning to the people and affecting them negatively.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The gap between those who have social power over thinking --an important form
			<lb/>
			5
			<lb/>
			Mention has to be made here that, already long ago, there was a call for a new ethic as the
			<lb/>
			paradigm to replace the present neoliberal ethic of constant growth. (11) (11a) This new,
			<lb/> &apos;desirable&apos; ethic was called the &quot;ethics of accommodation&quot;. It has called for
			simpler patterns of
			<lb/>
			living, more in balance with nature. One might agree with such an approach only in what pertains
			<lb/>
			to the finite availability of natural resources in our planet but, in what relates to social and
			<lb/>
			economic determinants of the ills of our world, this new ethic seems to be a typical example of a
			<lb/>
			partial focus on global realities and a selective choice of action priorities that condones social
			<lb/>
			status-quo and thus poverty.
			<lb/>
			of capital--and those who have not, has reached dimensions no less formidable
			<lb/>
			than the gap in access to economic assets. (12) (12a, 12b)
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Establishing the needed links
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Public health professionals need to learn from the people, as well as from their
			<lb/>
			perceptions of the problems. They need to establish links with local mass
			<lb/>
			movements and participate in their consciousness raising. The socioeconomic
			<lb/>
			contradictions present locally need to be highlighted and sharpened to give
			<lb/>
			priority to political action over, say, technological action that will only superficially
			<lb/>
			and short-term benefit poor people and marginalized groups of society. The
			<lb/>
			choice is, essentially, between leading poor people towards changes based on
			<lb/>
			an external consciousness, and raising mass consciousness and their capability
			<lb/>
			to make the changes themselves. It is important to demonstrate to them that it is
			<lb/>
			in their power, not only to change social reality, but the physical reality that
			<lb/>
			surrounds them as well. (13) (13a, 13b)
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>The bottom line
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Public health professionals go to the field either as researchers or as persons in
			<lb/>
			charge of certain interventions or projects. As such, they should always
			<lb/>
			participate, as well as intervene. They should enter into a dialogue with the
			<lb/>
			community which will more likely direct their action also towards the social
			<lb/>
			determinants of health that, in the community members&apos; eyes, are relevant to
			<lb/>
			solve their health problems. It is probably because this is not done that quick in-<lb/>and-out field
			research or projects create more frustration than motivation, both in
			<lb/>
			their implementers and in the community.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>That said, the desirable role of public health professionals doing field work should
			<lb/>
			be more one of a listener that does not allow interventions to proceed unchanged
			<lb/>
			if they are culturally or politically neutral or even biased against the interests of
			<lb/>
			the beneficiaries.
			<lb/>
			This leads us to the concept of accountability mentioned earlier; to whom should
			<lb/>
			these professionals in the field be accountable-to for their work, besides
			<lb/>
			themselves? Traditionally, they have been accountable to their peers and to
			<lb/>
			funding agencies. Too often they have neglected their accountability to the
			<lb/>
			beneficiaries. (14) (14a, 14b) 6
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>At this point, we are back full circle then to the question: &apos;What can I do?&apos; All that
			<lb/>
			has been said here just stresses the fact that the battle against preventable ill-<lb/>health, preventable
			malnutrition and preventable deaths can be won, if only
			<lb/>
			public health professionals play their roles to their ultimate consequence.
		</p>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
