<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>Introduction
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The principles behind how people respond to heat and conditions which would
			<lb/>
			influence health, comfort and human performance have been extensively
			<lb/>
			studied and are well understood <ref type="biblio">(1)</ref>. To avoid unacceptable heat strain in
			<lb/>
			specific populations and in specific contexts requires the application of those
			<lb/>
			principles into guidelines and heat management systems. How to do that is
			<lb/>
			not well understood.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Heat stress is determined by the metabolic heat production of the body,
			<lb/>
			which increases with level of activity (even at rest a person produces around
			<lb/>
			100 Watts of heat) and the ability to lose heat to the environment so that heat
			<lb/>
			stored in the body does not raise body temperature to unacceptable levels.
			<lb/>
			Clothing will restrict heat loss (or gain) between the skin and the
			<lb/>
			environment, which is determined by air temperature, radiant temperature,
			<lb/>
			humidity and air velocity. It is the interaction and combined effect of these
			<lb/>
			six factors that determines the level of heat stress.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Heat strain is a consequence of the response of the body to heat stress.
			<lb/>
			Increased heart rate and blood flow to the skin, and sweating can cause
			<lb/>
			illness and death in vulnerable people even when internal body temperatures
			<lb/>
			are at what would normally be considered to be acceptable levels. Sweating
			<lb/>
			can lead to dehydration and as well as increased body temperature can lead
			<lb/>
			to collapse, heat stroke and death.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>This paper provides a summary of physiological responses to heat and
			<lb/>
			presents methods for reducing heat strain. The aim of the paper is to consider
			<lb/>
			the application of knowledge of human response to heat to provide methods
			<lb/>
			for maintaining the health, comfort and productivity of people during a
			<lb/>
			prolonged and atypical period of hot weather (a heat wave).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Physiological response to heat
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>In heat stress the body temperature may rise and receptors sensitive to
			<lb/>
			change in temperature in the skin, muscle, stomach and other areas of the
			<lb/>
			central nervous system, as well as in the anterior hypothalamus itself, all send
			<lb/>
			signals via the central nervous system to the anterior hypothalamus. The ratio
			<lb/>
			of sodium to calcium ions is also monitored. Where temperatures are above
			<lb/> &apos;set point&apos; levels, blood circulation is controlled in specific areas of the body
			<lb/>
			through the sympathetic nervous system which dilates the cutaneous vascular
			<lb/>
			bed and hence increases skin blood flow and invokes the sweating
			<lb/>
			mechanism if necessary. This provides greater potential for heat to flow from
			<lb/>
			the body and hence maintain body temperature. Because the heart cannot
			<lb/>
			supply blood to all of the body&apos;s organ systems the autonomic nervous and
			<lb/>
			endocrine system control allocation of blood to competing organs.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>During exercise there is an initial sympathetic vasoconstriction so that blood
			<lb/>
			may flow to active muscles. If heat is required to be dissipated there is an
			<lb/>
			increased cutaneous blood flow. During continuous work, in the heat, central
			<lb/>
			nervous blood volume decreases as the cutaneous vessels dilate. The stroke
			<lb/>
			volume falls and the heart rate must increase to maintain cardiac output. The
			<lb/>
			effective circulatory volume also decreases as water is lost through sweating.
			<lb/>
			Sweat glands are stimulated by cholinergic sympathetic nerves and secrete
			<lb/>
			sweat onto the surface of the skin. Sweat rates of 1 litre per hour are common
			<lb/>
			and for each litre evaporated 675W of heat are lost per hour <ref type="biblio">(2)</ref>. However,
			<lb/>
			large sweat losses reduce body water content and hence thermoregulatory
			<lb/>
			effectiveness. During sweating salt is lost at about 4 g per litre (1 g per litre in
			<lb/>
			acclimatized persons). As a normal diet provides 8 -14 g per day then a
			<lb/>
			normal diet is often sufficient. Salt tablets can irritate the stomach and heavier
			<lb/>
			use of salt at meals is preferred, but salt supplementation will probably not
			<lb/>
			normally be required <ref type="biblio">(2)</ref>. Potassium is also lost in sweat and a high salt intake
			<lb/>
			may increase potassium loss. In most cases however potassium will be
			<lb/>
			replaced by a normal diet (especially fruit and vegetables).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The overall physiological response for continued heat storage is therefore
			<lb/>
			vasodilatation to increase skin temperature and then sweating leading to
			<lb/>
			profuse sweating (including ineffective dripping of some sweat losing
			<lb/>
			insignificant heat but important water). As &apos;core&apos; temperature continues to rise
			<lb/>
			and the skin is completely wet, hidromeiosis (a reduction in sweating) may
			<lb/>
			occur due to swelling and blocking of sweat glands in the wet humid
			<lb/>
			conditions <ref type="biblio">(3)</ref>. This is often confused with so-called sweat gland fatigue. The
			<lb/>
			decrease in sweating promotes a further, often rapid, increase in &apos;core&apos;<lb/>
			temperature to beyond 38 -39 °C where collapse may occur to above 41 °C
			<lb/>
			(rectal temperature), where heat stroke may occur. There will be mental
			<lb/>
			confusion, behavioural changes, failure in central nervous thermoregulation
			<lb/>
			and sweating and death with eventual denaturing of body protein. NIOSH
			<lb/>
			(1986) <ref type="biblio">(2)</ref> consider age, gender, body fat, drugs (including alcohol) and other
			<lb/>
			non-thermal disorders as important individual factors. There is a large
			<lb/>
			individual variability in the mechanisms of response, which are not fully
			<lb/>
			understood. Physical fitness however, has been shown to be of great
			<lb/>
			importance. The mnemonic, &apos;SHAFTS&apos; can be used to advise people how to
			<lb/>
			increase tolerance to heat. This is: Sensible (i.e. appropriate behaviour;
			<lb/>
			reduce exercise or work activity); Hydrated; Acclimatised; Fit; Thin: and Sober
			<lb/>
			(including avoidance of alcohol and other drugs).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Heat physiology and health
			<lb/>
		</head>
		<p>
			Leithead and Lind (1964)
			<ref type="biblio">(4)</ref>
			conclude that heat disorders occur for one or
			<lb/>
			more of three reasons:
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<list>
			<item>1. the existence of factors such as dehydration or lack of acclimatization;
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				2. the lack of proper appreciation of the dangers of heat, either on the part of
				<lb/>
				the supervising authority or of the individuals at risk; and
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				3. accidental or unforeseen circumstances leading to exposure to very high
				<lb/>
				heat stress.
				<lb/>
			</item>
		</list>
		
		<p>They conclude that many heat-related deaths can be attributed to neglect and
			<lb/>
			lack of consideration and that even when disorders do occur much can be
			<lb/>
			done if all the requirements for the correct and prompt remedial treatment are
			<lb/>
			available. In climates such as those found in Singapore, military personnel are
			<lb/>
			exposed to hot, humid conditions and must carry out essential tasks in
			<lb/>
			protective clothing. Although heat stroke will occur, severe consequences
			<lb/>
			have been avoided by organizational methods including extensive training of
			<lb/>
			personnel and an efficient back-up system to transport casualties rapidly to
			<lb/>
			hospital.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>There are a number of classification systems for heat disorders. The
			<lb/>
			mechanisms are summarized in <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref> (5) and a description is provided in
			<lb/>
			<ref type="table">Table 1</ref>
			(6).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>INSERT FIGURE 1 ABOUT HERE
			<lb/>
			INSERT TABLE 1 ABOUT HERE
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>There are a number of other complaints related to heat exposure. For
			<lb/>
			example, in mildly sunburnt skin sweat can be trapped and accumulate under
			<lb/>
			the dead surface layer and cause discomfort as well as reducing evaporative
			<lb/>
			efficiency. In industries where chemicals and particulates are present in the
			<lb/>
			air they may interact with sweat on the skin surface to cause complaints. The
			<lb/>
			interaction between chemical substances in the air and a sweating person has
			<lb/>
			yet to be fully explored but can be significant. Pollution and poor air quality
			<lb/>
			may be an additional hazard along with heat and in combination may cause
			<lb/>
			and exacerbate respiratory disorders. Protective clothing and equipment may
			<lb/>
			promote sweating and will reduce the ability to evaporate sweat to cool down.
			<lb/>
			This will often increase the risk they the clothing is protecting against and
			<lb/>
			dangerous levels can occur at what would normally be considered to be
			<lb/>
			moderate temperatures.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Acclimatisation
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Acclimatisation refers to the increased ability of a person to reduce heat strain
			<lb/>
			due to experience of exposure to heat. It takes two forms: behavioural and
			<lb/>
			physiological. Behavioural acclimatisation is most effective and is mainly
			<lb/>
			gained in the context of the heat exposure. If we go to a hot climate we soon
			<lb/>
			Parsons<lb/>learn to drink appropriately and keep out of the sun. Physiological
			<lb/>
			acclimatisation involves adjustments to our ability to thermoregulate to allow a
			<lb/>
			greater capacity for and more efficient vasodilatation and in particular
			<lb/>
			sweating. When people become exposed to heat they increase their ability to
			<lb/>
			sweat <ref type="biblio">(7)</ref>. Significant changes occur even after only three days of exposure. It
			<lb/>
			is possible to gain physiological acclimatisation by exposing people for a few
			<lb/>
			hours per day to high levels of heat (e.g. in a laboratory -called acclimation)
			<lb/>
			and this is often used as a technique to reduce strain when people are about
			<lb/>
			to travel to a hot climate.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In short, if a person is used to being exposed to heat then they will adjust
			<lb/>
			physiologically to some extent and learn how to behave to tolerate the heat. In
			<lb/>
			extremely hot tropical environments this &quot;behavioural change&quot; will include a
			<lb/>
			reduction of physical activity workload, and an increase of frequency and
			<lb/>
			length of rest breaks. If they are not used to the heat and the weather
			<lb/>
			suddenly becomes hot then they will be more vulnerable to heat strain.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Maintaining health in heat waves
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>There is no reason why a person should suffer ill health in a heatwave as the
			<lb/>
			principles of reducing heat strain are well understood. The requirement is that
			<lb/>
			we have adequate management systems based upon these principles.
			<lb/>
			Physiological responses to heat have generally been studied on fit young
			<lb/>
			males and under conditions that could be regarded as very hot and towards
			<lb/>
			the extremes of weather conditions. For less fit and vulnerable people,
			<lb/>
			physiological responses such as increased heart rate, prolonged sweating
			<lb/>
			and respiratory responses (related to air quality or dryness) will pose a threat.
			<lb/>
			Increased body temperature will eventually be a threat to health but it may not
			<lb/>
			be the primary cause of illness and death in a heatwave.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>So what do we do to maintain health? We set up a management system to
			<lb/>
			ensure that people are not exposed to unacceptable heat stress. Heat stress
			<lb/>
			is determined by the interaction of air temperature, radiant temperature, air
			<lb/>
			velocity and humidity. It is also greatly influenced by the clothes a person is
			<lb/>
			wearing and the activity they are performing. Consideration of these six
			<lb/>
			factors must form the basis of any management programme. A full discussion
			<lb/>
			of management programme for heat-waves is provided in <ref type="biblio">(8)</ref>. Of particular
			<lb/>
			importance will be the availability of household water and electrical power.
			<lb/>
			Moving people away from hot homes to cooler areas (e.g. public libraries or
			<lb/>
			modern shopping centres) will reduce heat strain but may not be practicable.
			<lb/>
			The use of water provides an effective and often practical method of keeping
			<lb/>
			cool in the heat. Simply plunging the hands and feet into cool water reduces
			<lb/>
			thermal strain. Immersing hands and arms in cool water is a practical way for
			<lb/>
			vulnerable people to avoid health problems in the heat. For those with a bath
			<lb/>
			tub, running a normal warm bath (e.g. 38 o C water temperature) to half full and
			<lb/>
			getting in, then running in cool water to fill the bath allows a non-stressful
			<lb/>
			method of keeping cool. The initial warm water will promote vasodilatation and
			<lb/>
			will not cause thermal shock, which will occur with cool water and raise blood
			<lb/>
			pressure. The slow cooling will not be detected by the body and at around
			<lb/>
			30 o C a &apos;cool&apos; bath will greatly enhance heat loss.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Spraying water on the face or exposed skin and enhancing evaporative
			<lb/>
			cooling with fans for example will reduce heat loss even when the air
			<lb/>
			temperature is above desired internal body temperature. The direction and
			<lb/>
			Parsons
			<lb/>
			strength of fans however has to be controlled as evaporation of mucous from
			<lb/>
			the airways and moisture from the eyes can cause irritation and respiratory
			<lb/>
			problems.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The use of air conditioning is very effective in reducing air temperature and
			<lb/>
			hence thermal strain. It requires electrical power however and if electric grid
			<lb/>
			systems cannot meet capacity then lack of power can cause a critical
			<lb/>
			problem. The above discussion provides methods for keeping cool in a heat
			<lb/>
			wave. It is not exhaustive and the reader is referred to <ref type="biblio">(8)</ref> for a fuller
			<lb/>
			discussion.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Maintaining comfort in heat waves
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Conditions for thermal comfort are well described by Fanger (1970) <ref type="biblio">(9)</ref> and
			<lb/>
			were later adopted worldwide in ISO 7730 (2005) <ref type="biblio">(10)</ref>. They are, that for a
			<lb/>
			person to be in thermal comfort they must be in heat balance (maintaining
			<lb/>
			internal body temperature) and that skin temperatures and sweat rates
			<lb/>
			must be within comfort limits. A method is derived from those three
			<lb/>
			premises that allows the prediction (from air temperature, radiant temperature,
			<lb/>
			air velocity, humidity, clothing and activity) of thermal comfort conditions and
			<lb/>
			of any thermal discomfort. The Predicted Mean Vote (PMV) index predicts the
			<lb/>
			mean rating of a large group of people exposed to thermal conditions (six
			<lb/>
			factors above) on the scale: +3 hot; +2 warm; +1 slightly warm; 0 neutral; -1
			<lb/>
			slightly cool; -2 cool; -3 cold. For a given PMV value the Predicted Percentage
			<lb/>
			of Dissatisfied (PPD) provides the likely level of dissatisfaction.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Parsons (2003) <ref type="biblio">(1)</ref> and Hodder and Parsons (2006) <ref type="biblio">(11)</ref> extend
			the scale
			<lb/>
			from 7 to 11 points by adding very hot/cold and extremely hot/cold on either
			<lb/>
			end. They then provide a simple rule of thumb method for taking account of
			<lb/>
			the direct sun on a person. For every 200Wm -2 of solar radiation (from 0Wm -2
			<lb/>
			totally cloudy to 600 blue sky to 1000 absolute maximum) the PMV (now
			<lb/>
			PMVsolar) is increased by one scale value. It is emphasised that this rule of
			<lb/>
			thumb provides a simplistic practical method which accounts for main effects.
			<lb/>
			For a more accurate assessment, direct and diffuse radiation, depending
			<lb/>
			upon turbidity and cloudiness, elevation of the sun, posture of the person and
			<lb/>
			more, also play a role but involve increasingly complex analysis.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>To take account of the ability for people to change behaviour or adapt to the
			<lb/>
			environment, Parsons (2003) <ref type="biblio">(1)</ref> suggested an Iequiv index which allows the
			<lb/>
			clothing insulation value, used in the calculation of PMV, to be adjusted to
			<lb/>
			take account of the effects of any adaptive opportunities in the environment
			<lb/>
			(e.g. ability to reduce clothing, open windows etc). The Iequiv method provides a
			<lb/>
			simplistic but direct method of accounting for adaptive opportunities available
			<lb/>
			to people. Estimates of adaptive opportunity however remain necessarily
			<lb/>
			subjective. There are other, less rational or &apos;causal&apos; adaptive models which
			<lb/>
			relate indoor comfort temperatures to outside conditions based upon data
			<lb/>
			from thermal comfort surveys. (e.g. 12). The &apos;causal&apos; model assumed in such
			<lb/>
			models is that the effects of the adaptive opportunity, such as that used in the
			<lb/>
			Iequiv method, are captured in the behaviour of people to outside conditions, for
			<lb/>
			example, a reduction in clothing when outside temperatures are high. The Iequiv
			<lb/>
			method suggests that a consequence of this is to provide the suggestion that
			<lb/>
			for reasonable levels of adaptive opportunity, it will not be necessary to cool
			<lb/>
			offices or homes below 25 o C to provide thermal comfort. This measure is
			<lb/>
			related to sustainable thermal comfort discussions <ref type="biblio">(13)</ref> and will also have the
			<lb/>
			Parsons
			<lb/>
			effect of significantly reducing electrical power requirements and hence
			<lb/>
			avoiding power failure. It is interesting to note that in Japan a few years ago,
			<lb/>
			the government in Tokyo ran a campaign to set a lower limit for cooling offices
			<lb/>
			to 28 o C air temperature. The prime minister at the time advised businessmen
			<lb/>
			not to wear a tie. The 28 o C limit clearly requires less energy to achieve in hot
			<lb/>
			outside conditions than a limit of 25 o C or below, however it is likely to cause
			<lb/>
			some discomfort. The practical point is that it is common practice to cool
			<lb/>
			rooms to around 20 o C (and often causes cold discomfort) in hot outside
			<lb/>
			conditions. This is an unnecessary and inefficient use of energy. An energy
			<lb/>
			saving by not cooling below 25 o C would be highly significant world-wide and it
			<lb/>
			is generally agreed would still allow thermal comfort.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Maintaining productivity in heat waves
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The most effective way to maintain human performance and productivity
			<lb/>
			during a heatwave will be to provide thermal comfort conditions. This is not
			<lb/>
			always possible however and in hot conditions productivity is likely to fall. This
			<lb/>
			is by no means certain however and motivation, morale and team spirit will all
			<lb/>
			be significant factors. There have been numerous studies into the effects of
			<lb/>
			heat on manual dexterity and cognitive performance. The most direct and
			<lb/>
			measurable effect on productivity however is &quot;time off task&quot; <ref type="biblio">(1)</ref> caused
			by
			<lb/>
			work having to be stopped or due to heat causing a distraction to people (e.g.
			<lb/>
			concentrating or finding fans or adjusting control systems or simply paying
			<lb/>
			attention to the heat). This will apply to people in homes, offices and other
			<lb/>
			work places. The relationship between the level of distraction caused by heat
			<lb/>
			and the level of heat stress is not known. Further investigation is needed if the
			<lb/>
			full economic costs of heat waves are to be determined. For practical
			<lb/>
			purposes the costs in terms of health and loss in productivity can be weighed
			<lb/>
			against the costs of systems for ensuring the avoidance of unacceptable
			<lb/>
			thermal strain during heatwaves.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Conclusions
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<list>
			<item>
				1. Much is known about human response to heat and basic principles can
				<lb/>
				be used to provide guidance on effective heat management systems.
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				2. With electrical power and especially water, it is possible to avoid health
				<lb/>
				problems due to heat.
				<lb/>
			</item>
			<item>
				3. For sedentary and light activities it is not necessary to cool rooms
				<lb/>
				below 25 o C to provide thermal comfort.
				<lb/>
			
			</item>
			<item>
				4.There is a need to determine the relationships between levels of heat
				<lb/>
				stress and how much distraction and time off work it causes.
				<lb/>
			</item>
		</list>
		
		<figure type="table">Table 1. Classification, medical aspects and prevention of heat illness
			<lb/>
			(from(6) )
			<lb/>
			Category and clinical features Predisposing factors
			<lb/>
			Underlying physiological
			<lb/>
			disturbance
			<lb/>
			Treatment
			<lb/>
			Prevention
			<lb/>
			1. Temperature Regulation Heatstroke
			<lb/>
			Heatstroke: (1) Hot dry
			<lb/>
			skin usually red, mottled
			<lb/>
			or cyanotic; (2) re
			<lb/>
			t , 40.5
			<lb/>
			°C (104 °F) and over; (3)
			<lb/>
			confusion, loss of
			<lb/>
			consciousness,
			<lb/>
			convulsions, re
			<lb/>
			t continues
			<lb/>
			to rise; fatal if treatment
			<lb/>
			delayed.
			<lb/>
			(1) Sustained exertion
			<lb/>
			in heat by
			<lb/>
			unacclimatized workers;
			<lb/>
			(2) Lack of physical
			<lb/>
			fitness and obesity; (3)
			<lb/>
			Recent alcohol intake;
			<lb/>
			(4) Dehydration; (5)
			<lb/>
			Individual susceptibility;
			<lb/>
			and (6) Chronic
			<lb/>
			cardiovascular disease.
			<lb/>
			Failure of the central
			<lb/>
			drive for sweating
			<lb/>
			(cause unknown)
			<lb/>
			leading to loss of
			<lb/>
			evaporative cooling and
			<lb/>
			an uncontrolled
			<lb/>
			accelerating rise in re
			<lb/>
			t ,
			<lb/>
			there may be partial
			<lb/>
			rather than complete
			<lb/>
			failure of sweating.
			<lb/>
			Immediate and rapid
			<lb/>
			cooling by immersion in
			<lb/>
			chilled water with
			<lb/>
			massage or by wrapping
			<lb/>
			in wet sheet with vigorous
			<lb/>
			fanning with cool dry air,
			<lb/>
			avoid overcooling, treat
			<lb/>
			shock if present.
			<lb/>
			Medical screening of
			<lb/>
			workers, selection based
			<lb/>
			on health and physical
			<lb/>
			fitness, acclimatization
			<lb/>
			for 5-7 days by graded
			<lb/>
			work and heat exposure,
			<lb/>
			monitoring workers
			<lb/>
			during sustained work in
			<lb/>
			severe heat.
			<lb/>
			2. Circulatory Hypostasis Heat Syncope
			<lb/>
			Fainting while standing
			<lb/>
			erect and immobile in
			<lb/>
			heat.
			<lb/>
			Lack of acclimatization.
			<lb/>
			Pooling of blood in
			<lb/>
			dilated vessels of skin
			<lb/>
			and lower parts of body.
			<lb/>
			Remove to cooler area,
			<lb/>
			rest recumbent position,
			<lb/>
			recovery prompt and
			<lb/>
			complete.
			<lb/>
			Acclimatization,
			<lb/>
			intermittent activity to
			<lb/>
			assist venous return to
			<lb/>
			the heart.
			<lb/>
			3. Water and/or Salt
			<lb/>
			Depletion
			<lb/>
			(a) Heat Exhaustion
			<lb/>
			(1) Fatigue, nausea,
			<lb/>
			headache, giddiness; (2)
			<lb/>
			Skin clammy and moist;
			<lb/>
			complexion pale, muddy,
			<lb/>
			or hectic flush; (3) May
			<lb/>
			faint on standing with
			<lb/>
			rapid thready pulse and
			<lb/>
			low blood pressure; (4)
			<lb/>
			Oral temperature normal
			<lb/>
			or low but rectal
			<lb/>
			temperature usually
			<lb/>
			elevated (37.5-38.5 °C)
			<lb/>
			(99.5-101.3 °F); water
			<lb/>
			restriction type; urine
			<lb/>
			volume small, highly
			<lb/>
			concentrated; salt
			<lb/>
			restriction type; urine less
			<lb/>
			concentrated, chlorides
			<lb/>
			less than 3 g/l.
			<lb/>
			(1) Sustained exertion
			<lb/>
			in heat; (2) Lack of
			<lb/>
			acclimatization; and (3)
			<lb/>
			Failure to replace water
			<lb/>
			lost in sweat.
			<lb/>
			(1) Dehydration from
			<lb/>
			deficiency of water; (2)
			<lb/>
			Depletion of circulating
			<lb/>
			blood volume; (3)
			<lb/>
			Circulatory strain from
			<lb/>
			competing demands for
			<lb/>
			blood flow to skin and to
			<lb/>
			active muscles.
			<lb/>
			Remove to cooler
			<lb/>
			environment, rest
			<lb/>
			recumbent position,
			<lb/>
			administer fluids by
			<lb/>
			mouth, keep at rest until
			<lb/>
			urine volume indicates
			<lb/>
			that water balances have
			<lb/>
			been restored.
			<lb/>
			Acclimatize workers
			<lb/>
			using a breaking-in
			<lb/>
			schedule for 5 to 7 days,
			<lb/>
			supplement dietary salt
			<lb/>
			only during
			<lb/>
			acclimatization, ample
			<lb/>
			drinking water to be
			<lb/>
			available at all times and
			<lb/>
			to be taken frequently
			<lb/>
			during work day.
			<lb/>
			(b) Heat Cramps
			<lb/>
			Painful spasms of
			<lb/>
			muscles used during work
			<lb/>
			(arms, legs, or
			<lb/>
			abdominal); onset during
			<lb/>
			or after work hours.
			<lb/>
			(1) heavy sweating
			<lb/>
			during hot work; (2)
			<lb/>
			Drinking large volumes
			<lb/>
			of water without
			<lb/>
			replacing salt loss.
			<lb/>
			Loss of body salt in
			<lb/>
			sweat, water intake
			<lb/>
			dilutes electrolytes,
			<lb/>
			water enters muscles,
			<lb/>
			causing spasm.
			<lb/>
			Salted liquids by mouth, or
			<lb/>
			more prompt relief by I-V
			<lb/>
			infusion.
			<lb/>
			Adequate salt intake with
			<lb/>
			meals; in unacclimatized
			<lb/>
			workers supplement salt
			<lb/>
			intake at meals.
			<lb/>
			4. Skin Eruptions
			<lb/>
			(a) Heat Rash (miliaria rubra; &apos;prickly heat&apos;)
			<lb/>
			Profuse tiny raised red
			<lb/>
			vesicles (blister-like) on
			<lb/>
			affected areas, pricking
			<lb/>
			sensations during heat
			<lb/>
			exposure.
			<lb/>
			Unrelieved exposure to
			<lb/>
			humid heat with skin
			<lb/>
			continuously wet with
			<lb/>
			unevaporated sweat.
			<lb/>
			Plugging of sweat gland
			<lb/>
			ducts with retention of
			<lb/>
			sweat and inflammatory
			<lb/>
			reaction.
			<lb/>
			Mild drying lotions, skin
			<lb/>
			cleanliness to prevent
			<lb/>
			infection.
			<lb/>
			Cool sleeping quarters to
			<lb/>
			allow skin to dry between
			<lb/>
			heat exposures.
			<lb/>
			(b) Anhydrotic Heat Exhaustion (miliaria profunda)
			<lb/>
			Extensive areas of skin
			<lb/>
			which do not sweat on
			<lb/>
			heat exposure, but
			<lb/>
			present gooseflesh
			<lb/>
			appearance, which
			<lb/>
			subsides with cool
			<lb/>
			environments; associated
			<lb/>
			with incapacitation in heat.
			<lb/>
			Weeks or months of
			<lb/>
			constant exposure to
			<lb/>
			climatic heat with
			<lb/>
			previous history of
			<lb/>
			extensive heat rash and
			<lb/>
			sunburn.
			<lb/>
			Skin trauma (heat rash;
			<lb/>
			sunburn) causes sweat
			<lb/>
			retention deep in skin,
			<lb/>
			reduced evaporative
			<lb/>
			cooling causes heat
			<lb/>
			intolerance.
			<lb/>
			No effective treatment
			<lb/>
			available for anhydrotic
			<lb/>
			areas of skin, recovery of
			<lb/>
			sweating occurs gradually
			<lb/>
			in return to cooler climate.
			<lb/>
			Treat heat rash and
			<lb/>
			avoid further skin trauma
			<lb/>
			by sunburn, periodic
			<lb/>
			relief from sustained
			<lb/>
			heat.
			<lb/>
			5. Behavioural Disorders
			<lb/>
			(a) Heat Fatigue -<lb/>Transient
			<lb/>
			Impaired performance of
			<lb/>
			skilled sensorimotor,
			<lb/>
			mental, or vigilance tasks,
			<lb/>
			in heat.
			<lb/>
			Performance decrement
			<lb/>
			greater in
			<lb/>
			unacclimatized and
			<lb/>
			unskilled worker.
			<lb/>
			Discomfort and
			<lb/>
			physiologic strain.
			<lb/>
			Not indicated unless
			<lb/>
			accompanied by other
			<lb/>
			heat illness.
			<lb/>
			Acclimatization and
			<lb/>
			training for work in the
			<lb/>
			heat.
			<lb/>
			(b) Heat Fatigue -<lb/>Chronic
			<lb/>
			Reduced performance
			<lb/>
			capacity, lowering of self-<lb/>imposed standards of
			<lb/>
			social behaviour (e.g.
			<lb/>
			alcoholic over-<lb/>indulgence), inability to
			<lb/>
			concentrate, etc.
			<lb/>
			Workers at risk come
			<lb/>
			from temperate
			<lb/>
			climates, for long
			<lb/>
			residence in tropical
			<lb/>
			latitudes.
			<lb/>
			Psychosocial stresses
			<lb/>
			probably as important
			<lb/>
			as heat stress, may
			<lb/>
			involve hormonal
			<lb/>
			imbalance but no
			<lb/>
			positive evidence.
			<lb/>
			Medical treatment for
			<lb/>
			serious cases, speedy
			<lb/>
			relief of symptoms on
			<lb/>
			returning home.
			<lb/>
			Orientation on life in hot
			<lb/>
			regions (customs,
			<lb/>
			climate, living conditions,
			<lb/>
			etc.).
			<lb/>
			Heat Stroke
			<lb/>
			Heat Stress
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<p>Figure 1: Causes of heat stroke (from (5))</p>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
