<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			The Arctic, has warmed substantially over last few decades. A recent study shows
			<lb/>
			that temperatures over the last century warmed almost three times faster in the Arctic
			<lb/>
			than elsewhere in the Northern Hemisphere, reversing a 2000 year cooling trend, and
			<lb/>
			outpacing current climate model predictions <ref type="biblio">(Kaufman et al., 2009)</ref>. This rapid warming
			<lb/>
			trend is anticipated to continue into the next century with temperature increases
			<lb/>
			exceeding those predicted in the rest of the Northern Hemisphere and will result in
			<lb/>
			accelerated loss of land and sea ice, an increased rate of sea level rise, with global
			<lb/>
			consequences. These changes are already impacting local communities who have
			<lb/>
			observed profound changes in their local environments, and is leading to significant
			<lb/>
			economic and cultural upheaval particularly for the indigenous peoples of the Arctic
			<lb/>
			<ref type="biblio">(ACIA 2005)</ref>. Because climate change is more advanced in the Arctic than other
			regions
			<lb/>
			of the world, the Arctic can play a vital role in preparing the world for what is to come.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Resident indigenous populations of the Arctic are uniquely vulnerable to climate change
			<lb/>
			because of their close relationship with, and dependence on, the land, sea and natural
			<lb/>
			resources for their well being <ref type="biblio">(Hess, et al., 2008)</ref>. Direct health threats from
			climate
			<lb/>
			change include morbidity and mortality resulting from increasing extreme events (storms,
			<lb/>
			floods, increased heat and cold) and an increased incidence of injury and mortality
			<lb/>
			associated with unpredictable ice and storm conditions. Indirect effects include increased
			<lb/>
			mental and social stress related to changes in environment and loss of traditional lifestyle;
			<lb/>
			potential changes in bacterial and viral diseases; and decreased access to quality water
			<lb/>
			sources <ref type="biblio">(Parkinson IOM 2008; Parkinson and Berner 2009)</ref>. Some regions are at risk
			for
			<lb/>
			increasing illness due to failing sanitation infrastructure resulting from changes in
			<lb/>
			permafrost and storm surge. Some regions will also experience changes in diet resulting
			<lb/>
			from changes in subsistence species distribution and accessibility <ref type="biblio">(Vors and Boyce 2009)</ref>.
			<lb/>
			This may result in a shift away from a traditional subsistence diet to a more western diet.
			<lb/>
			While this shift may be beneficial, providing a more varied and reliable diet, however the
			<lb/>
			increased accessibility to processed foods, high in saturated fats and sugar, may result in
			<lb/>
			an increase the incidence of obesity, diabetes, cardiovascular disease and cancer (
			<ref type="biblio">(Orr
				<lb/>
				1994; Bjerragaard 2004)
			</ref>
			. Projected warming, will affect the transport, distribution and
			<lb/>
			behavior of contaminants, further threatening the safety of the traditional food supply and
			<lb/>
			potentially increasing human exposure <ref type="biblio">(Kramer and Berner 2005)</ref>. Higher temperatures
			<lb/>
			at lower latitudes will increase volatization of contaminants resulting in increased
			<lb/>
			delivery of contaminants to the Arctic. As precipitation increases over land, river flow
			<lb/>
			will increase resulting in greater delivery of contaminants to the coasts and oceans.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>These health impacts are taking place in the context of ongoing cultural and
			<lb/>
			socioeconomic changes occurring in Arctic communities. Climate change represents
			<lb/>
			another of many sources of stress on these northern societies and cultures as it affects the
			<lb/>
			relationship between the people and the land and environment, which will further stress
			<lb/>
			communities and individual psychosocial health. The potential impact on human health
			<lb/>
			will differ from place to place depending on regional, even local differences in climate
			<lb/>
			change as well as variations in health status and adaptive capacity of different
			<lb/>
			populations <ref type="biblio">(Hess et al., 2008)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Arctic populations have a long history of both endemic and epidemic infectious diseases
			<lb/>
			<ref type="biblio">(Parkinson et al., 2008)</ref>. Despite advances in antimicrobial therapy, and
			availability of
			<lb/>
			vaccines, high rates of invasive diseases caused by Streptococcus pneumoniae,
			<lb/>
			Haemophilus influenzae and Mycobacterium tuberculosis persist. Sharp seasonal
			<lb/>
			epidemics of viral respiratory infections also commonly occur. The over-use of
			<lb/>
			antimicrobial drugs in some regions has lead to the emergence of multi-resistant S.
			<lb/>
			pneumoniae, Helicobacter pylori, and methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus..
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The impact of climate on the incidence of these existing infectious disease challenges is
			<lb/>
			unknown. However it is known that inadequate housing and sanitation are already
			<lb/>
			important determinants of infectious disease transmission in many Arctic regions.
			<lb/>
			Damage to the sanitation infrastructure by melting permafrost or flooding may therefore
			<lb/>
			result in increased rates of hospitalization among children for respiratory infections, as
			<lb/>
			well as an increased rate of skin infections, and diarrheal diseases caused by bacterial,
			<lb/>
			viral, and parasitic pathogens <ref type="biblio">(Hennessy et al., 2008)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Some infectious diseases are unique to the Arctic and lifestyles of the indigenous
			<lb/>
			populations, and may increase in a warming Arctic. For example, many Arctic residents
			<lb/>
			depend on subsistence hunting, fishing and gathering for food and a predictable climate
			<lb/>
			for food storage. Food storage methods often include above ground air-drying of fish and
			<lb/>
			meat at ambient temperature, below ground cold storage on or near the permafrost, and
			<lb/>
			fermentation. Changes in climate may prevent the drying of fish or meat, resulting in
			<lb/>
			spoilage. Similarly loss of the permafrost may result in spoilage of food stored below
			<lb/>
			ground. Outbreaks of food-borne botulism occur sporadically in communities in the
			<lb/>
			Arctic and is caused by ingestion of improperly prepared fermented traditional foods
			<lb/>
			<ref type="biblio">(Sobel et al., 2004; Proulx 1997; Sorensen et al., 1993)</ref>. Because germination of
			<lb/>
			Clostridium botulinum spores and toxin production occurs at temperatures above 4C, it is
			<lb/>
			possible that warmer ambient temperatures in these regions associated with climate
			<lb/>
			change may result in an increase the rates of food-borne botulism. Out breaks of Vibrio
			<lb/>
			parahemolyticus gastroenteritis are commonly associated with sea water temperatures
			<lb/>
			above 15C. An outbreak of gastroenteritis caused by Vibrio. parahemolyticus was
			<lb/>
			documented among cruise ship passengers consuming raw oysters in Prince William
			<lb/>
			Sound, Alaska <ref type="biblio">(McLaughlin et al., 2005)</ref>, and provides direct evidence of an
			association
			<lb/>
			between rising sea water temperature and onset of illness. In order to prevent further
			<lb/>
			oyster farm outbreaks, a water temperature monitoring and shell-fish testing program has
			<lb/>
			been recommended. No additional outbreaks have been reported.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Warmer temperatures may allow an infected host animal species to survive winters in
			<lb/>
			larger numbers, increase in population and expand their range of habitation and thus
			<lb/>
			increase the opportunity to pass infections to humans. For example the climate related
			<lb/>
			northern expansion of the boreal forest in Alaska and northern Canada has favored the
			<lb/>
			steady northward advance of the beaver, extending the range of Giardia lamblia, a
			<lb/>
			parasitic infection of beaver that can infect other mammals, including humans who use
			<lb/>
			untreated surface water <ref type="biblio">(ACIA 2005)</ref>. Similarly warmer temperatures in the Arctic
			and
			<lb/>
			sub-Arctic regions could support the expansion of the geographical range and populations
			<lb/>
			of foxes and voles, common carriers of Echinococcus multilocularis and the cause of
			<lb/>
			alveolar echinococcus in humans <ref type="biblio">(Rausch 2003; Castrodale et al 2002)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Climate change may influence the density and distribution of animal hosts and mosquito
			<lb/>
			vectors which could result in an increase in human illness or a shift in the geographical
			<lb/>
			range of disease caused by these agents. West Nile virus entered the US in 1999, and in
			<lb/>
			subsequent years infected human, horse, mosquito and bird populations across the US
			<lb/>
			and as far north as northern Manitoba <ref type="biblio">(Parkinson and Butler 2005)</ref>. In the Russian
			<lb/>
			Federation infected birds and humans have been detected as far north as the region of
			<lb/>
			Novosibirsk <ref type="biblio">(Revich 2008)</ref>. In Sweden the incidence of tick-borne encephalitis (TBE)
			<lb/>
			has substantially increased since the mid-1980s . This increase corresponds to a trend of
			<lb/>
			milder winters and an earlier onset of spring resulting in an increase in the tick population
			<lb/>
			(Ixodes ricinus) that carries the virus responsible for TBE and other potential pathogens.
			<lb/>
			Similarly in Northeastern Canada, climate change is projected to result in a northward
			<lb/>
			shift in the range of Ixodes scapularis,a tick that carries Borrellia borgdoreri the etiologic
			<lb/>
			agent of Lyme disease <ref type="biblio">(Ogden et al., 2005)</ref>. Major increases in the prevalence of
			<lb/>
			hantavirus and tick borne infections in human populations in northern Europe and central
			<lb/>
			Asia during the last decade have been associated with rodent population irruptions linked
			<lb/>
			to a series of exceptionally warm winters <ref type="biblio">(Pettersson et al., 2008; Gray et al.,
				2009)</ref>. In
			<lb/>
			the unexpected outbreak of Puumula virus (a Hanta virus) in northern Sweden in 2007 the
			<lb/>
			incidence was found to be 313/100.000 inhabitants in Vasterbotten County. The increase
			<lb/>
			in the rodent population, milder weather and less snow cover were probably contributing
			<lb/>
			factors <ref type="biblio">(Pettersson et al., 2008)</ref>. Similar outbreaks have been noted in the Russian
			<lb/>
			Federation <ref type="biblio">(Revich, 2008)</ref>. Whether or not disease in humans is a result of these
			climate-<lb/>induced alterations of vector range depends on many other factors, such as land-use
			<lb/>
			practices, human behavior, human population density, and adequacy of the public health
			<lb/>
			response.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The public health response to these emerging microbial threats should be focused
			<lb/>
			regionally include enhancing the public health capacity to monitor diseases with
			<lb/>
			potentially large public health impacts, including respiratory diseases in children, skin
			<lb/>
			infections, and diarrheal diseases, particularly in communities being undermined by
			<lb/>
			melting permafrost that is damaging water and sewage systems. Monitoring certain
			<lb/>
			vector borne diseases, such as West Nile virus, Lyme disease, TBE and Puumla virus
			<lb/>
			should be priorities in areas at the margins of focal regions known to support both animal
			<lb/>
			and insect vectors and where climate change may promote the geographic expansion of
			<lb/>
			vectors .
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Because Arctic populations are relatively small and widely dispersed region-specific
			<lb/>
			detection of significant trends in emerging climate related infectious diseases may be
			<lb/>
			delayed. This difficulty may be overcome by linking regional monitoring systems for the
			<lb/>
			purposes of sharing standardized information on climate sensitive infectious diseases of
			<lb/>
			mutual concern over larger areas. Efforts should be made to harmonize notifiable disease
			<lb/>
			registries, laboratory methods and clinical surveillance definitions across administrative
			<lb/>
			jurisdictions to allow comparable disease reporting and analysis. An example of such a
			<lb/>
			network is the International Circumpolar Surveillance system for emerging infectious
			<lb/>
			diseases. This network links hospital and public health laboratories together for the
			<lb/>
			purposes of monitoring invasive bacterial diseases and tuberculosis in Arctic populations
			<lb/>
			<ref type="biblio">(Parkinson et al., 2008)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Public health capacity should be enhanced to promptly respond to infectious disease
			<lb/>
			food-and waterborne outbreaks (botulism, or gastroenteritis caused by Giardia lamblia,
			<lb/>
			Cryptosporidium or Vibro parahemolyticus). Public health research is needed to
			<lb/>
			determine the baseline prevalence of potential climate sensitive infectious diseases (e.g.,
			<lb/>
			West Nile virus, Puumla virus, Borrellia borgdoferi, Brucella spp., Echinococcus spp.,
			<lb/>
			Toxoplasma spp, and intestinal protozoa) in both human and animal hosts in regions
			<lb/>
			where emergence may be expected. Such studies can be used to accumulate additional
			<lb/>
			evidence of the effect of climate change or weather on infectious disease emergence, to
			<lb/>
			guide early detection and public health intervention strategies, and to provide science
			<lb/>
			based support for public health actions on climate change.
		</p>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
