<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>Introduction
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>There is an increasing literature today on cosmopolitanism and global justice in
			<lb/>
			the disciplines of philosophy and international relations. Global Justice: A
			<lb/>
			Cosmopolitan Account consolidates and extends Gillian Brock&apos;s important
			<lb/>
			contributions to this literature. While some sections are based on previously
			<lb/>
			published essays, the book represents a reworking, application and deepening of
			<lb/>
			her ideas. In this review essay I ofer an overview of the content of the book
			<lb/>
			followed by brief critical appraisal of its central arguments. My specific concern is
			<lb/>
			that Brock gives an insufciently robust account of human rights with which to
			<lb/>
			define the nature of global justice and thereby leaves cosmopolitanism too
			<lb/>
			vulnerable to the normative pull of local and traditional moral conceptions that
			<lb/>
			fall short of the universalism that cosmopolitans should be able to embrace.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Summary of the book
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The introduction presents the core thesis of the book: that the cosmopolitan
			<lb/>
			vision, which sees the moral status of each individual globally as equal, can lead
			<lb/>
			to a viable conception of, and program for, global justice. Brock draws several
			<lb/>
			distinctions within cosmopolitanism. One is derived from Samuel Schefer and
			<lb/>
			distinguishes &quot;extreme&quot; from &quot;moderate&quot; cosmopolitanism. An extreme
			<lb/>
			cosmopolitan thinks there is a single universally valid theory which can justify
			<lb/>
			the cosmopolitan outlook, while a moderate cosmopolitan thinks that diferent
			<lb/>
			cultural traditions can ground cosmopolitan policies upon their own moral
			<lb/>
			premises. A second distinction is that between &quot;weak&quot; and &quot;strong&quot;<lb/>
			cosmopolitanism where the former pursues a minimal standard of global justice
			<lb/>
			while the latter seeks stronger forms of global egalitarianism. It will transpire
			<lb/>
			that Brock is both a moderate and a weak cosmopolitan in these senses.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Chapter two ofers a literature review centred on oohn Rawls&apos;s The Law of
			<lb/>
			Peoples 1 . Brock ofers a brief overview of that book and rehearses the
			<lb/>
			considerable debate which it has generated. She rightly points out that those
			<lb/>
			familiar with debates around Rawls could skip this chapter. Yet it does serve to
			<lb/>
			set up the problems that she goes on to deal with.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The thesis of the next chapter is that cosmopolitans should not support a
			<lb/>
			globalised version of Rawls&apos;s diference principle as derived from his A Theory of
			<lb/>
			Justice, but should rather support a &quot;minimum standard principle&quot; in which
			<lb/>
			justice consists in the provision of social goods sufcient to allow even the
			<lb/>
			poorest to live a life of simple human dignity by having their basic needs met.
			<lb/>
			Brock imagines a &quot;normative thought experiment&quot; not unlike Rawls&apos;s original
			<lb/>
			position in which delegates are randomly selected to attend a global conference
			<lb/> &quot;to fesh out what we can reasonably expect of one another in a way that avoids
			<lb/>
			inappropriate partiality&quot; <ref type="biblio">(48)</ref>. She argues that it is a minimum standard principle
			<lb/>
			that would be agreed to in such a scenario. She supports this with empirical
			<lb/>
			research which shows that people in such situations do actually prefer the
			<lb/>
			principle that, &quot;The most just distribution of income is that which maximizes the
			<lb/>
			average income only after a certain specified minimum income is guaranteed to
			<lb/>
			everyone&quot; <ref type="biblio">(55)</ref>. The problem with the diference principle and that of equality
			of
			<lb/>
			opportunity is that it is not easy to define the social goods in respect of which fair
			<lb/>
			distributions or equality should obtain without appealing to culturally specific
			<lb/>
			conceptions of such social goods. The issue of the goods which should be
			<lb/>
			distributed justly cannot be overcome in a world marked by moral pluralism.
			<lb/>
			Accordingly, it is better to focus on what is needed to live a decent life than on
			<lb/>
			the &quot;maximin&quot; principle or on equality. Without explaining exactly how, Brock
			<lb/>
			suggests that a needs approach, like Martha Nussbaum&apos;s capabilities approach,
			<lb/>
			can undergird the justification of basic human rights. Indeed, she argues that it is
			<lb/>
			superior to, and more widely applicable than, a discourse on rights because the
			<lb/>
			rights discourse is convincing only in the more liberal of the world&apos;s cultures.
			<lb/>
			Moreover, the focus on needs helps us to imagine a realistic utopia. Rather than
			<lb/>
			saying that a world order is just if it honours everyone&apos;s rights, Brock argues that
			<lb/>
			a global distribution is just if it meets everyone&apos;s basic needs, where such needs
			<lb/>
			are the conditions and provisions that are necessary for meaningful human
			<lb/>
			agency.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Chapter four discusses global governance. Brock distinguishes this from any
			<lb/>
			form of global government which would extinguish national sovereignties.
			<lb/>
			Rather, the issue is one of balancing the rights of sovereignty -which are already
			<lb/>
			declining as a result of globalization -with the need for global cooperation in
			<lb/>
			pursuit of global goals. The unfettered pursuit of the national interest on the part
			<lb/>
			of states is inimical to global justice. But, says Brock following Thomas Pogge, if
			<lb/>
			global governance is an instrument to secure justice, then it is currently a very
			<lb/>
			poor one. In order to improve global governance, it should be made more
			<lb/>
			responsive. One way that has been suggested for doing that is to make it more
			<lb/>
			democratic. Brock reports on debates between David Held and Will Kymlicka on
			<lb/>
			what social conditions are necessary to democratic participation. Brock doubts
			<lb/>
			whether a shared collective identity is necessary for authentic democratic
			<lb/>
			deliberation. Awareness of common problems, vulnerabilities and
			<lb/>
			interdependence, determination to solve common problems, and minimal shared
			<lb/>
			values may be sufficient.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>For her part, Brock proposes a model of &quot;responsive democracy&quot; <ref type="biblio">(104)</ref> which is
			<lb/>
			efective in attending to people&apos;s interests and accountable to the people
			<lb/>
			afected. On this model agency could be given to suitable experts or delegates
			<lb/>
			who are responsive to their constituencies. The International Criminal Court is
			<lb/>
			ofered as an example. She argues that we pursue global democracy not to
			<lb/>
			enhance political agency but to meet people&apos;s needs and interests. The latter
			<lb/>
			can be achieved by making institutions more responsive and by giving experts
			<lb/>
			more of a say. Moreover, while future generations are not political agents they
			<lb/>
			do have interests. Democracy should not be held hostage to current public
			<lb/>
			opinion. It is accountability that is most important. Brock concludes that global
			<lb/>
			governance must be efective and accountable, and responsive forms of
			<lb/>
			democracy can fulfil these desiderata even if they are less than fully
			<lb/>
			participatory.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Chapter five begins a series of chapters that make concrete proposals for making
			<lb/>
			the world more just. It discusses Pogge&apos;s proposals for a global resources
			<lb/>
			dividend and also his criticisms of the borrowing and selling privileges enjoyed
			<lb/>
			by despotic governments, and goes on to propose a series of international taxes,
			<lb/>
			including the Tobin Tax, that would discourage tax havens and dishonest
			<lb/>
			accounting practices such as &quot;transfer pricing&quot; so as to promote economic
			<lb/>
			development in poorer countries. These proposals would be feasible, according
			<lb/>
			to Brock, even without universal agreement or global implementation.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The next chapter discusses what steps need to be taken in order to protect the
			<lb/> &quot;basic liberties&quot; of the world&apos;s people. The focus is upon freedom of the press
			<lb/>
			and on securing criminal justice. The press can be hampered in many ways but
			<lb/>
			there are currently efective NGOs which seek to protect journalists and
			<lb/>
			encourage press freedom. For its part, the International Criminal Court is playing
			<lb/>
			an important role in countering the ability of a culture of impunity to protect
			<lb/>
			criminals in many countries -whether corrupt government ofcials, warlords or
			<lb/>
			drug barons. Brock argues for the relevant liberties by once again using her
			<lb/>
			normative thought experiment. In such a context, &quot;reasonable people will care at
			<lb/>
			least a little about enjoying some freedoms&quot; <ref type="biblio">(152)</ref> and &quot;delegates would,
			<lb/>
			therefore, endorse freedom of conscience, speech, dissent, and exit.&quot; <ref type="biblio">(153)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The next chapter focuses almost exclusively on military forms of humanitarian
			<lb/>
			intervention, and it is therefore not surprising that it endorses the use of just war
			<lb/>
			principles in order to place limits on them. The central theoretical argument for
			<lb/>
			justifying humanitarian intervention is drawn, once again, from Brock&apos;s
			<lb/>
			normative thought experiment. She argues that reasonable delegates to an
			<lb/>
			original convention would endorse principles that would allow for humanitarian
			<lb/>
			intervention because they would welcome interventions to protect their lives and
			<lb/>
			basic needs if they were in the situation of the victims of oppression. Brock also
			<lb/>
			cites the International Commission on Intervention and State Sovereignty (ICISS)
			<lb/>
			report which extends the concept of sovereignty so that it includes responsibility
			<lb/>
			for the internal protection of human rights. Not only is sovereignty the right not
			<lb/>
			to be interfered with, but it is also the responsibility to protect the rights of
			<lb/>
			citizens internally. Accordingly, a state that fails to protect its citizens forfeits its
			<lb/>
			right to non-intervention because it forfeits its sovereignty.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>That her hypothetical normative thought experiments might not be as
			<lb/>
			unequivocal as one might hope is admitted by Brock in her chapter on
			<lb/>
			immigration. She here concedes that individualist cosmopolitans in such a
			<lb/>
			scenario may choose a policy of open borders from behind a veil of ignorance
			<lb/>
			but that those of a more communitarian bent might endorse a more restrictive
			<lb/>
			policy so as to preserve the cultural homogeneity of their societies. Rather than
			<lb/>
			explore these issues more fully however, Brock takes a consequentialist view
			<lb/>
			and asks who benefits from migratory movements. She highlights the costs to
			<lb/>
			developing countries when their trained people leave for more lucrative jobs in
			<lb/>
			developed countries -especially in the health professions. She discusses
			<lb/>
			solutions that include compensation from the developed countries to cover the
			<lb/>
			costs of training such people and of restoring services that are compromised by
			<lb/>
			their departure. Brock also discusses the benefits and problems that fow from
			<lb/>
			the remittances that migrants send home to developing countries and which
			<lb/>
			contribute substantially to those economies. The virtue of this chapter is that it
			<lb/>
			shows that migration is not just a matter of justice for the individuals who
			<lb/>
			migrate. It is also a matter of justice for the societies they leave behind and for
			<lb/>
			future generations in those societies. Brock does not discuss problems of
			<lb/>
			multiculturalism arising from migration or problems relating to refugees whose
			<lb/>
			reasons for migration are not economic.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Chapter nine explores the possibilities for improving the lot of the poor by
			<lb/>
			reforming international trade. Deriving her thought from a multitude of technical
			<lb/>
			studies, she doubts that a simple liberalisation of trade would always do so and
			<lb/>
			argues that &quot;special and diferential treatment&quot; would often be necessary. Fair
			<lb/>
			international trade arrangements should allow for specific needs in order to
			<lb/>
			attain the goals of global justice. Similarly, there should be reform of working
			<lb/>
			conditions and wages throughout the world, and eforts to link such
			<lb/>
			improvements to the conditions of trade should be encouraged. Although
			<lb/>
			philosophers reading the book would not be able to assess the validity of these
			<lb/>
			proposals on the basis of their expertise or on the basis of the amount of
			<lb/>
			information provided in this chapter, it is valuable for them to be reminded of the
			<lb/>
			need to link normative proposals to concrete institutional and programmatic
			<lb/>
			reforms. There is a greater need for synergies between advocacy, philosophy,
			<lb/>
			political science and economics in order to develop workable solutions, and if
			<lb/>
			Brock has extended her reach beyond her own discipline in this and preceding
			<lb/>
			chapters, she should be applauded for doing so.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Chapter ten returns the book to a more philosophical level of discussion. It
			<lb/>
			critiques the &quot;liberal nationalist&quot; position of such writers as Yael Tamir and David
			<lb/>
			Miller which argue that our duties towards our co-nationals are stronger and
			<lb/>
			more immediate than our duties to foreigners. Brock points out that both authors
			<lb/>
			are inconsistent because they allow that universal and impartial considerations
			<lb/>
			provide a normative backdrop and constraint on the degree to which we may
			<lb/>
			favour members of our own groups. For her part, Brock argues that it is not the
			<lb/>
			case that we are permitted to attend to international obligations only after we
			<lb/>
			have secured national interests. &quot;Rather, what we may permissibly do for co-<lb/>nationals must operate
			within the bounds of respecting our international duties.&quot;<lb/>
			<ref type="biblio">(262-3</ref>) This is especially true in relation to securing global justice. According
			to
			<lb/>
			Brock, nations should secure global justice before they attend to the welfare of
			<lb/>
			their own citizens. She goes on to use her normative thought experiment to
			<lb/>
			suggest that delegates in an original position would agree to seeing to the needs
			<lb/>
			of co-nationals only after the basic needs and liberties of all globally were
			<lb/>
			secured and fair terms of cooperation across borders were established.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In a dense and complex section of the chapter, Brock goes on to refute some
			<lb/>
			common objections to &quot;impartialism&quot;. Do cosmopolitan duties devalue friends
			<lb/>
			and family? Should we really save the philanthropist rather than our mother from
			<lb/>
			the burning building in the classic example? Are we required to be &quot;neutral&quot; in
			<lb/>
			our actions? Brock admits that constitutive relationships are valuable and
			<lb/>
			associative obligations binding but she appeals to a distinction Brian Barry
			<lb/>
			makes between first and second order impartiality. <ref type="biblio">(267)</ref> First order impartiality
			<lb/>
			requires not putting your own interests or those of your family or group members
			<lb/>
			first, while second order impartiality requires adherence to just institutions.
			<lb/>
			Critics of impartiality attack first order impartialism, but defenders defend
			<lb/>
			second order impartialism. Brock argues that in an original position no one could
			<lb/>
			object to the preference parents show to their children, but they would object to
			<lb/>
			institutional arrangements that are partial to members of certain casts,
			<lb/>
			ethnicities or other identity-forming groups. Moreover, they would not endorse
			<lb/>
			national or cultural allegiance is a basis for partiality because this would privilege
			<lb/>
			specific conceptions of the good life. The specific conception of the good life that
			<lb/>
			would be being assumed here is the communitarian/nationalist one promoted by
			<lb/>
			Kymlicka, Tamir and Miller. Brock&apos;s point is that we should not seek to adjudicate
			<lb/>
			from a nationalist perspective between the claims of national partiality and
			<lb/>
			cosmopolitan impartiality because that would be to beg the question. We must
			<lb/>
			suspend nationalism by adopting her normative thought experiment. To illustrate
			<lb/>
			this point, Brock says that we cannot ask whether it is fair to spend the national
			<lb/>
			resources primarily on internal welfare before asking whether the national
			<lb/>
			resources have been fairly obtained or justly retained. &quot;Nations should only
			<lb/>
			distribute resources to their own members if those resources are defensibly to be
			<lb/>
			used by the nation as it pleases, but we can only decide that matter if we have
			<lb/>
			first determined what global justice requires of all people and nations, and what
			<lb/>
			constitutes fair ownership of resources.&quot; <ref type="biblio">(269)</ref> It is only by suspending the
			<lb/>
			nationalist perspective that this broader question can be broached and the
			<lb/>
			claims of global justice fairly considered.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Chapter eleven begins by refuting a number of further arguments for favouring
			<lb/>
			co-nationals, including those that use the &quot;expanding circles&quot; model to suggest
			<lb/>
			that our obligations become less stringent as our relations to other people
			<lb/>
			become more tenuous or more distant. It then returns to the argument that we
			<lb/>
			have the responsibility to see that global justice criteria are met before we are
			<lb/>
			morally permitted to favour co-nationals. Brock makes this point by revisiting her
			<lb/>
			earlier material about the efects of migration on the provision of health care in
			<lb/>
			third world nations, along with several other cases, such as the adequate
			<lb/>
			collection of taxes internationally. We can look after the needs of co-nationals,
			<lb/>
			she says, provided all the necessary safeguards and provisions are in place to
			<lb/>
			ensure justice for non-nationals.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Chapter twelve is a rather dense and cryptic chapter that raises a number of
			<lb/>
			theoretical issues. The main thrust of it seems to be to ask about the content of
			<lb/>
			global justice: in respect of what do cosmopolitans insist on equality? Brock had
			<lb/>
			already argued that equality of wealth distribution or of opportunities for social
			<lb/>
			position are not apposite, and she is also opposed to Rawls&apos;s diference principle.
			<lb/>
			Her position is that everyone should have equal access to those conditions and
			<lb/>
			resources that are required for living a minimally decent or dignified human life.
			<lb/>
			This chapter adds more. Referring to the work of Elizabeth Anderson, Brock
			<lb/>
			argues that recognition and the kind of status which allows one to participate in
			<lb/>
			democratic decision making are the social goods which should be available
			<lb/>
			equally to all. Egalitarians should secure conditions, norms and institutions that
			<lb/>
			would accord what Anderson calls &quot;democratic equality&quot; which would ensure
			<lb/>
			freedom from oppression and domination to all. Brock says that this ties in with
			<lb/>
			her notion of responsive democracy. She argues that the community in which
			<lb/>
			this ideal of equality should be realised is that of the whole world rather than
			<lb/>
			specific states or cultural communities because the whole world is now a
			<lb/>
			globalized economic system.
			The distribution of wealth or social goods is not
			<lb/>
			what is of central importance to cosmopolitans, but rather the equal according of
			<lb/>
			the kind of social respect and recognition that becomes concrete in the ability of
			<lb/>
			all individuals to participate in democratic processes. The distribution of social
			<lb/>
			goods and the meeting of basic needs are merely instrumental in relation to this
			<lb/>
			fundamental value. An equitable distribution of social goods is a means of
			<lb/>
			ensuring equality of respect. It is not the ownership of, or access to, social goods
			<lb/>
			and opportunities that is of fundamental value to cosmopolitans but the social
			<lb/>
			recognition and democratic participation that these enable.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The last chapter address the &quot;feasibility sceptics&quot; who think that meaningful
			<lb/>
			change for the better is not possible. Brock reminds her readers of the many
			<lb/>
			suggestions that she has made or reported on in the preceding chapters which
			<lb/>
			show that change is possible.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Critique
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The book covers a wide range of important topics which range from theoretical
			<lb/>
			issues to practical applications of cosmopolitan principles. However, I find the
			<lb/>
			sequence of chapters a little unhelpful. That the more practical chapters occur in
			<lb/>
			the middle of the book results in the needs to repeat some materials at the end
			<lb/>
			when the feasibility of those proposals is discussed, while the central question of
			<lb/>
			how national obligations stand to cosmopolitan duties should have been resolved
			<lb/>
			earlier to as to prepare for the more concrete proposals that Brock makes.
			<lb/>
			Moreover, these proposals extend the scope of the book beyond the remit of
			<lb/>
			philosophy. To discuss these matters with the necessary rigour would require a
			<lb/>
			degree of knowledge of economics and related social sciences that philosophers
			<lb/>
			as such do not have. While I admire Brock for making such proposals, it would
			<lb/>
			require social scientists and social activists operating at a number of fronts and
			<lb/>
			using a wide range of expertise to decide which proposals are best and how they
			<lb/>
			might be implemented. The general problem here is that of making utopian
			<lb/>
			thinking more realistic and feasible and this is not a problem that philosophy, as
			<lb/>
			such, is equipped to deal with.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>What philosophy is equipped to deal with is the justification of the principles of
			<lb/>
			justice which should provide the basis for such realistic utopian thinking and for
			<lb/>
			responsible action to secure global justice. While the book embraces this task, I
			<lb/>
			find that it falls somewhat short on its promise. There are a number of ways in
			<lb/>
			which cosmopolitans can seek to justify and operationalise the principle of the
			<lb/>
			equal moral status of every individual globally that is central to their outlook and
			<lb/>
			to articulate what global justice might require in the light of this principle. The
			<lb/>
			first of these is to apply Rawls&apos;s diference principle globally in the way espoused
			<lb/>
			by Charles Beitz and Thomas Pogge 2 . Brock rejects this approach although she
			<lb/>
			uses a scenario very similar to Rawls&apos;s original position, applied globally, to
			<lb/>
			reach her own conclusions. A second way is to argue that basic human rights
			<lb/>
			apply to everyone globally and that the obligation to honour those rights is
			<lb/>
			incumbent on everyone globally as well -although those obligations can be
			<lb/>
			fulfilled by various institutions including both national governments and
			<lb/>
			transnational organisations. Brock firts with this second approach but does not
			<lb/>
			commit herself fully to it because of her preference for the discourse of needs.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Let me first say why I am concerned about Brock&apos;s reliance on her &quot;normative
			<lb/>
			thought experiment&quot;. Although I have compared it to Rawls&apos;s original position, it
			<lb/>
			is important to see that Rawls does not apply his scenario globally. One reason
			<lb/>
			for this is that he sees a domestic society as a more or less self-enclosed system
			<lb/>
			of cooperation that grounds reciprocal duties of justice which do not cross the
			<lb/>
			borders of that society. But a more profound reason is that he understands his
			<lb/>
			scenario as an articulation of liberal assumptions about how a reasonable
			<lb/>
			participant in political institutions would think in the context of an idealised
			<lb/>
			decision procedure. By suspending all knowledge of how the specific interests of
			<lb/>
			participants might be realised in the society that those participants are
			<lb/>
			designing, they cannot but act in an impartial manner and pursue goals which
			<lb/>
			any other participant could endorse. The original position constitutes them as
			<lb/>
			free and equal moral persons. In this context they constitute idealised liberal
			<lb/>
			political subjects who cannot but agree on institutional arrangements that are
			<lb/>
			fair. In this way, Rawls sees himself as explicating the notion of an ideal liberal
			<lb/>
			political participant -a notion which he assumes his readers share -and spelling
			<lb/>
			out the principles which such a participant would be rationally committed to
			<lb/>
			endorsing. It is precisely because he recognises that his model is liberal to its
			<lb/>
			very core in this way that he thinks it cannot be applied globally to societies
			<lb/>
			which are not liberal. It is applicable only to well-ordered societies in which the
			<lb/>
			political capacities of impartiality and a sense of justice are developed so as to
			<lb/>
			constitute political participants as ideal liberal subjects.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>But in Brock&apos;s use of an analogous scenario she asks us to speculate as to what
			<lb/>
			principles and practices would be endorsed by randomly chosen and reasonable
			<lb/>
			delegates who could come from any cultural or political background. The veil of
			<lb/>
			ignorance in this context would lead delegates to think in impartial terms
			<lb/>
			because they would have to consider the impact of the decision upon themselves
			<lb/>
			if they were to end up in the least favoured position. Accordingly, any
			<lb/>
			arrangement that would be so chosen would be considered by them to be fair
			<lb/>
			and just. In this version, the experiment is being used to establish what global
			<lb/>
			justice demands or to test arrangements as to whether they could be accepted
			<lb/>
			as just by anyone at all. And then it transpires that the arrangements endorsed
			<lb/>
			in such a scenario take on a liberal, individualist and democratic hue. Rather
			<lb/>
			than assuming liberalism as a background for the original position, as Rawls
			<lb/>
			does, Brock seems to use her normative thought experiment to establish it.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The problem with this variation on Rawls&apos;s idea is that it cannot be assumed that
			<lb/>
			participants are ideal liberal subjects who would endorse liberal outcomes. A
			<lb/>
			randomly chosen delegate might be a cardinal of the Roman church, a Hindu
			<lb/>
			renouncer, a Brahmin, an Imam, or an uneducated Afghan woman who had no
			<lb/>
			conception of democracy. Would such delegates agree with arrangements that
			<lb/>
			were fundamentally liberal in tenor? Insofar as he holds moral views with deep
			<lb/>
			conviction, could the Brahmin seriously agree that an &quot;untouchable&quot; should
			<lb/>
			receive the same respect and social recognition as Brahmins, for example? Even
			<lb/>
			if he imagined himself in the position of the untouchable, would he not suppose
			<lb/>
			that, as an untouchable, it would be unthinkable for him to aspire to anything
			<lb/>
			except the job of cleaning away human waste? If a delegate were an Afghan
			<lb/>
			woman of traditional upbringing and no education, would she not think it
			<lb/>
			impossible, even for herself, to participate in democratic processes that may
			<lb/>
			involve disobeying her husband?
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Brock fails to see that her normative thought experiment will not inevitably
			<lb/>
			promote fundamentally liberal or cosmopolitan values. Delegates are asked to
			<lb/>
			consider how they themselves would react if the arrangements they agreed to
			<lb/>
			yielded an outcome not acceptable to the least favoured and if they were
			<lb/>
			themselves those least favoured. There is no allowance made for the possibility
			<lb/>
			that delegates might see themselves as spokespersons for their groups and may
			<lb/>
			endorse conditions which, while they would not welcome them for themselves,
			<lb/>
			they consider to be necessary to the living of the good life which their tradition
			<lb/>
			teaches them to accept and to endorse for their constituents. So a male delegate
			<lb/>
			may endorse a restriction on a woman&apos;s rights because he thinks that he would
			<lb/>
			or should accept it if he were a woman. At the time of writing this review there
			<lb/>
			were reports in the newspaper of a young woman in Malaysia who had been
			<lb/>
			condemned by judges in a Sharia court to six lashes of the cane for drinking
			<lb/>
			alcohol. She is reported to have said that if this punishment were the will of Allah
			<lb/>
			and if it would provide a salutary example to other Muslims, then she would be
			<lb/>
			happy to accept it. This would seem to imply that if she were presented with this
			<lb/>
			scenario in Brock&apos;s normative thought experiment, she would think such a
			<lb/>
			punishment was fair and appropriate. There were reports also of interviews with
			<lb/>
			Afghan women living in Australia who said that they could not understand why it
			<lb/>
			would be worthwhile for them to vote in the Afghan elections if they were still
			<lb/>
			living in that country because, according to them, voting and politics are men&apos;s
			<lb/>
			responsibilities 3 . In this way a traditionally minded delegate may think it fair to
			<lb/>
			accept illiberal restrictions on basic liberties in Brock&apos;s normative thought
			<lb/>
			experiment. Someone who genuinely believes that adulterers should be stoned
			<lb/>
			would imagine themselves accepting such a stoning in institutions set up to
			<lb/>
			create social and sexual order. They would regard it as unfair, even from the
			<lb/>
			victim&apos;s point of view, to escape from such a punishment -a punishment that
			<lb/>
			will have been made to seem natural and just by years of indoctrination into the
			<lb/>
			ways of the tradition. A traditional moral conception may override the self-<lb/>centred quest for autonomy
			which liberals imagine would motivate any
			<lb/>
			reasonable person at all. This point might also apply to Brock&apos;s arguments about
			<lb/>
			humanitarian intervention. Some delegates may have such strong nationalist
			<lb/>
			views that they would reject intervention even if it was their own individual rights
			<lb/>
			which would be protected by such a violation of sovereignty. One could well
			<lb/>
			imagine contemporary Chinese nationalists thinking in this way.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The problem is that when we are asked to imagine what delegates would agree
			<lb/>
			to in Brock&apos;s version of the original position, we inevitably imagine them thinking
			<lb/>
			as if they were liberals such as ourselves. Because our acculturation has been
			<lb/>
			broadly liberal we could not imagine ourselves agreeing to what we would see as
			<lb/>
			unjust and discriminatory institutions. And so we could not imagine anyone else
			<lb/>
			doing so. Although Brock does back up her rejection of Rawls&apos;s diference
			<lb/>
			principle by appealing to what was actually agreed to in a series of staged
			<lb/>
			psychology experiments, by creating a hypothetical scenario in which we are
			<lb/>
			asked to imagine what others would agree to without adequate empirical
			<lb/>
			evidence as to what they actually do agree to, we can only fall back upon our
			<lb/>
			own intuitions and hypotheses about what we would agree to. But most of us are
			<lb/>
			liberals in some broad sense. It therefore becomes inevitable that the
			<lb/>
			arrangements we can imagine being agreed to in the experiment are liberal
			<lb/>
			arrangements. Brock&apos;s argument commits the fallacy of begging the question.
			<lb/>
			The aim of the argument is to establish that liberal cosmopolitan principles,
			<lb/>
			practices and institutions would be fair. But it then relies on the intuitions of
			<lb/>
			liberal cosmopolitans to distinguish outcomes that would be fair from those
			<lb/>
			which would not be. In a world of moral pluralism there are people whose ways
			<lb/>
			of thinking and scales of value are simply incomprehensible to those of us who
			<lb/>
			are of a modernist and liberal persuasion. The fact is that we cannot imagine
			<lb/>
			how such people would decide on issues in Brock&apos;s normative thought
			<lb/>
			experiment, and hence we cannot know what they would agree to.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Perhaps it is to overcome this problem that delegates in the normative thought
			<lb/>
			experiment or their decisions are described as having to be &quot;reasonable&quot;. But
			<lb/>
			this specification merely exacerbates the problem. Who is to count as reasonable
			<lb/>
			from our point of view? Inevitably, we would only count as reasonable people
			<lb/>
			who think broadly in the way that we do. We would not count the Brahmin or the
			<lb/>
			Afghan woman as reasonable because we cannot recognise the cogency of their
			<lb/>
			thinking. But this really means that to be deemed reasonable in the experiment
			<lb/>
			it is necessary to think in broadly liberal terms just as we do. Once again, we
			<lb/>
			have created a condition for the normative thought experiment which results in
			<lb/>
			the argument begging the question. It is inevitable that reasonable people will
			<lb/>
			agree to liberal principles if to count as reasonable one must already be a liberal.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>What this shows is that a genuinely cosmopolitan theory of justice needs to dig
			<lb/>
			deeper. It cannot just be a specification of what would count as criteria for justice
			<lb/>
			in the view of people who already think in modernist, individualist and liberal
			<lb/>
			terms. It is one thing to say what makes a situation or an arrangement just (for
			<lb/>
			example, that it secures a minimum standard of provision necessary for living a
			<lb/>
			life of simple human dignity, or that it fulfils Rawls&apos;s maximin criteria, or that it
			<lb/>
			secures equality in the distribution of some specifiable social good), but it is
			<lb/>
			another to say what justice is, or what is good about justice. We can ask the
			<lb/>
			classic Socratic question here: is a situation just because it would be endorsed in
			<lb/>
			an original position, or would it be endorsed in an original position because it is
			<lb/>
			just? The first of these options is unhelpful for reasons just explained. The second
			<lb/>
			option requires us to develop an account of what makes a situation just so that it
			<lb/>
			would be endorsed in an original position.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>It might help to explain this in negative terms. A person who sufers an injustice
			<lb/>
			sufers a harm. But what is the harm that constitutes the injustice? To help us
			<lb/>
			understand this question let us compare two cases. First, suppose a person loses
			<lb/>
			her home because it is washed away in a tsunami which no one could have
			<lb/>
			reasonably warned her of or prevented. This is a harm because she has need of a
			<lb/>
			home and she now does not have one. Second, suppose a person loses her home
			<lb/>
			because a powerful developer bribed a local ofcial to remove her from it so that
			<lb/>
			he could acquire the land and build a beach-side resort. In both cases the woman
			<lb/>
			sufers the harm of losing the home that she needs. In both cases her needs are
			<lb/>
			not met. But in the second case she also sufers an injustice. (There might be
			<lb/>
			those who think she sufers an injustice in the first scenario, but they would
			<lb/>
			require a pre-modern theory in which natural disasters are seen as violating
			<lb/>
			some form of cosmic justice.) So in the second case she sufers two harms: the
			<lb/>
			need for a home not being met, and the injustice. This shows that, contrary to
			<lb/>
			what is implied by Brock&apos;s view, this injustice does not consist simply in the need
			<lb/>
			not being met. What sense are we to make of this injustice, then? In what does
			<lb/>
			this injustice consist? Would we have explained the injustice if we were to say
			<lb/>
			that, in Brock&apos;s normative thought experiment, the woman would not have
			<lb/>
			endorsed any principle, practice or institution that would allow her home to be
			<lb/>
			taken away from her in this way? No, this adds nothing. It is merely another way
			<lb/>
			of saying that it was unjust. Perhaps it adds that we would agree, from our liberal
			<lb/>
			vantage point, that it is unjust. But what it does not tell us is what the extra harm
			<lb/>
			is that she has sufered. There is some hint of an answer in Brock&apos;s suggestion
			<lb/>
			that injustice involves a lack of social recognition and respect, but then it is not
			<lb/>
			clear how this woman has had her capacity for democratic participation
			<lb/>
			compromised. According to Brock, it is because democratic participation matters
			<lb/>
			that social recognition and respect are important.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>I would suggest that the extra harm is that her right to her home has been
			<lb/>
			violated. The tsunami did not violate her right to her home, even though it did
			<lb/>
			result in her losing her home, but the developer&apos;s action did violate her right to
			<lb/>
			her home. There were legal arrangements by virtue of which she was entitled to
			<lb/>
			her home and the action of the developer circumvented these arrangements and
			<lb/>
			resulted in her loss. Introducing the notion of a right here serves to introduce
			<lb/>
			another relevant notion as well: namely, that of obligation. Whenever anyone
			<lb/>
			has a right, someone else has an obligation. This might be an obligation to
			<lb/>
			provide some good to which the recipient is entitled or it might be an obligation
			<lb/>
			to desist from some harmful action. Many such positive and negative obligations
			<lb/>
			are established by laws and contracts. In the case before us, there is an
			<lb/>
			obligation on the part of everyone to honour the property rights of others and
			<lb/>
			this obligation is a logical counterpart of the property right in question. Our
			<lb/>
			developer has not fulfilled his obligation to honour the property right of the
			<lb/>
			beach-side home owner and it is for this reason that she has sufered an
			<lb/>
			injustice. What this example shows is that the harm of having her need for a
			<lb/>
			home frustrated that is sufered by this woman is not just a result of bad luck -<lb/>as it would have been
			had her home been destroyed by the tsunami -but is an
			<lb/>
			example of injustice. And this is because her right to her home was violated by
			<lb/>
			the developer who failed to fulfil his obligation to adhere to the law. Along with
			<lb/>
			the harm she sufers in losing her home, the injustice she sufers is the violation
			<lb/>
			of her right to her home.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Of course, this shifts the focus of the argument into the nature and basis of
			<lb/>
			rights. If her normative thought experiment cannot do the work that Brock wants
			<lb/>
			it to, then it had better be done by a robust theory of human rights. Brock ofers
			<lb/>
			no such theory but does go close to it when she speaks of human needs and
			<lb/>
			capabilities. She needs to go that one step further in order to show that what we
			<lb/>
			need for a life of basic human dignity we also have a right to. I myself have used
			<lb/>
			Brock&apos;s earlier work and some ideas from Martha Nussbaum 4 to develop such an
			<lb/>
			argument 5 . The argument has the following structure:
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<list>
			<item>
			1. Describe human nature in terms of what would give dignity and worth to a
			<lb/>
			human life by fulfilling that nature through the exercise of essential
			<lb/>
			human capabilities.
			<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item>
			2. Note that this description is normative for all human beings.
			<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item>
			3. Conclude from 1 and 2 that all people should be enabled to exercise the
			<lb/>
			human capabilities given in that description.
			<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item>
			4. Assert that people need the resources to exercise those capabilities rather
			<lb/>
			than just wanting them (and need them even when they do not express a
			<lb/>
			want for them).
			<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item>
			5. Conclude from 3 and 4 that social institutions and individuals should not
			<lb/>
			prevent the exercise of the listed human capabilities and should provide
			<lb/>
			whatever assistance or resources that are needed for such exercise. This
			<lb/>
			step derives obligations from needs without specifying who carries those
			<lb/>
			obligations. It is open to diferent cultures and societies to meet them in
			<lb/>
			difering ways.
			<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item>
			6. Note that obligations and rights are symmetrical.
			<lb/>
			</item>
			
			<item>
			7. Conclude from 5 and 6 that all human beings have a right to the freedom
			<lb/>
			and the necessary resources to exercise the capabilities central to human
			<lb/>
			dignity. Insofar as there is an obligation -not yet allocated to anyone in
			<lb/>
			particular -to meet the needs of people so that they can exercise the
			<lb/>
			capabilities described and so live a human life of minimal dignity, so all
			<lb/>
			people have a right to have those needs met.
			<lb/>
			</item>
		</list>
		
		<p>It is clear, however, that Brock does not want to rely on a theory of rights. In
			<lb/>
			chapter six, for example, she uses a terminology of &quot;basic liberties&quot;. Why does
			<lb/>
			Brock not use the language of basic political and civil rights in this context? Why
			<lb/>
			does she not use Nussbaum&apos;s terminology of capabilities or her own preferred
			<lb/>
			discourse of human and social needs? The concept of liberties seems vague and
			<lb/>
			its relation to that of rights needs to be spelt out. Moreover, to speak of liberties
			<lb/>
			is, once again, to import too much of the liberal outlook (although Brock does
			<lb/>
			allow for the liberty to form non-liberal associations).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Perhaps the reason that Brock has chosen not to go down the path towards a
			<lb/>
			robust theory of justice based on the universal value of human rights is that it
			<lb/>
			would make her an &quot;extreme&quot; cosmopolitan. In her twelfth chapter Brock returns
			<lb/>
			to the classifications of cosmopolitanism from her introduction and says, &quot;I am
			<lb/>
			happy to take a pluralistic line on the sources of value [of cosmopolitanism]. And
			<lb/>
			on the question of whether or not multiple fundamental principles of justice
			<lb/>
			might exist, I remain open-minded to the possibility there might be such, though
			<lb/>
			I have not come across particularly robust arguments for these yet.&quot; <ref type="biblio">(316)</ref> This is
			<lb/>
			revealing. What it shows is that Brock does not have a theory about what makes
			<lb/>
			an unjust situation unjust. Using an original scenario tells us what people would
			<lb/>
			choose and so gives us criteria for what situations might be classified as just or
			<lb/>
			unjust, but it does not tell us why they are unjust. For this one needs a
			<lb/>
			substantive theory. A theory of human rights is such a theory, but Brock avoids
			<lb/>
			this in favour of her discussion of needs and capabilities.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>An extreme cosmopolitan theory of justice based on universal human rights
			<lb/>
			would also help Brock in her arguments about humanitarian intervention in
			<lb/>
			chapter seven. I reported that the argument she relies on to justify such
			<lb/>
			interventions is that reasonable delegates to her normative original position
			<lb/>
			would agree to such interventions if they imagined their needs not being met
			<lb/>
			because of tyrannical and oppressive regimes. She also mentions the ICISS
			<lb/>
			principles that, first, a state which violates the rights of its citizens forfeits its
			<lb/>
			sovereignty and that, second, such violations can constitute &quot;just cause&quot; under
			<lb/>
			the criteria for just war. These ICISS principles clearly show that the concept of
			<lb/>
			rights plays a crucial role in this context. But the concept of rights is superior to
			<lb/>
			Brock&apos;s appeal to needs for a further reason. Using the principles of just war as
			<lb/>
			both Brock and the ICISS do runs the risk of conceiving military humanitarian
			<lb/>
			interventions as acts of war. In the context of the Westphalian system of
			<lb/>
			mutually aggressive states, the concept of sovereignty is logically tied to that of
			<lb/>
			war in that statehood relies on the ability to defend the state&apos;s borders.
			<lb/>
			Accordingly, war is primarily seen as a violation of state sovereignty. The
			<lb/>
			paradigm case of a war is an invasion. Humanitarian interventions should not be
			<lb/>
			thought about in this framework. It would be much better if they were thought of
			<lb/>
			as police actions directed at the violators of human rights. To do this we need to
			<lb/>
			use the human rights discourse rather than the vague discourse of basic needs
			<lb/>
			which Brock uses. I have argued that her normative thought experiment cannot
			<lb/>
			be used to establish how justice is constituted. Accordingly, if needs not being
			<lb/>
			met were to be considered by delegates in the original scenario to justify
			<lb/>
			interventions, this will be because of humanitarian considerations rather than
			<lb/>
			considerations of justice. It will be motivated by a desire to meet the needs of
			<lb/>
			victims (or by imagining what it would be like to be such a victim) rather than
			<lb/>
			the determination to punish their oppressors. What the human rights discourse
			<lb/>
			gives us is the ability to justify sanctions for violations. Henry Shue has ofered
			<lb/>
			an argument for the legitimacy of foreign intervention based on the premise that
			<lb/>
			talk of human rights is empty unless we are prepared to police their observance <ref type="biblio">6</ref> .
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Accordingly, the concept of policing is tied to that of human rights. Talk of
			<lb/>
			human rights obliges us to provide for the protection of those rights and for the
			<lb/>
			punishment of those who violate them. This is a matter of upholding
			<lb/>
			international law. If military humanitarian interventions were described as police
			<lb/>
			actions they would be more readily understood as attempts to back up the global
			<lb/>
			human rights regime than as invasions on the part of one state or group of states
			<lb/>
			into the territory of another even if it were for humanitarian reasons such as the
			<lb/>
			meeting of needs. This way of thinking would require an extreme form of
			<lb/>
			cosmopolitanism that we should not shy away from.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Brock has gone a long way towards elucidating a cosmopolitan foundation for the
			<lb/>
			norms of global justice. However, in committing herself to being only a moderate
			<lb/>
			cosmopolitan she has failed to provide a robust and universally applicable theory
			<lb/>
			of justice. The fact of global moral pluralism should not be allowed to deter
			<lb/>
			cosmopolitans from developing such a theory.
		</p>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
