<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>
			Cinema is part of contemporary life; there is no barrier between them.
			<lb/>
			But this dialogue between visual forms of representation,
			<lb/>
			this new relationship between the cinema and the museum, this is a problem for me.
			<lb/>
			(Victor Erice)
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>
			&quot;The cinema is dead -long live the cinema (in the museum)&quot;
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>For several decades now, the cinema&apos;s demise has been presented as a fact: at first,
			<lb/>
			television took away the family audience, then the video recorder killed off the
			<lb/>
			neighbourhood cinemas, and now digitization has broken the indexicality of the
			<lb/>
			photographic image, undermining its &apos;documentary&apos; value by replacing the optico-<lb/>chemical link
			to
			physical reality with numerical code. News of the cinema&apos;s death is thus
			<lb/>
			no longer new, and some will say that it is greatly exaggerated: the hegemonic might of
			<lb/>
			Hollywood movies reigns unabated, but young auteurs continue to emerge in Asian
			<lb/>
			countries, Latin America and the Middle-East, and a myriad of festivals show new films
			<lb/>
			from all over the world -even from &apos;old&apos; Europe -to crowded venues.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Yet clearly, a certain cinema is no more: the great masters of the European art
			<lb/>
			cinema of the post-war period are either dead or fell silent long ago: Rossellini, Visconti,
			<lb/>
			Fellini; Hitchcock, Welles, Bunuel; Fassbinder, Pasolini, Kieslowski, and now Antonioni
			<lb/>
			and Bergman have passed away. Only in France do Alain Resnais, Eric Rohmer, Jacques
			<lb/>
			Rivette, Jean-Marie Straub and Jean-Luc Godard still occasionally make films, yet they
			<lb/>
			are among the ones most eloquently melancholy about the &apos;death&apos; of cinema.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Should one revive this heroic past, not just at retrospectives in cinematheques and
			<lb/>
			with university film courses? Open the fine arts museums? No contemporary exhibition
			<lb/>
			can do without the moving image, either in the form of video and installation art, or
			<lb/>
			serving as educational-informative support; so why not make museums the permanent
			<lb/>
			home of cinema? Some cinephiles will say that this is how it should be. The cinema,
			<lb/>
			finally come of age as the art form of the 20 th century, has earned the right to enter into
			<lb/>
			the traditional temple of the arts. The &apos;death of cinema&apos; actually makes it easier. We now
			<lb/>
			know who are the masters and which are the canonical masterpieces. We can begin to
			<lb/>
			study them afresh, with the eyes of art historians or &apos;image-anthropologists&apos;. The archive
			<lb/>
			and the museum can and must take over from the film studio, the distributor and the
			<lb/>
			exhibitor, to save, restore, preserve and valorize: as art-works as well as heritage and
			<lb/>
			cultural patrimony. Not unlike in previous periods of civilization, when the (primary
			<lb/>
			economic) use-value of an object is exhausted, a film, after its commercial run has ended,
			<lb/>
			can enter into different cycles of the value chain, moving from &apos;commerce&apos; to &apos;culture&apos;<lb/>
			and &apos;art&apos;. It can become part of a collection, acquire aesthetic status as a unique artefact,
			<lb/>
			or attain the aura of a personal work, thanks to the auteur&apos;s stylistic signature. Others will
			<lb/>
			argue that these very moves constitute an act of betrayal, or even &apos;theft&apos;. The cinema was
			<lb/>
			made for the people, and belongs to the people; films are products of an industry and
			<lb/>
			their commodity-status is an essential part of their historical meaning. As &apos;public
			<lb/>
			memory, privatised&apos; and as &apos;designs for living&apos;, they advertise if not always the moral
			<lb/>
			life, then the &apos;good life&apos;, for everyone: cinema the democratic art. The afterlife of films
			<lb/>
			and filmmakers, if it cannot be the big screen, should be television, the Internet, every
			<lb/>
			medium and on any platform, including the ever more readily available DVDs, with their
			<lb/> &apos;bonuses&apos;, extras and other enticements to consumption. Cynics (or realists) will
			<lb/>
			conclude that the musealization of the cinema suits both parties. It adds cultural capital to
			<lb/>
			the cinematic heritage and redeems its lowly origins in popular entertainment, but it also
			<lb/>
			adds new audiences to the museum, where the video monitor and the moving image -<lb/>market-research prove
			it
			-retain the visitors&apos; attention several seconds longer than the
			<lb/>
			framed painting or the free-standing, static sculpture. And it puts the intellectual and
			<lb/>
			financial resources of a century-old institution (usually supported by the State) behind
			<lb/>
			something as fragile and perishable as celluloid, when &apos;the industry&apos; is at best prepared to
			<lb/>
			digitally re-master the cult classics, and thus falsifies not only the historic record, but in
			<lb/>
			the rush for returns, obliterates the material traces of an otherwise irrecoverable &apos;time
			<lb/>
			past, stored&apos;, more than ever in urgent need to be &apos;re-stored&apos;, rather than re-packaged.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>So, when the cinema enters the museum, matters are not straightforward.
			<lb/>
			Different actor-agents, power-relations and policy agendas, different competences, egos
			<lb/>
			and sensibilities, different elements of the complex puzzle that is the contemporary art
			<lb/>
			world and its commercial counterpart come into play. Other considerations are also
			<lb/>
			pertinent: for today&apos;s practicing artists, photography, film, video, the digital media are the
			<lb/>
			paint, pencil clay or bronze of their predecessors -in other words, their primary materials
			<lb/>
			and natural tools of the trade. And like artists before them, they consider these
			<lb/>
			predecessors fair game: to appropriate, re-use, parody, plunder, plagiarize or pay homage
			<lb/>
			to. Such is especially the case for the cinematic heritage, which belongs to everyone. If
			<lb/>
			Surrealism, Dada, Pop art and Fluxus have demonstrated how to recycle the materials and
			<lb/>
			commodities of the first industrial age as found objects, ready-mades and &apos;junk&apos;, to be
			<lb/>
			dis-placed and re-coded as both art and anti-art, then moving images of the first hundred
			<lb/>
			years of cinema, as they enter the museum, are necessarily also &apos;found footage&apos;, whatever
			<lb/>
			their provenance: anonymous or authored, from a well-known classic or a home movie.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>This in itself can be the cause of several dilemmas. Installation artists are now
			<lb/>
			often trained as filmmakers, bringing to their work an extensive knowledge of cinema
			<lb/>
			history, as well as of avant-garde film or &apos;expanded cinema&apos; practices. What relation do
			<lb/>
			they entertain with the works of such acknowledged auteurs as listed above? Is Douglas
			<lb/>
			Gordon&apos;s 24-Hour Psycho a homage, an auto-pilot remake or a late-night tv-stupor
			induced pastiche of Hitchcock&apos;s film, which itself migrated from &apos;schlock&apos;
			(in
			1960) to
			<lb/> &apos;masterpiece&apos; (since the 1980)? Or how does Dog Day Afternoon (1975) feature in Pierre
			<lb/>
			Huyghe&apos;s The Third Memory (1999): as an authored work by Sidney Lumet, famously
			<lb/>
			starring Al Pacino, or as the &apos;first memory/first reality&apos; that has substituted itself for
			John
			<lb/>
			Wojtowicz&apos;s own recollection of his attempted bank-robbery and hostage-taking? At one
			<lb/>
			and the same time &apos;found footage&apos; and &apos;authored texts&apos;, &apos;works&apos; and &apos;worlds&apos;,
			such films
			<lb/>
			are &apos;fragments&apos;, even if shown in the museum in their entirety:
			the museum is no cinema
			<lb/>
			and the cinema no museum, not least because of the different time economies, obliging
			<lb/>
			the viewer in the museum to &apos;sample&apos; a film, rather than make it the occasion for &apos;a night
			<lb/>
			at the movies&apos;; but also because the institutions and discourses of which each is a part,
			<lb/>
			has its cultural matrix located elsewhere, in distinct &apos;public spheres&apos;, with different
			<lb/>
			constituencies.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The dilemma of contending public spheres is equally acute for the avant-garde
			<lb/>
			filmmakers from the 1960s and 70s (often politically committed to fusing art and life),
			<lb/>
			whose films suddenly could no longer count on screenings either in art-et-essai cinemas
			<lb/>
			or on late-night television programmes. A &apos;happy few&apos; found a second life as installation
			<lb/>
			artists, commissioned to create new work by curators of international art shows like the
			<lb/>
			Kassel documenta. Especially since Catherine David in 1997 invited filmmakers from
			<lb/>
			France, Germany, Belgium and Britain to documenta X -among them Harun Farocki,
			<lb/>
			Ulrike Ottinger, Sally Potter, Chantal Akerman, Johan Grimonprez, as well as H.J.
			<lb/>
			Syberberg and J.L.
			Godard -the cross-over has continued at the Venice Biennale, the
			<lb/>
			Whitney Biannial, at Carnegie Mellon and many other venues. These filmmakers-turned-<lb/>installation
			artists are now usually named side by side with artists-turned-filmmakers like
			<lb/>
			Fischli &amp; Weiss, Johan Grimonprez, William Kentridge, Matthew Barney, Tacita Dean,
			<lb/>
			Pippilotti Rist, or Sam Taylor-Wood.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>The Film Auteur as Museum Artist
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Bearing these challenges in mind, how then can one imagine Ingmar Bergman &apos;enter&apos; the
			<lb/>
			museum, a director whose &apos;faithful wife&apos; -in his own words -was the theatre, and whose
			<lb/> &apos;mistress&apos; was the cinema, who &apos;lived&apos; music, loved and staged opera, but claimed
			rarely
			<lb/>
			if ever to have set foot in a museum? Can it be done, should it be done? While he was
			<lb/>
			still alive, he might well have tried to sabotage such an enterprise, seeing neither special
			<lb/>
			urgency nor purpose to it. Were one to persist, however, and consider the venture a long
			<lb/>
			overdue homage to one of the &apos;great artists&apos; of the 20 th century (occasioned by what
			<lb/>
			would have been his 90 th birthday on July 14 th , 2008), the precedent would be Alfred
			<lb/>
			Hitchcock. Hitchcock was the first -mainstream, popular, albeit still &apos;European&apos; -<lb/>director to
			receive a major museum&apos;s accolade, the exhibition &quot;Hitchcock et l&apos;Art:
			<lb/>
			Coincidences fatales&quot;, shown in 2000/2001 in Montreal and at the Centre Pompidou
			<lb/>
			Paris. While not without stirring controversy, it set a new standard of how to present the
			<lb/>
			work of a film director in the museum.
			But Hitchcock had already been the &apos;subject&apos; of
			<lb/>
			another exhibition, &quot;Notorious -Alfred Hitchcock and Contemporary Art&quot;, at the
			<lb/>
			Museum of Modern Art in Oxford, in 1999, where some fourteen artists were assembled,
			<lb/>
			with (in some cases, specially commissioned) work based on Hitchcock&apos;s films. Since
			<lb/>
			then, Hitchcock-inspired art has itself become something of a genre, in turn ripe for
			<lb/>
			pastiche, as in Johan Grimonprez&apos; &quot;Looking for Alfred&quot; (2007)
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>With Bergman, however, one can also take one&apos;s cue from another (more
			<lb/>
			conventional, if still exceptionally rich) exhibition, devoted to Stanley Kubrick in
			<lb/>
			Frankfurt in 2004 (and subsequently touring Berlin, Melbourne, Zurich, Rome):
			photos
			<lb/>
			both personal and from studio locations, film fragments, home movies, cameras, special
			<lb/>
			effects devices, props from the sets, scripts, letters, director&apos;s sketches, drafts, as well as
			<lb/>
			documentation of all the many unfinished and abandoned projects. Given the existence of
			<lb/>
			an archive at the Ingmar Bergman Foundation, and in light of Bergman&apos;s sixty-odd
			<lb/>
			feature films (not counting television productions, plays, scripts, books and notebooks)
			<lb/>
			produced during a career spanning almost as many years as he made films, the material
			<lb/>
			objects, photographs and written documents amassed in the course of such a &apos;life-work&apos;<lb/>
			can easily fill a major exhibition space.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>It is also possible not to take Bergman at his word about his indifference to the
			<lb/>
			visual arts, and go through his films, on the lookout for paintings, sculptures, objets d&apos;art.
			<lb/>
			Very soon it becomes evident how precise an eye he (and his art-directors or set
			<lb/>
			designers) had for the dramatic or ironic uses of sculpture, as well as for staging scenes
			<lb/>
			that are clearly meant to invoke pictorial traditions, ranging from Nordic masters of sea-<lb/>and
			landscapes,
			French impressionists, to directly citing compositions from the German
			<lb/>
			Caspar David Friedrich and the Danish painter Vilhelm Hammershoi (of whom Bergman
			<lb/>
			owned two works). A film like The Passion of Anna (1969), not normally regarded as one
			<lb/>
			of his masterpieces, reveals itself to be a particular rich source for studying Bergman&apos;s
			<lb/>
			affinity with landscape painting, with the Dutch still-life tradition and the Danish school
			<lb/>
			of interiors (besides Hammershoi, it is Carl Vilhelm Holsoe who comes to mind).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Is this enough to make Bergman a museum artist, in the sense of placing him in
			<lb/>
			the mainstream of modern art-movements, like Luis Bunuel or Jean Cocteau? Does it
			<lb/>
			shift aesthetic coordinates and moral perspectives, allowing one to see his work afresh, as
			<lb/>
			Dominique Paini and Guy Cogeval did for Hitchcock (supported, it should be said, by
			<lb/>
			two decades of a veritable &apos;Hitchcock industry&apos; of critical commentary, scholarly
			<lb/>
			publications and academic conferences)? Or, returning to the comparison with Kubrick,
			<lb/>
			who for most of his life had been the great recluse, making -few and far between -<lb/>&apos;Hollywood&apos;
			films out of a country estate in England, and leaving a correspondingly
			<lb/>
			large number of aborted projects: does Bergman hold the same mystery and leave
			<lb/>
			similarly unrealized projects? He had been such a promoter of his own &apos;family secrets&apos;,
			<lb/>
			had been so flamboyantly autobiographical throughout his life, had had so many
			<lb/>
			(television) films devoted to himself, and so many artist-friends to turn his late scripts
			<lb/>
			into films, that it is hard to see how the need (or desire) for an exhibition could be born
			<lb/>
			from the lack of primary information.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>More promising, therefore, would seem the other initiative associated with
			<lb/>
			Hitchcock: bring together artists inspired by his work, or under the director&apos;s spell, or
			<lb/>
			who might feel provoked into wrestling with his (at times, especially in his native
			<lb/>
			Sweden, oppressive) influence. Such a dialogue may take the form of parody, to shake
			<lb/>
			off with a laugh the pessimism and gloom that pervaded some of his most famous films,
			<lb/>
			or it may want to engage with the raw emotional violence, the physicality, the sheer
			<lb/>
			presence of bodies in his films. It is also worthwhile once more to listen to Bergman&apos;s
			<lb/>
			soundtracks and &apos;see&apos; them as palpably as his images. And audiences who enjoy David
			<lb/>
			Lynch&apos;s Mulholland Drive will surely be drawn into the &apos;mind-games&apos; a film like
			<lb/>
			Persona plays with his characters and audiences alike. After fellow directors have had
			<lb/>
			their say (Bergman is amply present not just in Woody Allen and David Lynch, but also
			<lb/>
			in Andrej Tarkowsky, Eric Rohmer, Robert Altman, Paul Schrader, Atom Egoyan), many
			<lb/>
			of whom have paid tribute in print as well (special journal issues on his 80 th birthday,
			<lb/>
			obituaries in 2007), it is now up to a new generation of filmmaker-artists or artist-<lb/>filmmakers, to
			re-discover Bergman, praise him -or to bury him.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Event and Encounter: the Dispositifs
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>But there may be another way: to try and make Bergman&apos;s films themselves speak the
			<lb/>
			language of the museum, but in the idiom of the contemporary practice par excellence,
			<lb/>
			that of the &apos;installation&apos;, combining object with process, place with temporal duration,
			<lb/>
			and engendering a different relation between viewer and artefact, thanks to the &apos;event&apos;.
			<lb/>
			This then, is the challenge: not to find a home for a homeless artist, nor to make the
			<lb/>
			museum take over the task of a cinematheque, but to bring about a different kind of event
			<lb/>
			and encounter. It necessitates, however, a brief reminder of the very real difficulties and
			<lb/>
			inherent contradictions that confront the moving image inside the museum. The cinema
			<lb/>
			and the gallery space are, both institutionally and philosophically, two distinct, if not
			<lb/>
			antagonistic visual arrangements and spatio-temporal dispositifs, their differences
			<lb/>
			commonly expressed in the juxtaposition of &apos;black box&apos; and &apos;white cube&apos;. Each space is
			<lb/>
			culturally pre-determined, has its own historically grown, but deeply ingrained traditions,
			<lb/>
			following particular architectonic ordering principles or &apos;logics&apos;, which amount to
			<lb/>
			distinct ontologies. Especially the cinematic dispositif requires a unique layout and
			<lb/>
			geometry, in the way screen, auditorium space and projector are aligned in relation to
			<lb/>
			each other, in order for the &apos;cinema-effect&apos; to occur. Often compared to Plato&apos;s parable of
			<lb/>
			the Cave, this cinematic apparatus -many times theorized and deconstructed in the way
			<lb/>
			it is predicated on projection, requiring fixity of spectatorial position and implying a
			<lb/>
			particular distribution of darkness, light and illuminated surface -has long been a key
			<lb/>
			element (along with &apos;montage&apos;) in any thinking about the cinema&apos;s specificity. The
			<lb/>
			apparatus is said to affect the cinema&apos;s psychoanalytic efficacy (the &apos;subject effect&apos; of
			<lb/>
			identification), as well as its ontological consistency (the &apos;realism effect&apos; of ocular
			<lb/>
			evidence and the illusion of physical presence).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The museum or gallery, too, is a specific dispositif. With its white walls,
			<lb/>
			preference for &apos;natural&apos; light, and emphasis on smooth surfaces, it organizes space in
			<lb/>
			such a way that the objects visible to the spectator are both brought close and maintain
			<lb/>
			their distance. The placing and hanging of pictures subtly privileges the upright, forward,
			<lb/>
			eye-level orientation of our gaze, directed at the formation of an &apos;image&apos;, distinctly
			<lb/>
			framed and positioned. Even after Cubism and Surrealism, still paying tribute to the rules
			<lb/>
			of Renaissance perspective, the white wall into which the image is &apos;cut&apos;, allows for
			<lb/>
			generous margins and empty surfaces to surround each picture, while the heavily gilded
			<lb/>
			frames are a reminder of the fundamental difference between the picture, what it
			<lb/>
			contains, the look it retains, and the space that surrounds it. In the museum, there is never
			<lb/>
			any space off-screen, to speak in the language of cinema: the classical oil painting is
			<lb/>
			wholly contained, indeed self-contained within the frame, while much of cinema lives
			<lb/>
			from the tension between off-screen and on-screen, of what the frame delimits, but also
			<lb/>
			creates a passage to, and a desire for: the invisible, but imagined. The film-critic André
			<lb/>
			Bazin famously distinguished the &apos;centripetal&apos; painting frame from the &apos;centrifugal&apos;<lb/>
			cinema frame.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Yet the salient argument to make here is that these apparent incompatibilities, and
			<lb/>
			the many contradictory relations that can be itemized or &apos;problemaitzed&apos; between these
			<lb/>
			respective dispositifs, are precisely among the theoretically most fruitful and in practice
			<lb/>
			most productive factors about the fine arts and visual culture today, not only enabling but
			<lb/>
			necessitating the new kinds of encounter alluded to, as moving images and museums
			<lb/>
			enter into sustained and no doubt permanent contact with each other. Each institution is
			<lb/> &apos;on the move&apos; and in flux, each discourse is undergoing internal transformation, and this
			<lb/>
			for reasons not at first glance interconnected or mutually dependent. Take as one
			<lb/>
			example, the upright forward orientation, the prevalence of the wall, the rectangle cut out
			<lb/>
			like a window: modern art, at least since the 1950s, has often subverted or ignored this
			<lb/>
			arrangement, when one thinks of the practices of Jackson Pollock, Carl André, Andy
			<lb/>
			Warhol, Joseph Beuys and many others. In very different ways, these artists have made
			<lb/>
			the floor, and no longer the wall, the site of display, of bodily-perceptual orientation, and
			<lb/>
			of the &apos;moment&apos; of art.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>More drastic, but also more banal in their everyday self-evidence, are the changes
			<lb/>
			that the cinematic apparatus has undergone: television long ago subverted it, merely by
			<lb/>
			substituting the small screen for the movie theatre, and phosphoric glow for projection,
			<lb/>
			provoking in turn different kinds of re-assertions of the power of the projected image,
			<lb/>
			whether thanks to cinemascope (in the 1950s) or the Dolby surround-sound design (in the
			<lb/>
			1970s). Since then, screens have become both bigger and smaller, but above all, they
			<lb/>
			have become more &apos;mobile&apos;: in their proliferation as monitors on virtually every table-top
			<lb/>
			(at home as well as at work), in their locations (as urban screens, electronic notice-<lb/>boards, in
			airplanes,
			in motor-cars or on public transport) but also embedded in the hand-<lb/>held devices we carry on our
			bodies, as
			music players or mobile phones. It means that the
			<lb/>
			opposition &apos;collective reception&apos; in ranked and regimented seating (cinema) versus
			<lb/> &apos;individual absorption&apos; in a state of solitary contemplation (museum) is also no longer
			<lb/>
			valid, at least not in any absolute way, while the most common experience in museums,
			<lb/>
			notably for the blockbuster shows international museums now habitually organize, the
			<lb/>
			throng of massed visitors (with audio-devices slung round their necks) makes the solitary
			<lb/>
			study of individual works a thing of the past, of another generation (and of another
			<lb/>
			technology).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>The Film Historian as Curator?
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>It is with these questions in mind that I want to introduce the initiatives that a group of
			<lb/>
			scholars and students in Stockholm, Yale and Amsterdam undertook, in order to bring
			<lb/>
			Bergman to the attention of the art world in a new kind of encounter and event. First of
			<lb/>
			all, the teams I assembled, whatever their background or ambitions as filmmakers or
			<lb/>
			installation artists, are working on this project as film historians and media theorists, and
			<lb/>
			despite the fact that both cinema and museum are in flux, the protocols to be observed in
			<lb/>
			each case are no less strict. Thus, one of the important features of the museum today is
			<lb/>
			not so much what it lets in, as the thresholds, limits and conditions of possibility it -<lb/>visibly and
			invisibly -(im)poses. Such an assertion may seem paradoxical, since from
			<lb/>
			Duchamp&apos;s urinal, Warhol&apos;s soup cans and Carl André&apos;s bricks, to Damian Hirst&apos;s shark,
			<lb/>
			Tracy Emmin&apos;s unmade bed and Chris Ofili&apos;s elephant dung, it seems that nothing is
			<lb/>
			being excluded from the museum. But this would be to overlook the extent to which the
			<lb/>
			fine arts in the 20 th century, and the institutions that serve them, have been relentlessly
			<lb/>
			meta-discursive and self-referential. Faced with the &apos;anti-art&apos; onslaught of successive
			<lb/>
			avant-gardes, the modern museum has reinvented itself, by marking -in a myriad of
			<lb/>
			subtle ways -its spaces as deceptively open and fiercely bounded, which is to say, as
			<lb/>
			both liminal and territorial: to be crossed and entered only by guarded acts of negotiation
			<lb/>
			and agreed terms of mutual interference. This liminality and what it implies is a valuable
			<lb/>
			gift the museum can make the cinema, in the sense that it forces it to double itself, and in
			<lb/>
			the process, also divest, divide or subtract itself. As a &apos;natural&apos; space of reflexivity and
			<lb/>
			recursiveness, the museum obliges everything that enters, however banal or precious, to
			<lb/>
			be perceived against a double horizon: that of its unique physical presence, and the
			<lb/>
			special significance attached to its placement (in the here-and-now) also being a dis-<lb/>placement. Every
			act
			and every object is both itself and its own statement, and thus the
			<lb/>
			museum, as it were, by this fact alone, &apos;knows&apos; the cinema better than the cinema knows
			<lb/>
			itself, or rather: the museum forces the cinema to be itself, by becoming more like itself.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		
		<p>One can summarize these turns or acts of displacement under a more general
			<lb/>
			heading, by claiming that the museum &apos;arrests&apos; and &apos;suspends&apos; the moving image -in
			<lb/>
			both senses of these words: with respect to motion and stillness, the moment and motility,
			<lb/>
			and in the legal sense of suspending a licence, an agreement, of suspend someone in his
			<lb/>
			functions or even of giving someone a suspended sentence. If the museum rescues the
			<lb/>
			cinema, it does so at the price of taking it, as it were, into protective custody. In short, it
			<lb/>
			is a holding operation and an ambiguous one at that.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		
		<p>What, then, in the case of Bergman&apos;s cinema, would be the particular forms of
			<lb/>
			arrest, suspension, and displacement -understood, in a preliminary sense, as synonyms
			<lb/>
			for stripping of context, for abstracting from the commodity-form, and for subtracting
			<lb/>
			from &apos;film culture&apos;? The move to the museum would, for instance, subtract from
			<lb/>
			Bergman&apos;s cinema &apos;narrative&apos;, anecdote, but also psychology (and thus &apos;drama&apos;): the
			<lb/>
			very life-blood of his films, one might say. Put differently, Bergman&apos;s cinema enters the
			<lb/>
			museum not as a story-telling medium, nor as a collection of personal themes and
			<lb/>
			obsessions (such as childhood and family, the marital couple, religion or &apos;art&apos;), but as its
			<lb/>
			own double, arresting the medium, its history and specificity, in an extended &apos;moment&apos; or
			<lb/>
			enduring snapshot, and thereby exposing, once more, the cinema&apos;s own &apos;archaeology&apos;<lb/>
			and &apos;ontology&apos;. Respecting the liminality and conditions of possibility discussed above,
			<lb/>
			the different thresholds to be negotiated could be grouped under the following categories:
			<lb/>
			ready-mades and fragments, reflexivity as archaeology and reflexivity as ontology,
			<lb/>
			minimalist relationality and the dispositifs of mutual interference.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Found Object: Ingmar Bergman, the Great Artist
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Feature films, I argued, no less than &apos;found footage&apos; enter the museum as ready-mades,
			<lb/>
			carrying with them the cultural use-values or junk-status of &apos;cinema&apos;. Once we decided
			<lb/>
			that Bergman should not (yet) be given the Hitchcock-Pompidou treatment, there still
			<lb/>
			remained the fact that he was and is a &apos;great artist&apos;. So in what sense can the great artist
			<lb/>
			be a &apos;ready-made&apos;? Major tributes to Bergman&apos;s fame are the parodies his films have
			<lb/>
			inspired, especially The Seventh Seal (by Woody Allen, French &amp; Saunders), Wild
			<lb/>
			Strawberries (&quot;The Düve/The Dove&quot;), but also Persona and The Silence. Bergman was
			<lb/>
			hyper-conscious of the danger of falling into self-parody, and chided both Bunuel and
			<lb/>
			Welles for succumbing to the vice. At the same time, his films are replete with artists:
			<lb/>
			would-be artists and con-artists, tormented artists and sensitive souls, artists as recluses
			<lb/>
			and artists as priapic satyrs, artists as humiliated clowns and pitiful buffoons, artists as
			<lb/>
			prostitutes and artists as pimps, pompous artists and heartless cynics: self-portraits or
			<lb/>
			self-parodies, products of self-loathing or self-idealization? Both, of course, and neither,
			<lb/>
			and therefore constituting the clichés of the post-romantic repertoire of &apos;art&apos;. And yet: a
			<lb/>
			compilation across some 20 films tracing the artist -from introvert boy or &apos;liar&apos; ( The
			<lb/>
			Silence, Fanny and Alexander) to the sarcastic, but worldly-wise church painter Albertus
			<lb/>
			Pictor (in The Seventh Seal) via the aspiring young dramatist and his burnt-out writer-<lb/>father (in
			Through A Glass Darkly), the homicidal-suicidal Johan (in Hour of the Wolf)
			<lb/>
			and the serene actress Emilie Ekdahl Fanny and Alexander), playing her role as mother
			<lb/>
			and grandmother just as professionally as she once did Hedda Gabler or Ophelia -would
			<lb/>
			both confound any sense of Bergman&apos;s artists journeying to eventual &apos;maturity&apos;, and
			<lb/>
			confirms that the director&apos;s view of the artist never changed. As the ready-mades of
			<lb/>
			bourgeois anti-bourgeois revolt, these &apos;portraits of the artist&apos; hold in suspense and arrest
			<lb/>
			for instance, the common trope of Bergman baring his soul, and Bergman as he bares his
			<lb/>
			soul, sharply observing everyone&apos;s reaction.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>The Work: Fragment and Totality
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Bergman has left an oeuvre of such extraordinary depth and epic proportions, so
			<lb/>
			consistent in its recurring motifs and repeated deployment of key actors, yet so diverse in
			<lb/>
			mood, tone, as well as setting, that any ambition other than a complete retrospective
			<lb/>
			would seem a strangely perverse act of homage. Indeed, rather than showing individual
			<lb/>
			films, according to period or genre, preference or popularity, 24-hour Bergman might be
			<lb/>
			the best way to use the museum&apos;s modulated but not strictly segmented time regime, in
			<lb/>
			order to test the fine line between homage and sacrilege. Re-thinking the technical
			<lb/>
			processes of montage, assemblage and collage, we tried to their different meanings in the
			<lb/>
			cinema and in modern art. Surprisingly enough, as we looked for extracts and scenes, our
			<lb/>
			renewed attention to moment and instant, to interval and intermittence, to seriality and
			<lb/>
			succession, to random distraction and free association, became of immense value in
			<lb/>
			looking closer at the films and appreciating their many levels of interlacing internal
			<lb/>
			architectures. Yet the experience of selecting and putting together these extracts has
			<lb/>
			proved another point, and produced another surprise. Bergman is like an earthworm:
			<lb/>
			wherever you cut him, and into however many pieces he is chopped, each fragments is
			<lb/>
			viable, and in the end, makes itself whole again.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Reflexivity as Ontology
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>What cinema shares with the fine arts, and in particular with painting, is a common
			<lb/>
			conception of vision, inherited from Renaissance perspective: that a rectangle of colour
			<lb/>
			and light, framed against a wall, can connote an &apos;open window on the world&apos;. In the face
			<lb/>
			of such an inherently improbable, but deeply held idea (and the sweeping changes that
			<lb/>
			the digital media are rapidly bringing to such assumptions), some of the differences often
			<lb/>
			noted between cinema and museum, such as mobile spectator/ fixed image, versus fixed
			<lb/>
			spectator/ moving image, diminish in consequence. A compilation that concentrates on
			<lb/>
			Bergman&apos;s use of windows -especially when combined with mirrors, frames and
			<lb/>
			doorways -can bring out the painterly composition of many of his scenes, and lead to
			<lb/>
			productive comparisons between theatrical staging in depth, pictorial conventions of
			<lb/>
			multiple planes of action, and cinematic &apos;deep space&apos;. But it also shows how restrictive
			<lb/>
			and &apos;conventional&apos; the window as master trope of human vision actually is, and how
			<lb/>
			adversely it can affect human interchange and communication. More generally, the idea
			<lb/>
			of the cinema as a window on the world is also known as the &apos;realist ontology&apos;, itself one
			<lb/>
			of the key definitions of &apos;what is cinema&apos;, and thus an affirmation of its specificity as an
			<lb/>
			art-form. That Bergman cites the window so often is sign of his classicism, and yet -as a
			<lb/>
			montage of similar scenes readily proves -much more happens when one focuses on his
			<lb/>
			half-open or half-closed doors, his full-length or hand-held mirrors, the moments of a
			<lb/>
			character crossing the threshold from one space into another, or when peering into one
			<lb/>
			space through the doorway of another. Repetition here creates a degree of reflexivity,
			<lb/>
			also with regards to spectatorship: it re-asserts the cinema&apos;s unique architecture of looks,
			<lb/>
			in rooms that often simulate the domestic interiors of bourgeois life, while threatening at
			<lb/>
			any moment to collapse into a claustrophobic hall of mirrors, doubling up on themselves,
			<lb/>
			and giving the spectator no place from which to retain a firm footing, nor to sustain the
			<lb/>
			illusion that s/he might be safely on the &apos;outside&apos;, merely looking in.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Reflexivity as Archaeology
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Bending to the time-constraints and spatial arrangements of the museum as &apos;white cube&apos;<lb/>
			rather than &apos;black box&apos; also produces another kind of reflexivity. The invention of &apos;new
			<lb/>
			forms&apos;, such as short films, montage-sequences, and above all loops and Moebius strips,
			<lb/>
			allowing for repetition within duration, turns out to be the re-invention, as meta-cinema,
			<lb/>
			of early film-forms from the time of cinema&apos;s &apos;origins&apos;: museum reflexivity becomes
			<lb/>
			media archaeology. Signalled clearly in the title of his autobiography The Magic Lantern,
			<lb/>
			Bergman makes frequent allusions in his films to pre-and proto-cinematic devices (The
			<lb/>
			Magician, Persona, Fanny and Alexander). They serve several functions: they inscribe
			<lb/>
			him into a genealogy of pioneers and entrepreneurs of spectacle and vision machines, and
			<lb/>
			they want to emphasize the element of craft, the practical skills and sheer technical know-<lb/>how that
			goes
			with being a filmmaker. But they also emphasize what the museum tends
			<lb/>
			to exclude: the white (and occasionally black) magic of entertainment and showmanship,
			<lb/>
			professing Bergman&apos;s affinity with the &apos;low arts&apos; practiced by the performers, strolling
			<lb/>
			players, manipulators and tricksters who people his films and whose lives of hard work -<lb/>despite the
			ironic
			or sarcastic tone -he seems to salute for their popular touch, as much
			<lb/>
			as recognize their bodily appetites (The Seventh Seal, Sawdust and Tinsel, The Rite).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Perhaps the most important function of these magic lanterns, puppet-theatres,
			<lb/>
			mechanical toys and illusionist contraptions, for our present project at least, is that they
			<lb/>
			are a useful reminder of an alternative genealogy for the cinema itself, not dependent on
			<lb/>
			(bourgeois, museum-friendly) Renaissance perspective and conceit of the window on the
			<lb/>
			world. Instead -while also deriving from the camera obscura -they lead via 18 th century
			<lb/>
			phantasmagorias, &apos;Pepper&apos;s Ghost&apos;, fog pictures, stereoscopy, apparition photographs and
			<lb/>
			spiritist séances, to the wilder shores of &apos;special effects&apos; of today, to 3-D graphics and the
			<lb/>
			immersive spectacles, promised by the new media, and not bounded by the picture frame,
			<lb/>
			nor predicated on the calibrated parameters of distance and proximity, typical of painting
			<lb/>
			and museum display, and instead envelop us in the permanent, ambient &apos;ether&apos; of fantasy.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Minimalism as Relational Aesthetics
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>There would seem to be little that is &apos;minimalist&apos; about Bergman&apos;s work, all on the side
			<lb/>
			of baroque exuberance, or haunted by an equally baroque melancholia and sense of
			<lb/>
			memento-mori. Here, too, the limits and constraints of the museum can lead to new
			<lb/>
			discoveries and a re-appraisal. As part of the &apos;subtractive&apos; turn, the compilation format
			<lb/>
			divests the cinema of narrative telos, and generates instead a different kind of linearity,
			<lb/>
			based on repetition, where a concatenation of moments, taken from their context, can be
			<lb/>
			re-inserted into a different scheme: the more obvious and simple the rules, the more enig-<lb/>matic the
			content
			can become. But also: the more minimal the perceptual perturbations,
			<lb/>
			the more demands are made on the spectator to experience a &apos;work&apos;, in the productive act
			<lb/>
			of giving meaning to perception itself. As gallery artists increasingly rely on works in
			<lb/>
			series, mimetically or intuitively reproducing the defilé of cinema, they also impose the
			<lb/>
			severest of self-restrictions: minute variations, almost imperceptible to the untrained eye,
			<lb/>
			challenge the notion of the discrete image, while nonetheless eschewing &apos;movement&apos;,
			<lb/>
			thereby focussing attention on the rule for generating the work, while highlighting the
			<lb/>
			rule&apos;s inability by itself to structure the viewer&apos;s experience. What would it mean, we
			<lb/>
			wondered, to have Bergman restrict himself to one tonality, one face, one gesture -the
			<lb/>
			way, say, Jasper Johns in the late 1950s painted only in shades of grey -but to do so, ad
			<lb/>
			infinitum? Ten minutes of Liv Ullmann&apos;s face, for instance, from all the films she made
			<lb/>
			with Bergman, or Max von Sydow, looking straight at the camera, from film to film, with
			<lb/>
			minimal variation, but becoming ever more intense. A thought to make one dream, but
			<lb/>
			one that needs a screen as big as a Tintoretto altar-piece, or Holbein&apos;s The Ambassadors.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Dispositifs of Mutual Interference
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Perhaps the most challenging assumption to come under scrutiny, when a filmmaker like
			<lb/>
			Bergman enters the museum, is the cinema&apos;s relation to the body, and especially its
			<lb/>
			engagement with the senses other than vision. Traditionally, the cinema has been
			<lb/>
			regarded as the triumph of the disembodied gaze. It arose, a little over a hundred years
			<lb/>
			ago, when there was no aerial transport via planes, no private motorcars, and the only
			<lb/>
			available mechanized means of transportation was the railway. Well into the 20 th century,
			<lb/>
			then, cinema was a mobile eye: an organ to see and to explore the world with, an eye no
			<lb/>
			longer tied to the body. It could roam freely, make itself invisible, and penetrate into
			<lb/>
			places that were either forbidden, barred or physically out of reach. The disembodied eye
			<lb/>
			was celebrated as a potent intimation of power and omniscience. Voyeurism, that primary
			<lb/>
			motive of assisted vision, is also intimately connected with a form of disembodiment:
			<lb/>
			who could resist the idea of not having to take responsibility for one&apos;s bodily presence in
			<lb/>
			a given space or at a given time, while still enjoying its intimacy? By contrast, visiting
			<lb/>
			the museum, we are inescapably present with our bodies, indeed this is the special
			<lb/>
			pleasure and privilege of being in a museum: sharing the same space with a unique work
			<lb/>
			of art, experiencing the tactility and vibrancy of paint, feeling the urge to touch the curves
			<lb/>
			or surfaces of a sculpture.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Framed within these expectations, Bergman&apos;s films are especially responsive. Not
			<lb/>
			only was he a master in teasing out tactile sensations from black-and-white photography,
			<lb/>
			and able to flood the screen with saturated colour -one thinks of the almost unbearably
			<lb/>
			intense reds in Cries and Whispers. One of the paradoxical effects of the digital
			image
			<lb/>
			having become the norm is that film scholars, too, have been paying more attention to
			<lb/> &apos;embodied&apos; forms of vision, they have spoken of the &apos;skin&apos; of the film (the way
			that
			<lb/>
			Roland Barthes spoke of the &apos;grain&apos; of the voice), noting a new materiality in video and
			<lb/>
			digital media, which leads to a more &apos;haptic&apos; mode of perception and reception on the
			<lb/>
			side of the viewer. If compared to the cinema&apos;s disembodied look, the gallery&apos;s default
			<lb/>
			value is embodied perception), then all manner of aesthetic parameters -I am thinking of
			<lb/>
			relations of size, scale, and detail -call for re-investigation and a deeper understanding.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>A further negotiated disruption or transgression is implied by the entry of sound,
			<lb/>
			and of sound-spaces into the museum, traditionally a site of silence and stillness in both
			<lb/>
			senses of the word. Here, too, Bergman can be seen at the forefront of developments he
			<lb/>
			may not have intended or even condoned. His carefully composed sound, usually integra-<lb/>ted into
			narrative
			and fictional space, can -isolated in the museum and concatenated in
			<lb/>
			the form of a compilation-montage -be appreciated for the special way it affect the
			<lb/>
			spectator bodily, touch the skin, grate on one&apos;s (mental) epidermis, or bring on a shiver of
			<lb/>
			pleasure, anticipating the richly musical cadences with which his actors (de)live(r) their
			<lb/>
			lines, to give illusions of familiarity and intimacy, possibly more to non-Swedish ears.
			<lb/>
			We have chosen &quot;Skin and Stone&quot;, &quot;Cries and Whispers&quot; (Bergman himself obliges) and
			<lb/> &quot;Mind and Brain&quot; to highlight ways in which that heightened awareness of the body in
			<lb/>
			the museum might benefit attentiveness to Bergman&apos;s special genius as a filmmaker.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Threshold, Transgression, Potential Presence
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>We do not want to minimize the transgressive nature of what we are proposing. A
			<lb/>
			filmmaker has the right to the integrity of his oeuvre, this being usually defined by the
			<lb/>
			autonomy of his individual films as coherent and complete works, to be shown exactly as
			<lb/>
			intended. We have no disagreement with such a position. Our argument is as simple as
			<lb/>
			might appear simple-minded. We do believe that there lie hidden in Bergman&apos;s films
			<lb/>
			certain layers of potential (not meaning, but) presence that can be actualized and literally
			<lb/>
			brought to the films&apos; sensory surface, when making the dispositifs of cinema and museum
			<lb/>
			less converge with each other, than mutually interfere with each other, as they do in the
			<lb/>
			form of installations and compilations. The encounter becomes an event, precisely to the
			<lb/>
			degree that the tensions can still be felt, and the seemingly incompatible properties of
			<lb/>
			each &apos;medium&apos; oblige curators to make choices rather than to compromise. Without
			<lb/>
			wishing to claim that somehow this reveals, say, the &apos;optical unconscious&apos; of a director&apos;s
			<lb/>
			work, or even assume that we have been able to distil Bergman&apos;s ars poetica, it does, we
			<lb/>
			believe, teach us something about the cinema -after the &apos;death of cinema&apos;. For besides
			<lb/>
			giving a new generation the opportunity to learn to look at films closely (that is, with all
			<lb/>
			their senses) by doing the kind of patient, labour-intensive and time-consuming work that
			<lb/>
			such compilations and installations require, this -in every sense, labour of love -<lb/>constitutes both a
			new
			form of cinephilia and a new hermeneutics of close reading.
			<lb/>
			Finally, beyond these pedagogical uses, important though they may be for museums as
			<lb/>
			much as for film scholars, the exercise does allow new questions to emerge and thus
			<lb/>
			helps us ask afresh the question of &apos;what is cinema&apos;, as it enters/ if it enters that public
			<lb/>
			space of reflexivity, by which I have defined the museum. Our hope for Ingmar
			<lb/>
			Bergman&apos;s 90 th birthday is that around his work, the avant-garde, the archive and the
			<lb/>
			academy might collectively and in mutual interdependence and even mutual interference,
			<lb/>
			preserve and present what we still have every reason to call -without historical
			<lb/>
			qualifications or technical specifications -&apos;cinema&apos;.
		</p>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
