<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<head>Introduction
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Infection due to Candida species and other fungi have increased dramatically in recent years
			<lb/>
			and are of particular importance because of rising number of Immuno-compromised patients
			<lb/>
			<ref type="biblio">[1]</ref>. Although Candida albicans remains the most common cause of human Candidiasis,
			the
			<lb/>
			frequency of infection attributed to other member of the genus is also increasing <ref type="biblio">[2,
				3]</ref>. This
			<lb/>
			is primarily due to the increase in the number of at risk individuals, particularly those with
			<lb/>
			impaired immunity, such as transplant recipients, cancer patients, receiving chemotherapy
			<lb/>
			and human Immunodeficiency virus-infected patients <ref type="biblio">[4, 5, 6, 7, and 8]</ref>. In the 1980&apos;s
			<lb/>
			Candida albicans accounted for more than 80% of all candidal isolates recovered from
			<lb/>
			nosocomial yeast infection <ref type="biblio">[9]</ref>. Now, Candida albicans accounts for more than 80% of
			all
			<lb/>
			Candida blood isolates in a recent review <ref type="biblio">[10]</ref>.The emergence of Candida species
			other than
			<lb/>
			Candida albicans is a matter of concern in several major institutions <ref type="biblio">
				[11,12,2,13,14,3]</ref>. These
			<lb/>
			species are also shown to have reduced susceptibility to antifungal agents. The frequency of
			<lb/>
			isolation of Candida krusei, Candida glabrata, Candida tropicalis, Candida prapsilosis is
			<lb/>
			steadily, increasing globally<ref type="biblio">[15,16]</ref>.Fungal infections particularly caused by
			Candida species
			<lb/>
			are being detected more frequently in clinical laboratories<ref type="biblio">[17]</ref>.Changing Candida
			<lb/>
			epidemiology and availability of newer antifungal drugs, with different antifungal spectrum
			<lb/>
			means that physician can no longer make therapeutic decision based on broad identification
			<lb/>
			of fungi as yeast and mold<ref type="biblio">[18]</ref>.The conventional methods of yeast identification
			which
			<lb/>
			mainly consist of assimilation and fermentation characteristic are reported to be cumbersome
			<lb/>
			and beyond the expertise range available in local laboratories. In non-specialized clinical
			<lb/>
			laboratories <ref type="biblio">[19]</ref>, especially with resource limited settings, identification of
			yeast and yeast
			<lb/>
			like organisms requires evaluation of microscopic morphology, and biochemical studies.
			<lb/>
			Some unusual yeast may require unique morphological and biochemical studies for
			<lb/>
			identification, occasionally requiring up to 21 days of incubation<ref type="biblio">[20]</ref>.Effective
			treatment
			<lb/>
			requires both, an early diagnosis and facilitates prompt initiation of therapy against fungal
			<lb/>
			infection<ref type="biblio">[21]</ref>.As the traditional methods are tedious and time consuming to perform
			in the
			<lb/>
			routine laboratories, numerous isolation media are available in the market that can identify
			<lb/>
			pathogen within 4-72 hours, depending upon the system<ref type="biblio">[22,,23,24,25,26]</ref>.Several
			brands of
			<lb/>
			Chromogenic media are available for rapid identification of yeast. These special media yield
			<lb/>
			microbial colonies with varying pigmentation secondary substrates that react with enzyme
			<lb/>
			secreted by micro organism <ref type="biblio">[27]</ref>.These media are species specific allowing the
			organisms to
			<lb/>
			be identified to the species level by their color and colonial characteristics. The manufacturer
			<lb/>
			of CHROMagar Candida currently advertise its product as able to detect and differentiate
			<lb/>
			three species, Candida albicans by growth as light to medium green colonies, Candida
			<lb/>
			tropicalis by growth as steel blue colonies accompanied by purple pigmentation diffused into
			<lb/>
			surrounding agar and Candida krusei by growth as large fuzzy; rose colored colonies with
			<lb/>
			white edges, after incubation of 48 hours at 37•C as also reported in several other studies
			<lb/>
			<ref type="biblio">[28,29,30,31,32]</ref>.Detection of Candida on CHROMagar Candida from poly fungal
			specimen
			<lb/>
			also allow direct and more rapid and specific identification of Candida albicans and other
			<lb/>
			spp. <ref type="biblio">[29, 32, 33]</ref>, that could specifically decrease the time required to obtain
			results. Use of
			<lb/>
			chromogenic media in clinical microbiology laboratory for the isolation and presumptive
			<lb/>
			identification of important candida species is easy to perform, requires less time and is cost
			<lb/>
			effective too. In this study our goal was to evaluate the usefulness of CHROMagar Candida
			<lb/>
			for detection and identification of major Candida species with accuracy to reduce the time of
			<lb/>
			identification and its characterization from poly fungal specimens, especially in developing
			<lb/>
			countries with resource limited settings.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Material and Methods:
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<head>Period of Study:</head> April 2006 to September 2009<lb/>
		
		
		<head>Clinical Isolates:
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>A total of 487 yeast strains, including Candida albicans(n=201),Candida tropicalis(n=140),
			<lb/>
			Candida prapsilosis(n=32),Candida krusei(n=30),Candida glabrata(n=21),Candida
			<lb/>
			lusitaniae(n=21),Candida guilliermondii(n=21)and Candida famata (n=21), were isolated
			<lb/>
			from various clinical specimens (n=435) after direct plating on CHROMagar Candida (109
			<lb/>
			urine,1l blood ,81 sputum,22 wound,91vaginal secretion, and 21 peritoneal fluid).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Strain and Media:
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Quality control strains of Candida albicans (ATCC90029), Candida prapsilosis (ATCC
			<lb/>
			2201) and Candida krusei(ATCC6258) taken from ATCC (American type culture collection)
			<lb/>
			and IIDRL lab, Department of Microbiology, University of Karachi. These control strains
			<lb/>
			were first confirmed by using conventional methods including germ tube formation test, and
			<lb/>
			morphological characteristics which includes macroscopic features (morphology, color, size,
			<lb/>
			texture) on SDA, Corn Meal agar with tween 80 and CHROMagar Candida (CHROMagar
			<lb/>
			Candida, France).
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>CHROMagar Candida medium comprised per liter peptone (10gm), glucose (20g), agar
			<lb/>
			(15g), and Chloramphenicol (0.5g), and Chromogenic ix. (2g), PH6.1.This medium was
			<lb/>
			prepared according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions, does not require autoclaving and
			<lb/>
			dispensed into Petri plates after cooling. Culture was inoculated and incubation was done at
			<lb/>
			37°C, the colonial appearance including color, size and textures on CHROMagar Candida
			<lb/>
			were analyzed.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Identification Methods:
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>All samples were first plated on SDA and CHROMagar for 48 hour at 37°C, the production
			<lb/>
			of colour and morphology as described by the manufacturer were recorded and the
			<lb/>
			photographs were taken for the record to follow, for candida albicans the germ tube test was
			<lb/>
			also performed to differentiate between candida albicans and non albicans candida. The
			<lb/>
			colonies from CHROMagar and SDA were plated on Cornmeal agar with tween 80 for
			<lb/>
			colonial morphological feature observed for the production of chlamydospores, blastospores,
			<lb/>
			true hyphae and branched pseudohyphae. The result were again compared with the colonies
			<lb/>
			that were grown on CHROMagar, these colonies from SDA were subjected to Biochemical
			<lb/>
			analysis by API 20C Aux (Biomuriex). Finally the results were again compared with the
			<lb/>
			cultural result and speciation was done. The data suggested that species which were identified
			<lb/>
			by CHROMagar and Cornmeal-tween 80 agar were the same as were confirmed by API 20C
			<lb/>
			Aux. It means that in the presence of CHROMagar it is not necessary to perform germ tube
			<lb/>
			test for candida albicans to confirm, also reported by odds <ref type="biblio">[31]</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Results:
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>We evaluated 487 yeast isolates from 435 clinical specimens during April 2006 to September
			<lb/>
			2009 (Table1). These samples were directly plated on CHROMagar Candida (CHROMagar
			<lb/>
			Candida, France) SDA (Oxoid), corn meal agar (Oxoid) with tween 80 and on CHROMagar
			<lb/>
			Candida and SDA. Colonial growth was observed after 24 hours and 48 hours of incubation.
			<lb/>
			The development of the colony color was noted on CHROMagar Candida, and we observed
			<lb/>
			that the medium better differentiated the color of colonies after 48 hours of incubation, while
			<lb/>
			after 72 hours of incubation a distinct deep color of the colonies was observed. It was also
			<lb/>
			noted that colonial colors of isolated strain were deepened with passage of time and
			<lb/>
			persistence of pigment was also observed on CHROMagar plates after more than 15 days,
			<lb/>
			also reported by Pfaller, Houston and Coffmann <ref type="biblio">[32]</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The yeast cells were identified according to morphology, and color of colony on CHROM
			<lb/>
			agar Candida. Germ tube formation for Candida albicans was done with microscopic
			<lb/>
			morphology on Corn meal tween-80 agar and confirmed by API 20C Aux yeast identification
			<lb/>
			panel (Biomuriex, France), based on assimilation of carbohydrates.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The distribution of colony color on CHROMagar Candida was similar as given by the
			<lb/>
			manufacturer i.e., green colonies of Candida albicans as indicated in(Figure1 C,D), steel
			<lb/>
			blue colonies of Candida tropicalis <ref type="figure">(Figure1-A,B)</ref> accompanied by purple pigmentation
			<lb/>
			which diffuses into surrounding agar by growth, large fuzzy; rose colored colonies with white
			<lb/>
			edges of Candida krusei , slightly white pale pink edges and Small pink to purple colonies of
			<lb/>
			Candida guilliermondii, can easily differentiated from Candida norvegensis which also
			<lb/>
			produces purple color colonies .The edges of the all colored colonies were paler and dark
			<lb/>
			centered and the colonial size was in between 1-5 µm in diameter, also described by Odds
			<lb/>
			and Bernaerts <ref type="biblio">[31]</ref> . The smooth white to light pink colonies of Candida glabrata
			which later
			<lb/>
			become pink <ref type="figure">(Figure 6)</ref> and others spp. of Candida appears off white which includes
			<lb/>
			Candida lusitaniae, Candida famata, Candida Prapsilosis, and Candida rugosa.
			<lb/>
			Ccomparative specificity and sensitivity of CHROMagar Candida (CHROMagar Candida,
			<lb/>
			France) in terms of colonial growth showed maximum sensitivity and specificity with 95%
			<lb/>
			Confidence level in the range of 95.3% -100 % <ref type="table">(Table 2)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>CHROMagar Candida correctly identify 99% of Candida albicans,98%Candida
			<lb/>
			tropicalis100%,Candida krusei,94% of Candida glabrata with accuracy, but for other
			<lb/>
			Candida species other tools of identification for e.g. API 20C Aux along with CHROMagar
			<lb/>
			Candida (CHROMagar Candida, France) should be used for the correct identification.
			For
			<lb/>
			example conventional methods which includes macroscopic / microscopic characteristic, and
			<lb/>
			biochemical profile by API system of identification (gold standard) to facilitate the diagnosis
			<lb/>
			with efficiency and accuracy, should be possible simultaneously so that the identification
			<lb/>
			should be accomplished.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Discussion:
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>In resource limited countries, lack of training, availability of proper reagents, supplies and
			<lb/>
			equipment makes detection and rapid presumptive identification of yeast species quite
			<lb/>
			difficult. In order to reduce the financial burden of the poor patients, these Laboratories do
			<lb/>
			not go beyond the germ tube test and limit their diagnosis to Candida albicans or Non
			<lb/>
			albicans Candida (NAC). The biochemical assimilation and fermentation tests are not used in
			<lb/>
			these laboratories due to lack of resources, expertise and the time required for these tests
			<lb/>
			which increases the cost of mycology cultures <ref type="biblio">[32]</ref>. As a result direct selection of
			appropriate
			<lb/>
			agents for antifungal therapy or prophylaxis becomes almost impossible.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In resource limited countries clinicians have little confidence in the accuracy and quality of
			<lb/>
			laboratory test results. They continue to prescribe costly antifungals without knowing the
			<lb/>
			exact antifungal profile of the infectious agent; thereby they increase the economic burden of
			<lb/>
			the society which also contributes to the emergence of resistant Candida spp. in the
			<lb/>
			environment.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Without diagnostic tools, safe and effective drug treatment, prevention of resistance to
			<lb/>
			antimicrobial therapy, and monitoring of resistance are not possible. In this setting there is
			<lb/>
			always a need of a medium which helps not only in the isolation but also in the identification
			<lb/>
			of the agent at specie level which was confirmed by PCR .The CHROMagar Candida
			<lb/>
			medium was selected as primary culture medium along with SDA and we found it as an
			<lb/>
			appropriate and affordable diagnostics medium in resource limiting setting. The reason is that
			<lb/>
			an approximate cost per culture for complete identification of Candida using SDA, Corn
			<lb/>
			meal agar, and API 20C Aux in Pakistan is around U.S. $15(Pak-Rs.1200), while
			<lb/>
			CHROMagar Candida costs around US $ 3(Pak-Rs.250) per specimen culture, thus it is more
			<lb/>
			economical.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>We also found that CHROMagar Candida, France easily identifies several species of
			<lb/>
			Candida on the basis of colonial color and morphology and accurately differentiates between
			<lb/>
			the three most common species of Candida i.e., Candida albicans, Candida tropicalis, and
			<lb/>
			Candida krusei , this has been also reported by C K Murray and M L Beckius et al <ref type="biblio">
				[20]</ref>. this
			<lb/>
			medium easily facilitate the detection of more than two species in a single specimen, by
			<lb/>
			giving different colored colonies on a plate at a time, and it was also observed that if the
			<lb/>
			specimen was heavily inoculated, it was difficult to differentiate between mixtures of yeast
			<lb/>
			species on single agar plate because of the different color reaction <ref type="figure">(Figure 5)</ref>.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>The specificity and sensitivity of CHROMagar Candida for green color colony of Candida
			<lb/>
			albicans calculated as 99%, for blue colonies with dark center surrounded by grey halo of
			<lb/>
			Candida tropicalis calculated as 98%, and for pink rough and spreading colonies with broad
			<lb/>
			white edges of Candida krusei it is 100%.The CHROMagar Candida (CHROMagar Candida,
			<lb/>
			France) can be used as culture medium for the primary isolation and for presumptive
			<lb/>
			identification of organism in cases where early diagnosis of infections is needed, without
			<lb/>
			doing PCR albicans has also been discussed by odds and Bernaerts <ref type="biblio">[31]</ref> .CHROMagar
			Candida
			<lb/>
			(CHROMagar Candida, France) can also support the growth of fungi, in some cases where
			<lb/>
			the causative agent might be a mold as reported by Beck-Sague et al <ref type="biblio">[9]</ref> .This has
			also been
			<lb/>
			observed in our study that some time we found the mixture of yeast and mold in a single
			<lb/>
			specimen, so this property of medium to support the growth of mold can easily utilized in the
			<lb/>
			laboratory setting.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Conclusion:
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>On the whole it is observed that as the CHROMagar Candida (CHROMagar Candida, France)
			<lb/>
			gives a presumptive identification within 48 hours, preliminary antifungal treatment can be
			<lb/>
			administered with confidence while the confirmed identification is being obtained. In
			<lb/>
			resource limited settings availability of this type of media not only facilitate the provision of
			<lb/>
			rapid patient care, but may also assist to control the rise in antifungal agent resistance by
			<lb/>
			reducing the time taken for presumptive identification of the organism at species level to start
			<lb/>
			the therapeutic regime, by the clinicians as a result CHROMagar directly help the patient.
			<lb/>
			We can conclude that use of fast and accurate diagnostic methods can help in rapid treatment
			<lb/>
			and fast therapeutic management of patients.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure>Fig # 1(A) Candida tropicalis bluish purple colonies(B)the appearance of C.tropicalis
			<lb/>
			after 72 hours of incubation on CHROMagar at 37°C. (C) Apple green color colonies
			<lb/>
			of Candida albicans grown for 48 h on CHROMagar Candida at 37°C.(D) isolated
			<lb/>
			A
			<lb/>
			B
			<lb/>
			C
			<lb/>
			D
			<lb/>
			E
			<lb/>
			F
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<figure type="table">TABLE
			<lb/>
			2.Comparat
			<lb/>
			ive
			<lb/>
			Specificity
			<lb/>
			and
			<lb/>
			Sensitivity
			<lb/>
			of 03
			<lb/>
			different
			<lb/>
			cultural
			<lb/>
			media for
			<lb/>
			Candida
			<lb/>
			Spp.
			<lb/>
			Name of
			<lb/>
			Media
			<lb/>
			Specificity
			<lb/>
			(N=487)
			<lb/>
			Sensitivity
			<lb/>
			(N=487)
			<lb/>
			95%
			<lb/>
			Confidence
			<lb/>
			Level
			<lb/>
			P
			<lb/>
			Value
			<lb/>
			SDA
			<lb/>
			464(95.3%) 467
			<lb/>
			(95.9%)
			<lb/>
			94.5% -<lb/>100%
			<lb/> &lt;0.05
			<lb/>
			CHROMagar
			<lb/>
			Candida
			<lb/>
			479(98.4%) 478
			<lb/>
			(98.2%)
			<lb/>
			95.3% -<lb/>100%
			<lb/> &lt;0.05
			<lb/>
			Corn meal
			<lb/>
			Agar with
			<lb/>
			Tween 80
			<lb/>
			470(96.5%) 463
			<lb/>
			(95.0%)
			<lb/>
			92% -99.4% &lt;0.05
		</figure>
	
	
	</text>
</tei>
