<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<p>Emerging technologies are more accessible, less expensive, and easier to learn than their predecessors.
			<lb/>
			Nevertheless, incorporating them into education remains a challenge. Sometimes faculty members question the
			<lb/>
			utility of new technologies and desire a strategic way to incorporate them into their classrooms that is
			effective,
			<lb/>
			efficient, and worth their time and effort.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Technology integration is an issue at all levels of education, from one learning activity in one classroom to
			<lb/>
			institution-wide programs. <ref type="biblio">1</ref> <ref type="table">Table 1</ref> summarizes a number of technology integration
			models and compares them to
			<lb/>
			eTIME, the emerging Technology Integration Model for Education we have developed. The first three columns
			<lb/>
			provide the name of the model, a brief description, and the source. The next column indicates the level of
			education
			<lb/>
			(for example individual lesson, curriculum) for which the model is suited. The next three columns indicate
			whether
			<lb/>
			or not the model contains the learning problem, references learning theory and/or assists with technology
			selection.
			<lb/>
			The last column indicates whether there appears to be a link between the previous three elements within the
			model.
			<lb/>
			Several of the models do not address learning theory and an understanding of how people learn. In our view,
			this is
			<lb/>
			a critical flaw of technology integration models when the end goal is student learning. Several other models
			lack a
			<lb/>
			strong connection between the choice of a particular technology and learning outcomes. We believe faculty
			<lb/>
			members will have more difficulty using these models to select a technology rationally.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In contrast, eTIME, the emerging Technology Integration Model for Education, explicitly includes the triad of
			<lb/>
			problem, technology, and learning theory. We believe that matching the technology to the learning theory and
			the
			<lb/>
			learning problem/goal is the critical first step in a strategic implementation effort. We have used eTIME
			each year in
			<lb/>
			our technology in education course and have iteratively improved it to encompass the critical facets needed
			to
			<lb/>
			consider when implementing a technology <ref type="figure">(Figure 1)</ref>.
			<lb/>
			eTIME begins by creating a preliminary solution through consideration of technology, theory, and problem.
			<lb/>
			Instructional design methods are then applied to arrive at the final implementation. Real-world examples
			from
			<lb/>
			health science educators are used throughout the paper. At the end of the paper we present an easy to use
			&quot;pocket
			<lb/>
			guide&quot; for health professionals who wish to strategically incorporate technology into teaching.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>To Arrive at a Preliminary Solution, consider these steps:
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Define a teaching or learning goal or problem to solve -Each time you make a change to instruction, you
			<lb/>
			either have an implicit goal you are trying to achieve or a problem to solve. Clearly state the goal or the
			problem for
			<lb/>
			yourself before even considering the technology.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>For example, one of our projects has the goal of providing nutrition education for elementary school children
			in
			<lb/>
			an after-school program. <ref type="biblio">8<ref></ref> The curriculum initially relied heavily on instructor involvement and was
			difficult to
			<lb/>
			implement and sustain. The problem was that children did not want to participate in a written curriculum
			after
			<lb/>
			school because it was not fun and instructors were not interested in formal teaching in an after-school
			setting. Our
			<lb/>
			solution was to design an online game to teach children about nutrition, solving both problems by making the
			<lb/>
			learning fun and not heavily reliant on an instructor. (Other facets of the problem description included the
			content
			<lb/>
			to be learned and how it might be taught. ) By stating the learning goal and/or the problem you can go
			forward with
			<lb/>
			a clear focus, referring back to it during the many design and implementation decisions.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Consider Learning Theory -Every faculty member holds some concepts about how to create a productive
			<lb/>
			classroom environment. Yet many faculty members do not articulate their ideas or compare them to those of
			others.
			<lb/>
			Perusing established learning theories will help faculty name the concepts they hold and point out other
			ideas that
			<lb/>
			may be helpful. When considering how to incorporate a new technology into their classrooms, it is useful to
			review
			<lb/>
			what constructs are successful in supporting student learning so that the best decisions can be made about
			adding a
			<lb/>
			role for technology.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>A dental hygienist taking our technology in education course used Bandura&apos;s social learning theory as a
			<lb/>
			theoretical foundation for her emerging technology project. <ref type="biblio">9</ref> She used streaming video to model patient care
			<lb/>
			behaviors. By designing the video with social learning theory in mind, she tailored her actions in the video
			to
			<lb/>
			encourage her students to imitate her behaviors. Grounding your technology selection in a theoretical
			framework
			<lb/>
			will help you capitalize on others&apos; best practices.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Match technology affordances to the problem -Affordance refers to the way a technology or software can be
			<lb/>
			used and what it allows the user to do or not to do. All technologies have different affordances arising
			from their
			<lb/>
			internal structure and functionalities. <ref type="table">Table 2</ref> lists several more established
			technologies along with some examples
			<lb/>
			of their uses in education. For example, if your goal is for students to collaboratively create content, you
			may
			<lb/>
			consider using a wiki. A wiki has the ability for all students to upload and contribute content in a format
			that is
			<lb/>
			integrated and easily searchable. A wiki allows students to collaboratively edit content, but it would be a
			poor
			<lb/>
			choice for real-time communication, for example, that may be another facet of collaboration.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>On the other hand, if your goal is that students reflect on a series of learning experiences, a blog may be a
			more
			<lb/>
			appropriate tool. A blog affords the learner a way to post or &quot;journal&quot; and allows others to
			comment on each entry.
			<lb/>
			The posts are presented in reverse chronological order so students can collaboratively reflect on their most
			recent
			<lb/>
			experiences or scroll down to go back in time for review.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>To determine technology affordances, look at the technology&apos;s functionality. <ref type="table">Table 3
		</ref> includes questions to think
			<lb/>
			about related to both affordances and sustainability.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>There are several ways to lower entry and sustainability barriers. Working with a group of colleagues who are
			<lb/>
			committed to trying a new technology can spread the workload and has the advantage of leveraging the skills
			within
			<lb/>
			the group. Group strategies might include asking for help from someone who already successfully used a
			<lb/>
			technology or adapting a technology that is already part of someone&apos;s personal life. Team-teaching
			presents special
			<lb/>
			challenges and opportunities. If you team-teach with other faculty, their technology experience and comfort
			level
			<lb/>
			are important and can be an asset or a barrier to successful implementation.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>An example of a technology being implemented based on its affordances was demonstrated by a dental faculty
			<lb/>
			member in our technology course who created and evaluated the use of Flickr to share educational dental
			images. <ref type="biblio">10</ref>
			<lb/>
			The project capitalized on this system&apos;s affordances of sharing images and of tagging images with
			information.
			<lb/>
			Tagging adds keywords to images that allow searching. He created a standardized system for tagging the
			images to
			<lb/>
			be useful for dental educators and shared this with his colleagues so they could tag, contribute images, and
			use the
			<lb/>
			resources for teaching.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In contrast, one of the nursing faculty in the course created a video to teach fundal height measurements and
			<lb/>
			Leopold&apos;s maneuvers to nurses in the undergraduate program. While the video format allowed students to
			watch
			<lb/>
			and listen to each step of this procedure, updating the video because of changing guidelines would be time-
			<lb/>consuming and problematic, making sustainability fairly time-and cost-intensive. An alternative way to
			create the
			<lb/>
			video would be to break it into short segments, thus allowing a single segment to be swapped out if needed.
			While
			<lb/>
			initially more time-consuming to create and edit, it would have made the video easier to update in the
			future.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>As new technologies become available, questions regarding affordances and sustainability may have to be
			<lb/>
			revisited. The act of changing technologies is never completely seamless; the best we can do is to minimize
			the
			<lb/>
			disruption by choosing technologies today with an eye toward updating in the future.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>To Arrive at the Final Implementation, also Consider these steps:
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Formulate behavioral learning objectives -Explicitly stating your learning objectives will help frame the
			<lb/>
			technology implementation and guide your evaluation. Learning objectives can fall in the cognitive,
			affective, and
			<lb/>
			psychomotor domains. <ref type="biblio">11-13</ref> Stated course objectives are one source of learning goals. Other sources include
			program
			<lb/>
			outcomes or certification/licensing guidelines. Often, interpersonal skills, such as team collaboration, are
			not
			<lb/>
			explicitly stated as part of course objectives but are nonetheless valid and important goals to achieve.
			Once you have
			<lb/>
			explicit learning goals, these can be referred back to on an ongoing basis during the design and
			implementation
			<lb/>
			decisions. These objectives will be measured during evaluation of the project and student learning.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Determine learner characteristics -Taking the characteristics of your students into consideration is critical
			for
			<lb/>
			the successful implementation of a new technology. There are a variety of factors that can have an impact on
			the
			<lb/>
			success of your implementation, including students&apos; ability to access technologies, their comfort level
			with and
			<lb/>
			preferences about technologies, and the classroom environment. Although the Pew Center for the Internet and
			<lb/>
			American Life has many different questionnaires, no simple questionnaire applicable to the use of emerging
			<lb/>
			technologies in education exists. An easy way to discover your students&apos; characteristics is to use a
			short survey,
			<lb/>
			possibly hosted by one of the free survey websites. Important questions, along with age and gender, that we
			have
			<lb/>
			used include the following:
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure type="table">What technology devices do you have access to? (Include technologies you are considering using, for
			example
			<lb/>
			an MP3 player if you are considering podcasts)
			<lb/>
			Which technologies are you comfortable using? (Include technologies you are considering using, for example
			an
			<lb/>
			MP3 player if you are considering podcasts)
			<lb/>
			Where do you learn the material? (Check all that apply) Home School Library Car Other
			<lb/>
			Do you have any barriers to using audio and video technology? Yes No If yes, please describe
			<lb/>
			.
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<p>After you&apos;ve implemented, consider these steps:
			<lb/>
			Evaluate the implementation -Evaluation is an integral part of incorporating anything into the classroom.
			<lb/>
			Kirkpatrick <ref type="biblio">14</ref> describes four sequential levels of evaluation, with information gained from each level
			informing the
			<lb/>
			next level of evaluation. Level one focuses on participant reactions. Personal reflection, collegiate
			discussion, and
			<lb/>
			perusal of students comments on course evaluations are other ways to gauge reaction. Valenza et al <ref type="biblio">10</ref>
			examined
			<lb/>
			usage data and reactions from faculty participants. Level two assesses whether learning is different between
			two
			<lb/>
			different conditions. For example, you might consider administering the same exam to a class using the
			technology
			<lb/>
			and a class not using the technology and then compare exam performance. Orientale et al. <ref type="biblio">15</ref> compared
			physical
			<lb/>
			exam performance of first year medical students who had access to videos of specific skills to the
			historical
			<lb/>
			performance of previous medical school classes. Level three addresses whether the students can transfer the
			<lb/>
			behavior, attitude, knowledge, and/or skills learned to a new situation. Level four addresses bottom line
			results.
			<lb/>
			Level four outcomes might include performance on licensing exams, acceptance into residency programs, or
			<lb/>
			publication of a peer-reviewed paper. Prokhorov et al. <ref type="biblio">16</ref> examined the impact of A Smoking Prevention
			Interactive
			<lb/>
			Experience (ASPIRE) on smoking initiation, among other outcomes. In general, the time and energy required of
			the
			<lb/>
			faculty member involved in evaluation increases with each level. However, performing at least a level-one
			<lb/>
			evaluation is critical to inform the next iteration of technology implementation.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>Another component of technology evaluation is looking at usability. Sample questions that could be evaluated
			<lb/>
			relate to use, success with technology, learning, learning efficiency and learning enjoyment.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Applying eTime to your teaching situation -the Pocket Guide
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Many health science fields use concise pocket guides, or cards, to remind practitioners of the most important
			<lb/>
			facts and considerations in a particular situation. In the same spirit, we have created a pocket guide to
			make
			<lb/>
			applying eTIME easier. <ref type="box">Box 1</ref> summarizes the parts of the model using action items. These are presented in a
			<lb/>
			linear list with the understanding that technology implementation is an iterative process that can start at
			any step
			<lb/>
			prior to evaluation.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Box 1 about here
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<head>
			Conclusion
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>The goal of this paper was to give health sciences instructors a review of topics to consider before
			implementing
			<lb/>
			technology in their classrooms. Students in our technology course, many of whom are faculty themselves, were
			able
			<lb/>
			to use these points in creating technology-based learning projects for their students.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<p>In conclusion, we believe that learning needs to be at the center of any technology implementation. Using
			<lb/>
			eTIME provides faculty with a strategic method for the successful implementation of new technologies into
			their
			<lb/>
			classroom environment. It provides a framework for implementing and evaluating whatever technologies could
			<lb/>
			emerge in the future.
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<head>Correspondence
			<lb/>
		</head>
		
		<p>Irmgard U. Willcockson, PhD
			<lb/>
			School of Health Information Sciences
			<lb/>
			University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston
			<lb/>
			7000 Fannin Suite 600
			<lb/>
			Houston, TX 77030
			<lb/>
			Phone: (713) 500 -3627
			<lb/>
			Fax:
			<lb/>
			(713) 500-3907
			<lb/>
			Email: Irmgard.Willcockson@uth.tmc.edu
			<lb/>
		</p>
		
		<figure>
			Figure 1. The eTime Model.
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<figure type="box">Box 1. Pocket Guide to Implementing Technologies
			<lb/>
			* Define a learning goal or problem
			<lb/>
			* Consider learning theory
			<lb/>
			* Match technology affordance to the goal and theory
			<lb/>
			* Formulate learning objectives
			<lb/>
			* Determine learner characteristics
			<lb/>
			* Evaluate the implementation
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<figure type="table">Table 1. Comparison of Technology Integration Models
			<lb/>
			Model
			<lb/>
			Brief Description of
			<lb/>
			Model
			<lb/>
			Reference
			<lb/>
			Content
			<lb/>
			Level
			<lb/>
			Problem Learning
			<lb/>
			Theory
			<lb/>
			Technology
			<lb/>
			Selection
			<lb/>
			Addressed
			<lb/>
			Comments
			<lb/>
			Assure
			<lb/>
			Analyze learners;
			<lb/>
			state objectives;
			<lb/>
			select media and
			<lb/>
			materials; utilize
			<lb/>
			media and materials;
			<lb/>
			require learner
			<lb/>
			participation;
			<lb/>
			evaluate and revise
			<lb/>
			Heinich et
			<lb/>
			al 2
			<lb/>
			All
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			Technology
			<lb/>
			selection not
			<lb/>
			linked to
			<lb/>
			learning
			<lb/>
			problem
			<lb/>
			ICARE
			<lb/>
			Introduce; connect;
			<lb/>
			apply; reflect; extend
			<lb/>
			Hoffman
			<lb/> &amp; Ritchie 3
			<lb/>
			Learning
			<lb/>
			activity/
			<lb/>
			lesson
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			Technology
			<lb/>
			selection not
			<lb/>
			linked to
			<lb/>
			learning
			<lb/>
			problem
			<lb/>
			Generic
			<lb/>
			Considers pedagogy,
			<lb/>
			social interaction and
			<lb/>
			technology
			<lb/>
			Wang 4
			<lb/>
			Learning
			<lb/>
			activity/
			<lb/>
			lesson
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			Systematic
			<lb/>
			Planning
			<lb/>
			Linear model consists
			<lb/>
			of problem statement;
			<lb/>
			learning objectives;
			<lb/>
			technology; rationale;
			<lb/>
			strategies; assessment
			<lb/>
			and reflection
			<lb/>
			Wang &amp;<lb/>
			Woo 5
			<lb/>
			All
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			3D
			<lb/>
			Consists of
			<lb/>
			information;
			<lb/>
			technology and
			<lb/>
			instructional design
			<lb/>
			Liu &amp;<lb/>
			Johnson 1
			<lb/>
			All
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			Technology
			<lb/>
			selection not
			<lb/>
			linked to
			<lb/>
			learning
			<lb/>
			problem or
			<lb/>
			theory
			<lb/>
			RIPPLES
			<lb/>
			Considers resources;
			<lb/>
			infrastructure; people;
			<lb/>
			policies; learning;
			<lb/>
			evaluation and
			<lb/>
			support
			<lb/>
			Surrey 6
			<lb/>
			All
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			SECTIONS
			<lb/>
			Considers students,
			<lb/>
			ease of use and
			<lb/>
			reliability; cost;
			<lb/>
			teaching and learning;
			<lb/>
			interactivity;
			<lb/>
			organizational issues;
			<lb/>
			novelty; speed
			<lb/>
			Bates &amp;<lb/>
			Poole 7
			<lb/>
			All
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			Partial
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			Technology
			<lb/>
			selection not
			<lb/>
			linked to
			<lb/>
			learning
			<lb/>
			theory
			<lb/>
			eTIME
			<lb/>
			Current
			<lb/>
			Paper
			<lb/>
			Learning
			<lb/>
			activity/
			<lb/>
			lesson
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			x
			<lb/>
			Technology
			<lb/>
			selection
			<lb/>
			linked
			<lb/>
			tightly to
			<lb/>
			learning
			<lb/>
			theory and
			<lb/>
			problem
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<figure type="table">Table 2. Emerging Technologies Table
			<lb/>
			Technology
			<lb/>
			Description
			<lb/>
			Examples
			<lb/>
			Educational Example
			<lb/>
			Blog
			<lb/>
			A website by one (or more)
			<lb/>
			authors with entries made in
			<lb/>
			reverse-chronological order
			<lb/>
			WordPress
			<lb/>
			Blogs can foster reflective
			<lb/>
			learning and critical thinking by
			<lb/>
			allowing students to make the
			<lb/>
			changes in their thinking visible
			<lb/>
			Social Network
			<lb/>
			An online community that
			<lb/>
			supports the sharing of your
			<lb/>
			persona, information and
			<lb/>
			ideas
			<lb/>
			Facebook
			<lb/>
			MySpace
			<lb/>
			LinkedIn
			<lb/>
			Ning
			<lb/>
			Social networks can foster
			<lb/>
			community and a sense of
			<lb/>
			belonging, may also support
			<lb/>
			communication to improve
			<lb/>
			learning
			<lb/>
			Wiki
			<lb/>
			A website authored by a
			<lb/>
			community, highly
			<lb/>
			interlinked and searchable,
			<lb/>
			easy to contribute to
			<lb/>
			Wetpaint
			<lb/>
			A class may use a wiki as a
			<lb/>
			collaboratively created
			<lb/>
			repository for the knowledge
			<lb/>
			students are learning
			<lb/>
			Microblogging
			<lb/>
			A microblogging text tool
			<lb/>
			that sends broadcasts of
			<lb/>
			under 140 characters
			<lb/>
			Twitter
			<lb/>
			Microblogging is useful for
			<lb/>
			providing real-time updates,
			<lb/>
			short pieces of content or quiz
			<lb/>
			questions to students
			<lb/>
			Serious Games
			<lb/>
			Electronic games that teach
			<lb/>
			in addition to being fun and
			<lb/>
			motivating
			<lb/>
			Whyville (both game and
			<lb/>
			virtual world)
			<lb/>
			Army of One
			<lb/>
			Games can be used by all age
			<lb/>
			groups to teach a variety of
			<lb/>
			health science content
			<lb/>
			Virtual Worlds
			<lb/>
			An online environment
			<lb/>
			where you are represented
			<lb/>
			by an avatar and you can
			<lb/>
			explore and communicate
			<lb/>
			with others in the world
			<lb/>
			Second Life
			<lb/>
			World of Warcraft (both
			<lb/>
			game and virtual world)
			<lb/>
			Virtual worlds are great for
			<lb/>
			simulating physical
			<lb/>
			environments for learning, such
			<lb/>
			as simulating a doctor/patient
			<lb/>
			interaction in a virtual clinic
			<lb/>
			Content Sharing
			<lb/>
			Flickr
			<lb/>
			YouTube
			<lb/>
			Podcast
			<lb/>
			Allows for easy uploading and
			<lb/>
			sharing of visual and/or
			<lb/>
			auditory content
			<lb/>
		</figure>
		
		<figure type="table">Table 3. Considerations around affordances and sustainability
			<lb/>
			Category
			<lb/>
			Questions to Ask
			<lb/>
			Affordances
			<lb/>
			 Is the technology synchronous or asynchronous?
			<lb/>
			 Can it be accessed and used by few or many people?
			<lb/>
			 Can it be loaded onto a mobile device or do you need a big screen?
			<lb/>
			 Will the users need to download programs or is it a web application?
			<lb/>
			Sustainability
			<lb/>
			 How easy is it to update the learning material?
			<lb/>
			 How widely used is this technology and who supports it? (In general, solutions supported by
			<lb/>
			a user community or a large company are less likely to disappear than those created by small
			<lb/>
			entrepreneurs.)
			<lb/>
			 Can content be exported into another technology if your current solution is no longer
			<lb/>
			supported?
			<lb/>
		</figure>
	</text>
</tei>
